Chapter 37
Chapter 28: “Misfits” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Date Point 10y4m2w2d AV
HMS Sharman (HMNB Folctha), Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches.

Martina Kovač

“Ow, ow ow, OW!”

“And hooold…”

“Fuuuuccckk…. Aargh!”

“There ya go.” Ares released the firm pressure he’d been applying, and Martina sucked in her breath. “You okay?” He asked.

“I was right, this is fucking weird!” Martina declared over her shoulder, before adding “…And painful!” almost as an afterthought.

“Do I gotta remind you again that your job involves measuring dicks?”

“Ugh, you keep bringing that up.” She grumbled. “Yes, that’s weird too! I’ve just gotten used to it, okay?”

“Well, get used to this. Come on, I let you keep your underwear on didn’t I? Believe me, this’d go easier without.”

Martina huffed, and put her head down on her folded arms. There had been a lot of midnight fantasies since she’d first met him that involved Ares. Therapeutic massage was proving to be a painfully effective antidote to all of them, which just wasn’t fair.

She gritted her teeth as he repeated that same press-and-stretch maneuver on another deep knot of tense and damaged gluteal tissue. The deep muscular pain gave way to an intense surface stinging as he stretched the heat-tightened skin as well, working on the patch that was threatening to scar.

“Agh, aagh, aaagh… fuck!"

He cleared his throat. “Sorry… Seriously though, this ain’t all down to your injury. Your fasciae are fucked. Do you even know how to stretch properly when you exercise?"

“Oh God, you’re gonna show me, aren’t you?”

“Fitness and nutrition is my job, remember.” Ares reminded her. He started massaging her obliques. “If I was using the suit wrong, you’d correct me, right?”

“Right, right…” for whatever reason, the pressure and stretching of her obliques was easier to handle. Then again, she probably hadn’t spent most of the last week with them permanently tensed, unlike most of the other muscles in her back. “I’m using my body wrong, huh?”

“Lemme guess. You start off with your jog first and think, like, ‘yeah, this’ll warm me up fine’ am I right?"

He was completely right. “…yeah.”

“Wrong. You’ve gotta stretch out." He shifted to her lats, which drew an immediate involuntary noise of complaint out of her. “Damn, were you just tensed up the whole time?!”

“I was in a lot of pain, okay?!” Martina defended herself. He pushed the breath out of her by applying some unrelentingly firm pressure. When he stopped, she hissed her breath back in through her teeth. “…ow.”

“You’re doin’ great.” He reassured her.

“Gotta… represent for the tech team.”

“Doin’ good so far.” He repeated. “Last time I gave this to one of the Lads, he was fuckin’ crying, the big baby.”

To everyone and in honour of major Powell’s term for them, the SOR Operators were universally known as “The Lads”, even among themselves. It sounded a bit strange in any kind of an American accent, but it was just part of the SOR culture nowadays.

“Oh? Details?”

“Forget it. Bro-code says no, and so does medical confidentiality.”

“Dammit.” She sighed, grimacing as he smoothed out another deep imperfection in her musculature. “So is this bro-code written down anywhere, or…?”

“Sure. In a book of steel, twenty feet tall, hidden in a mountain temple. To even read it you gotta pass the twelve trials of manliness.”

Amused, Martina rolled her eyes. “Keep your head when all about you are losing theirs and - OW!”

“Sorry.”

“-and blaming it on you, that kinda thing?”

“I was thinking more like… y’know, punching bears, cutting down trees, stuff like that. Was that a quote?”

Martina found her laugh. With all his technical talk of fasciae and his obvious aptitude and intelligence for sports medicine, it was sometimes easy to forget that Ares was in other ways quite uneducated. “Rudyard Kipling. You really don’t know it?”

“Should I?”

“My dad said it’s-” She had to stop, as he did something agonizing to her shoulder. “…aaaaargh! FUCK!! What was that?!"

“Your intraspinatus muscle. What’d your dad say?”

“Right, uh… ow… he said, uh, he said Kipling’s popular among combat arms. I figured you’d know it.”

“I didn’t know that.”

“It’s more of an Army thing, I guess. Daddy was a Ranger.” She sighed and rode the next discomfort with little more than squeezing her eyes shut for a second. “I don’t know HOW he’s gonna react when I write him and say ‘Guess what daddy? I got my butt scorched in space!’…"

“And your back.”

“Dude, the - oof! - the booty’s more important.”

“No argument here…”

She laughed, and he pushed through his final ministrations to her left shoulder.

“Okay,” he declared “That’s it for this session. Next one should be easier.”

He handed her a bathrobe and turned around as she stood up. She shimmied on the spot, feeling oddly limber and loose, and noted that her healing burn hurt noticeably less from the motion, too. It wasn’t perfect - she was still feeling sore and bruised from the firm therapy, and frankly exhausted to go with it, as if she’d just gone a round in the boxing ring - but she felt hugely improved.

“Wow!”

Ares beamed his patented goofy smile and bounced slightly in place. She’d always liked that about him, that despite everything that had happened to him and despite his sheer physicality and all the testosterone that must come with it, he was the guy on the team who smiled the most often and who came with the most inexhaustible store of puppyish energy.

“Okay, so what’s next, Doctor Ares?”

“Warm bath, plenty of fluids, and protein.” He replied promptly. “And you limber up properly last thing before going to bed and first thing in the morning."

“Will do. Are we doing this again tomorrow? Only, I have to go stand in front of the old man tomorrow.”

“Aww, man, really? You don’t deserve that.”

She laughed. “Relax. I gave Davison my Crue knowing I was gonna get in trouble for it. I’ll take my lumps, whatever they are."

“I hope he goes easy on you…”

“Ares, Major Powell’s the best commander I ever had. Whatever he decides I deserve, that’s what I deserve. Don’t worry so much.”

Date Point 10y4m2w2d AV
War Platform Lifebringer, Perfection System, The Core Worlds

Grand Fleetmaster Tk’vrrtnnk A’Khvnrrtk

The first thing that struck Tk’v about the human fleet’s deployment was its precision and expertise. Their fleetmaster clearly had an outstanding grasp of operations and tactics, was well-versed in three-dimensional thinking, and had a cadre of shipmasters reporting to him each of whom seemed to have similar insight and competence.

Considering how small the human fleet was, it was doing an admirable job of providing near-perfect orbital coverage, especially over the major population centers. Knowing what he did of human space combat doctrine, thanks to the records from Capitol Station, Garden and the recent skirmish in this very system, he was prepared to call it masterful.

Which was why he was determined that this was going to be a cordial and nonviolent encounter. The presumably-late former fleetmaster Xkk’ of Perfection’s system defence fleet had found himself pushed into a prestigious career dead end precisely because of his fatal tendency to focus on the problem directly in front of him and, frankly, because of his bigotry.

Tk’v prided himself on having avoided those pitfalls.

“Slow the fleet to one-quarter lightspeed and hail the humans.” he ordered. The fleet responded like the well-oiled, battle-hardened machine it was. Years of sporadic clashes along the Celzi borders had kept them tough and lean, and full of only the best officers and crew. None of the bickering political dolts who got sidelined into system defence, this was a Dominion wargroup, the very best. His orders were obeyed smoothly and precisely.

“Channel open, fleetmaster.”

Tk’v nodded to the comms officer, and spoke aloud. “This is Grand Fleetmaster Tk’vrrtnnk A’Khvnrrtk aboard the war platform Lifebringer. Our fleet wishes to approach peacefully."

The reply was a handful of Ri’ in coming. When it did, and he laid eyes on his human opposite number, he was struck by the impression both of age and weariness that the deathworlder was giving off. Tk’v had educated himself extensively on their species, and was quite sure that the human was either unwell, or exhausted.

Most likely the latter, if this was the same ‘Caruthers’ who had so badly confounded Xkk’. And he could hardly blame the deathworlder for physical and emotional fatigue. The man must be feeling a weight of responsibility for what the Hunters had done to Perfection.

“Fleetmaster William Caruthers aboard the destroyer Violent." he replied, confirming Tk’v’s suspicions. A few of the Lifebringer‘s officers exchanged nervous looks, and Tk’v could hardly blame them. ’Destroyer’? ’Violent’? Neither the classification nor name were calculated to inspire confidence in the peacefulness of deathworlders.

“Bellicose names, fleetmaster.” Tk’v observed. “I hope they are not a statement of intent.”

“Only toward our enemies, fleetmaster.” Caruthers replied. “I very much hope we don’t count you among them…?”

“You do not.” Tk’v assured him. “As Grand Fleetmaster of the Dominion Fifth Grand Fleet, I thank you for your defence of this our planet in its time of need, and my fleet stands ready to relieve yours of your vigil. Will you withdraw?”

“We shall.” Caruthers replied. Though he did not know the words and etiquette, his politeness and formality were obvious. He turned to somebody out of his camera’s field of view and nodded. The humans must already have planned for this eventuality, because their fleet smoothly climbed to high orbit and warped as one to the orbit of Perfection’s smallest moon. Tk’v wondered whether his own veteran commanders could have executed the maneuver so professionally.

Considering how short a time humans had been a spacefaring species, their competence was faintly disquieting. He could see why Xkk’ had panicked.

“Transports to enter low orbit and begin the aid drops.” he ordered. “Military vessels to take higher orbit and provide coverage.”

He admitted an expression of satisfaction to himself as his ships matched the humans for precision and finesse. He was determined to be peaceful and constructive, but there was no reason to show the Dominion at anything less than its best. Indeed, the Dominion’s best was exactly what these deathworlders needed to see right now.

He transferred the channel to his desk at the back of the command deck, so as to continue the conversation with a little more privacy and discretion.

“As one fleetmaster to another,” he said, once settled, “I would appreciate hearing your version of events, rather than relying purely on the sensor data. I’m given to understand that the system defence fleet was neutralized by you.”

Contextual information on the screen attempted to analyze Caruthers’ expressions and body language as he composed his reply. They settled on a decision that the human was emoting awkwardness and no small degree of remorse. “…I won’t deny as a matter of historical fact that their sensors were disabled at my order.” he ventured.

“Was that necessary?” Tk’v asked.

“I deemed it so at the time.”

“And now?”

Caruthers glanced outside his camera’s FOV again. Tk’v could only guess what he was looking at. After a few long Ri’, the human spoke again, choosing his words with care.

“I… feel a great sadness and sympathy that this attack has happened, fleetmaster,” he said at last. “But I can’t and won’t accept responsibility for it. In the circumstances I think our decisions and actions were warranted, proportionate and reasonable.”

Tk’v examined the preliminary estimates flowing in from the aid and rescue ships. “The early estimates suggest that the Hunters may have killed more than a million people, fleetmaster.” he pointed out. “And abducted who-knows-how- many.”

“I’m aware.” Caruthers replied. On Tk’v’s screen, the contextual information tentatively hazarded a cocktail of sorrow and determination, though the probabilities were low. Humans had such expressive faces that the software’s second best guess was a blend of anger and remorse. The differences, it seemed, were measured in millimeter variations in the precise tension of dozens of different muscles.

“They were able to do so because, on your orders, the system defence fleet was crippled and defenceless.” Tk’v continued.

“Yes.”

“To protect a single ship.”

“…Yes.”

“And you believe that this was ‘warranted, proportionate and reasonable’, fleetmaster?”

Caruthers sat back in his seat. The translator gave up on trying to read his expression. “In the circumstances,” he stressed, “with the knowledge available to me at the time I made the decision - yes.”

“This event is going to harm your species, you know.” Tk’v pointed out.

“Thank you for the warning, Fleetmaster,” Caruthers replied. “But - from one commander to another, as equals who should be allies against our mutual enemies - I must ask what you would do if your species was threatened with extinction. What price would you be willing to pay?”

Tk’v did not reply. Instead, he ran a hand thoughtfully down the length of his nose, and nodded. “…If you are willing to lend your help a while longer,” he suggested, “we could use an out-system patrol. Your ships have the speed and stealth to perform admirably in that role.”

“Communicate your orders, and I will see them done to the best of our ability.” Caruthers promised.

Tk’v outlined in brief what role the humans would be performing - to loiter silently in the system’s outer icy object halo and serve as a front line of warning should the Hunters return, and to alert the fleet of incoming merchant vessels.

Caruthers listened earnestly and alertly, only speaking to first clarify, and then confirm what he was being asked to do. “We’ll see to it,” he declared once briefed.

“Thank you.” Tk’v sketched a gesture of respect and gratitude. “And… I extend an open invitation for you to inspect my ship, once the situation is controlled.”

Caruthers betrayed only a moment of calculation. “Thank you. I gratefully accept.”

“Carry out your orders.”

“Aye aye, fleetmaster.”

The human ships were already aligned and maneuvering. Tk’v had barely closed the line to Violent before they went to warp, displaying an alarming acceleration profile. Tk’v’s fastest scout ships could only barely have matched them, and he very much doubted that Caruthers had shown their full capability.

He turned his attention away from them for now, and toward the surface of Perfection. There was a lot to do.

Date Point 10y4m2w3d AV
**HMS Sharman (HMNB Folctha), Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Major Owen Powell

“Send her in.”

Considering she was probably still enduring some lingering tenderness from both her injuries and Warhorse’s thorough rehabilitative ministrations, Kovač wasn’t showing an iota of it. She entered Powell’s office with parade-ground perfection, not a hair out of place, not a ribbon misaligned. Her left-face, attention and salute were all razor-sharp.

“Sir, Technical Sergeant Martina Kovač reports as ordered.”

Dressings-down required Powell to look for any imperfection, however tiny. Kovač stood rock-still and expressionless as he circled slowly around her, looking for the slightest blemish and finding none. That was a relief - he knew in his heart that he’d have done the exact same thing in her situation, and would have hated to make this telling-off any more severe than it had to be, especially not over a triviality.

She held the salute as he circled her, and only snapped it back down after he had returned to his seat, returned it, and slowly lowered his own hand.

“Technical sergeant Kovač, do you know the purpose of this meeting?” He asked, lightly.

“Yes, sir.”

“Normally, Kovač,” he said, “I expect NCOs to be enforcers of the rules, rather than breakers of them.” She knew better than to respond to what had not been a question, so he didn’t draw the pause out for long. “I would be interested in hearing your explanation.”

“Davison might well have died, sir. I believe that explanation suffices.”

Kovač was experienced and intelligent. Rather than playing it cagey she was appealing to an age-old reality of war, which was that the rules sometimes had to bend, especially in the face of suffering. Truth be told she was right - the explanation did suffice.

Nevertheless…

Powell nodded. “Certainly from what I gather he was looking at permanent disfigurement and disability.” He said. “In light of which your actions are entirely understandable. I might even say commendable….” He paused, then delivered the inevitable “…However. I must find that they were not acceptable.”

“As NCO in charge of suit systems one of your principal duties is to ensure that all SOR personnel, yourself included, are mission ready at all times. The use of Crue-D is restricted to SOR not only for that reason, but also because our supply of it is so limited. We simply do not have enough to administer to every wounded man and woman in all the allied services who suffers a grievous injury. I know you understand this rationale. Much as I appreciate that it’s difficult to be cold when faced with suffering like that, the restriction exists for a reason. Do you understand?"

“Yes, sir.”

He picked up a folded piece of paper. “In light of the circumstances, I have written this Letter of Counseling,” He said, handing it over, “Which shall be maintained in your Regimental records until such time as I see fit to dispose of it. This is not a punishment but it is a stern warning and it is evidence, which you should not compound with further incidents. Do you understand?”

“Yes sir.” Kovač was good at not giving anything away, but Powell was looking for the very subtlest of tells, and decided that she was receiving exactly what she had known was coming and was prepared to accept.

“Read it.”

She did so, diligently, and signed it after Powell had outlined the assorted legal necessities.

“Very well.” Powell stood, rounded the desk and leaned against it. “Just a parting comment, and this is more… informal.” He added. Kovač didn’t break posture. “The ideals of the SOR are Humility, Service and Selflessness.” He reminded her, not that he needed to. Everyone in the Regiment knew the ideals. “Calculated gambles with your career for what you think is a good and justified cause, well… If, Heaven forfend, you should ever find yourself needing to make a similar choice in future, I want you to remember that the regiment needs you, Kovač. We have a lot of talented people here, and they need both your expertise… and the example you set.”

Her composure finally showed a minor flaw - she blinked. “…Yes sir.”

Powell made a satisfied ‘hmm’ and returned to his chair.

“Technical Sergeant Martina Kovač, you are dismissed.”

Martina Kovač

Warhorse was loitering a respectful but nearby distance from the major’s office. She’d protested that he needn’t: he’d insisted.

“How’d it go?” he asked, following slightly behind her, given that the base’s narrow hallways and his own bulk prohibited side-by-side perambulations.

“I got exactly what was coming to me.” Martina told him, allowing herself a satisfied smile. Powell’s veiled compliment at the end there had done much to lift her spirits. It was good to know that the old man had disciplined her out of obligation - like everybody else in the unit she was slightly in awe of him, and knowing that he was as much on her side as he could be in the circumstances was a real boost.

“That’s… good?” Adam hazarded.

She smiled and nodded. “LoC.”

“That’s still a punishment…” Ares pointed out.

“You’ve never had one?”

“Not yet.”

“You will.” Martina predicted. “Everybody gets one sooner or later and, hell, that was nothing. Believe me, it could have been a lot worse…” She stopped and turned to him. “But y’know what? I saved a guy’s face, and maybe his life. Fucking. Worth it.”

“…Feels good, don’t it?” Adam agreed.

“Yup. Just need to heal up and I can call this one a win.”

“Oh, yeah. About that.” he said. “Got a decision for ya.”

“Shoot.”

“Okay, so we can keep on with the rehab like we have been, or we could go Crue-assisted.” He said. “It’ll go twice as quick, but it’ll hurt more.”

Martina sighed. She was getting kinda sick of pain. Which in fact meant that there was no sense in prolonging it.

“Do you know what body-slamming into red hot metal feels like?” She asked. He shook his head. “I do. I can handle the Crue regime.”

He grinned. “Attagirl.”

Date Point 10y4m2w3d AV
North Clearwater County, Minnesota , USA, Earth.

Xiu Chang

Allison had a musical laugh - it started deep inside her and bubbled up like water. It was a nice compliment to Julian’s filthy throaty chuckle. Perfect for drawing out of them with campfire stories after sunset.

“Oh my God, really?” You couldn’t smell it or anything?"

Xiu shrugged with a faintly embarrassed laugh. “I didn’t know what alcohol smells like! And uh… Yeah, Talamay is, well…. Actually it’s about as strong as this beer." she waggled the bottle for emphasis. Beer had come as a surprise, considering that the only other alcoholic drinks she had to compare it to were red wine and Talamay. She hadn’t expected cold, fizzy and bitter to translate to something she enjoyed, but in fact once she got past that and found the wheaten and even fruity flavors lurking underneath she’d converted, much to Allison’s delight.

Julian was poking at the burning wood with a stick, assessing it for when they could put the meat over it. She could see his teeth twinkling in the firelight.

“How much did you have?” Allison asked.

“Uh…” Xiu put her head back and stared at the stars, thinking. It was nice to imagine that one of them was Gaoyn, even though she knew that particular sun was much too far away to be seen by the naked eye. “We got so used to how I drank more water and had a bigger appetite than the Mothers that… well, they were drinking shot glass sized measures, and I was having it in more like a highball glass.”

“And Gaoians really don’t get drunk?” Julian asked.

“No. They just like the taste.”

“How does that work?” Julian wondered. “It’s the same solvent and they’re not that biologically different to us… it’s got to get into their bloodstream, right?"

“Maybe. I don’t know.” Xiu shrugged. “All I know is, they don’t get drunk. They were all kinds of surprised when I started giggling and stumbling around and then fell asleep.”

Allison made a snrrk sound and aborted the swig she’d been about to take of her own beer.

“You’re a lotta fun when you’re drunk, though,” she noted.

“I’m fun when I’m sober too!” Xiu objected.

“And even more fun when you’re drunk!” Allison nodded. Her grin broadcast pure teasing.

Xiu shot her a mock-bitchy pout, which Allison returned and they spent a few seconds pulling increasingly silly faces at each other before Xiu pulled out a trick she hadn’t done since she was a little girl and touched the tip of her nose with her tongue while squinting.

Whatever the subconscious rules of their completely impromptu game were, she considered it a win when Allison’s splutter and laugh ruined her next attempt.

“Penalty! Finish your drink!” Xiu ordered her.

“Awww! …Yes ma’am.”

“Good girl.” Xiu loved that little back-and-forth. Out of solidarity, she finished her bottle along with Allison.

“More?” Julian offered. He reached to his right and knocked on the cooler full of ice water and beer bottles.

Allison shuffled up next to Xiu. “I think he’s trying to ply us with drink,” she observed.

“I think he is!” Xiu agreed. “…I say we let him.”

“Yeah?”

“Yeah.”

“Well alright! Ply away, Etsicitty.”

“Yes ma’am!”

Xiu smiled to herself as he selected two fresh cold bottles from the cooler and accepted the ‘good boy’ this earned him with a quiet smile. Apparently happy that they were ready to cook, he also grabbed the tupperware with its garlic and lemon chicken breasts and flipped them onto the metal grill where they hissed and steamed beautifully.

“…I’m going to miss this.” Xiu decided, looking around. Once upon a time, she would have thought that being in the woods after sundown surrounded by trees and animal noises would have been terrifying. Instead, the house and property that Julian had inherited from his grandfather felt cozy, in the little stain of firelight. “I love it here.”

“We’ve got another week before we have to leave, babe.” Allison told her.

“And you get to fly a spaceship." Julian pointed out. “I love this place too, but come on, tell me you aren’t excited.”

“…A little bit.” Xiu admitted, taking refuge in massive understatement. She’d found time to call home and talk to her parents during the week, and had found it easier with some distance and with Julian and Allison there for support. Hearing the envy in her brother Wei’s voice had been delicious, which was so wrong of her, but still…

“Liar.” Allison accused fondly. “You can’t wait.”

“Okay, okay, sorry!” Xiu laughed. “You’re right.”

“What’s there left to do anyway?” Allison asked.

“Nothing.” Julian replied. “All the jobs are done. We’ve got a week to relax and be free.”

“So that’s why you suddenly decided to celebrate." Allison snapped her fingers. “Shoulda guessed.”

“So, um… what are we going to do for that week?” Xiu asked. It was dawning on her that her life had been so driven by objectives over the last several years that suddenly having nothing to do was actually a daunting and alarming prospect.

“Uh…” Julian hesitated. “…Actually, I don’t know.”

They looked at Allison, whose expression was suddenly that of a woodland creature staring at the lights of a speeding truck. “Uh… we could…?”

They sat in mutual awkward cluelessness for about ten seconds before Julian finally laughed. “Seriously, do we-? Do none of us know how to just take a load off?"

“I… guess not.” Xiu said.

“Hey, we do!" Allison disagreed. “Movie nights?”

“Every day for a week?” Julian asked. “That much Disney might kill a man!”

“You like Disney!" Allison frowned at him.

“Ever heard of too much of a good thing?”

“Well okay mister,” Xiu challenged him, “Come up with an idea.”

Julian turned the chicken over, thoughtfully. “Actually… I always wanted to see Yosemite.”

“The national park?” Allison asked.

Julian laughed. “No, the cartoon cowboy,” he snarked. Allison rolled her eyes and flipped him the bird with a wry expression, so he leaned over and gave her a kiss. “How about it? Quick road trip, visit some places we’ve always kinda wanted to…?”

He looked at Xiu. “Whaddya think?”

Xiu blinked, desperately trying to think of somewhere she wanted to go. Her parents had always talked about visiting the “old country” despite both of them having been born in Canada, but she sensed that maybe places outside of North America weren’t an option.

She selected the first thing that came to mind. “Um… I don’t know. Vegas?”

“Okay. That’s not too far from Yosemite, either.” Julian nodded. “Al?”

Allison tugged her phone out of her pocket, and for the fiftieth time Xiu reminded herself to inquire just where the hell she found jeans with useful pockets. “Sec’.”

Julian and Xiu traded a confused frown as she Googled something.

“Al?”

“It’s Memorial Day this week, right? Which means…” Allison lowered her phone, grinning hugely. “…The Carnaval San Francisco is this weekend.”

“That sounds pretty easy. Fly to Vegas, day on the strip, rent a car and drive to Yosemite, then to San Fran, return the car there and fly to Omaha.”

“Can we afford that?” Xiu asked.

“Julian and I got paid by the abductee repatriation program for the work we did on Kirk’s ship.” Allison explained. “We can afford it.”

Julian turned the chicken over again. “Hell, if all this legal shit wasn’t threatening the house, we wouldn’t need to take the Byron contract. I mean, I’d still want to-" he added, before Allison could say anything, “but we wouldn’t need to."

Xiu looked back at the house. “So we fixed it up and now we’re just… going away?”

“We can enjoy the fruits of our labors for a day or two.” Allison assured her. “But I like this road trip idea! We were gone for so long and we’ll be leaving again, I think we should at least try to, uh…"

“Reconnect.” Julian suggested.

“Yeah!” Allison nodded.

Xiu’s own attempts at reconnecting had been disastrous. Her old friends had all shown up with an assortment of hugs, chocolates, cards and a beautiful red leather phone case decorated with a hand-painted golden heron from her best school friend.

She’d promptly not heard from any of them again after that. Xiu Chang, living ghost - remembered fondly, but everyone had already mourned her and moved on. Having her pop up alive again, ten years later and five years too young thanks to the effects of stasis… It had been too awkward for everybody involved.

She decided not to mention her doubts that any of them could really connect any longer. Allison was far too headstrong to be gracefully talked out of something she was enthusiastic for, and in his own quiet way Julian was even more tenacious still.

Besides… Xiu was self-aware enough to know that she was a natural introvert, and she was feeling the familiar inertia of all introverts being pulled on by a more extroverted personality like Allison. It was counterbalanced by the knowledge that Al was entirely correct, and that she would enjoy herself, if only she allowed herself to be led.

“Fine, fine!” She smiled. “Let’s do it.”

Julian turned the chicken over, then clicked his tongue irritably. “Forgot the plates.”

“I’ll get them.” Allison sprang to her feet and headed back indoors.

“It’s ready?” Xiu asked. She crawled forward to get a closer look “That was fast.”

“Not yet.” Julian said. “It’s uh… gonna need a while longer yet…”

“Smells delicious.” Xiu turned toward him and suddenly became aware of just how close they’d unconsciously gotten. “Um…”

There was a long, hopeful moment where every detail became crystal clear - the way his breath was shaky in the inhale and he didn’t exhale at all: the supple play of the muscles in his throat, the way his mouth opened slightly, the way she could see, up close, that he was longingly watching her lips.

Her own expression was probably a perfect mirror image of his.

He turned his head slightly, called “…Al?” and the moment fell apart. Not for the first time, Xiu sat back and tried not to resent Allison for her ‘ask first’ policy. Julian sagged, sighed out his caught breath and cleared his throat.

Allison’s voice floated out of the kitchen window. “Yeah?”

“…Never mind.”

“What?”

“Never mind!”

“…Okay!”

Julian sighed and, for something to do, he flipped the meat again. “…Dammit.”

Xiu self-consciously tidied some hair out of her face. “Um….are we…?” she began.

Julian smiled for her. “I’ll talk with her.” he promised. “I just… ” He raised his hand to gesticulate something, but whatever idea he’d been about to express, the words clearly eluded him.

Somehow, though, Xiu knew exactly what he meant. She would have replied, said something, except that Allison chose that moment to push the screen door open with her butt and emerge from the house carrying plates and cutlery in one hand and a bowl of mixed salad in the other.

“So!” she said, without preamble and apparently too eager to start planning their trip to notice Xiu’s and Julian’s awkwardness. “Vegas, huh?”

Xiu looked to Julian, who sniffed a silent laugh, smiled, shook his head and returned to tending the meat.

“…yeah.” She said. “I had this dream one time…”

Date Point 10y4m2w3d AV
Starship Negotiable Curiosity, Cimbrean system, the Far Reaches

Bedu

What surprised Bedu was how businesslike the humans were despite their considerable discomfort. They were all complaining and groaning now… but the moment the word arrived to stand up and prepare for boarding, they had immediately laid out their equipment neatly in plain sight and had then stood against the wall of the ship’s common area while the ship came to a relative halt and prepared to be boarded.

When the unmistakable sound of the airlock cycling began, they turned, pressed their hands to the wall above their heads, and waited. Bedu was at a loss as to why, but his speculation was soon answered when, once the lock cycled, five more humans in that thick space armor of theirs bustled efficiently onto his ship.

In any other situation he might have used the term ‘brandishing’ their weapons, but in fact they were far too clinical and workmanlike for that word to apply. Those guns were being held in the tight, snappy grip of elites who knew exactly how to use them, and who didn’t need to wave them around to draw attention to the possibility of future violence.

There was a short, tense and efficient interlude as each of his captors’ heads was subjected to a scan of some kind. Only once all four had been pronounced ’green, whatever that meant, did they relax. The weapons were put away, the body language changed. Smiles and hugs and alarmingly physical gestures of affection were roundly shared. In that second they went from utterly professional killing machines to the very best of friends, reunited and excited about it.

One of them remained aloof from the cycle of affection. Not that he was standoffish - quite the reverse, he welcomed Rebar, Titan, Snapfire and Starfall with obvious affection, but it was a more… detached affection.

The Corti had no words for ‘fatherly’ or ‘brotherly’.

Bedu soon found himself under the taciturn care of one of the smaller humans, referred to by the others as ‘Highland’. Two others, both of whom were behemothic slabs of muscle laden with an alarming amount of equipment, seemed to be the medical experts, and they rushed to attend to their exhausted comrades. Bedu could understand why - over the course of what they called a “week”, those four men had gone from being imposing forces of physical force, to groaning statues who barely moved except when compelled to by need of nutrition or duty change.

Their predicament was an effective antidote to any notion that humans were invincible. Greatly more durable than anybody else could ever hope to be, yes, but Bedu had spent a week watching them slowly fight a losing battle with their own equipment. They were people to him now. Nice people even: Courteous, clever, conscientious people whom he was forced to watch suffer.

Even for Corti, that was an uncomfortable situation.

The slightly aloof one, whom he took to be the leader, approached him once things had settled down. He was among the smallest of them, but still easily out-massed Bedu several times over.

“Bedu?” he asked.

“Yes.”

The leader nodded. “My name’s ‘Stainless’. You’ve been detained for questioning as a witness in a matter pertaining to the freedom and security of the peoples of Earth and Cimbrean, and of all humans." he announced, formally. “Sorry for the inconvenience.”

“As it happens, I’ve rather enjoyed the inconvenience.” Bedu stood. “Besides, this detention is legal so long as you reimburse me for my time…”

“That wouldn’t be my responsibility.” Stainless informed him. “But everything should be above-board and legal, yes.”

“Excellent…. Are your subordinates going to be well? They seem to have suffered rather badly during the flight.”

Stainless glanced over at his men.

“They’ll be fine,” he said. “Thank you for your concern.”

“So what happens now?” Bedu asked.

There was a lurch, and the ship chimed its usual alert sound for accelerating into a re-entry.

Bedu inclined his head. “The planet Cimbrean, I presume?”

“That’s right.” Stainless nodded. He exchanged a few quiet words with Titan that Bedu didn’t catch, and gave the (presumably) younger man a pat on the shoulder as he staggered and groaned his way forward to help with the re- entry.

Bedu excused himself and took inventory of his belongings, making sure they were all put away and that he had memorised their exact position. He doubted that he would come back to find anything missing, but it would at least be nice to know if they had been moved or searched.

The landing wasn’t as smooth as Mwrmwrwk would have managed, but it was by no means a bad one. In fact, humans being the high-gravity species they were, and capable of handling really quite serious jolts, they probably felt it was perfectly smooth.

Through the wall, Bedu heard Hkzzvk bleat in alarm. Snapfire called something comforting along the lines of “it’s okay buddy, we just landed!” and Hkzzvk’s panicked noises immediately ceased.

Rebar, Titan, Snapfire and Starfall disembarked first, though Starfall was leaning heavily on the largest of his comrades, and Snapfire had to be carried, slung across the shoulders of the second-largest, whose careful footfalls still made the deck plating groan and protest. Bedu watched with mingled awe and disbelief - Snapfire had struck him as being so heavy that even medium stevedore drones would have struggled with his mass. While the feat certainly didn’t look effortless for his comrade, neither did it look like it was pushing his limits.

Bedu and Hkzzvk were carefully shepherded down the ramp by Stainless, Highland and one of the large ones, whose moniker Bedu had not learned. They were met at the bottom by a consignment of humans not wearing armored pressure suits, but instead clad in looser and clearly more comfortable working garments. These were still armed - a ludicrous consideration given that either one of them was comfortably strong enough to dismember anybody who wasn’t human - but the weapons were small, and holstered.

“This way please.” one of them said, waving his hand toward a nearby vehicle. Closer still, the four aching SOR men were being aided onto a transport whose rear step was almost brushing the ground.

Bedu looked around. Cimbrean was a pleasant planet, but there was something… strange about it, that he just couldn’t quite identify. Maybe it was the humans themselves - their every movement seemed faintly awkward, as if they weren’t quite walking naturally. Of course, they wouldn’t be, would they? Cimbrean’s gravity was rather higher than Bedu’s native norm, but must be much lower than Earth’s.

Or maybe it was the auditory landscape. Corti ears were large and sensitive, well adapted to the comparatively low atmospheric density of Origin. In Cimbrean’s denser air, every noise was a little louder and a little deeper and they carried distant hints of shouting, construction work, traffic, and alien laughter. Only that last one was an unfamiliar sound of course, but the cadences and sheer business…

Hkzzvk provided the answer. He trudged down the ramp, shying away from the humans and glancing nervously around as if looking for somewhere to run, but as he always did whenever they landed, he paused and took a deep breath.

He promptly buried his nose in his hands, croaking aggrievedly to himself.

“Hkzzvk?” Bedu asked.

“This planet reeks." Hkzzvk explained.

Corti had very little to speak of in the way of a sense of smell, so Bedu deferred to his crewman’s superioriority in matters olfactory. “In what way?”

Hkzzvk raised his head and his nostrils flared. “It smells of predators.” he decided. “and … urgh, I don’t know what most of these smells are, but I don’t like them.”

That would be it. Weak as Corti nasal acuity was, the pheromones and scents on the air would still be present on a subconscious level, informing his mood. He nodded, satisfied that the mystery was solved.

“Well,” he said. “All the more reason to be done with this interview and get on our way.”

“What about our employers?” Hkzzvk asked.

Corti didn’t smile often, but when they did it was usually because they had scored some small moment of empowerment. Bedu allowed himself an unabashed expression of triumph, and borrowed a human word of unmatched communicative potential.

"‘Fuck’ our employers," he said.

Date Point 10y4m2w3d AV
HMS Sharman (HMNB Folctha), planet Cimbrean, the Far Reaches

Martina Kovač

Anybody who knew the “Lads” knew they weren’t superhuman. Absolutely pushing back the limits of what ‘human’ could mean, yes, but it was difficult to be in awe of somebody when you regularly saw how much pain, inconvenience and indignity they suffered through.

Ares had put his finger on it - Martina was a bio-mechanical expert who had more academic training than most civilian surgeons and a broad role covering absolutely everything about the life-support functionality of every EV-MASS they had, including the ones waiting in reserve for qualified Operators who could wear them. It fell to her to dig through feedback and medical reports diagnosing the most minor of concerns with the suit and liaising with the Lads themselves on their own fitness and suit-readiness. It fell to her to sign off on every life support pack’s fitness for use, and it fell to her to keep the suit techs properly briefed on any concerns that needed addressing.

She loved to boast to her friends and family that she was in charge of a whole team of spacesuit experts, but the unglamorous reality was that many of the suits’ most important systems were below the waist and so, as Ares had pointed out, it fell to her on a monthly basis to intimately measure all of the Lads, and that was only the most minor of the several vital responsibilities she had that all involved the pelvic anatomy.

Put bluntly she had to think a lot about how much the guys pissed and shit, both in terms of frequency and in terms of volume. Those inelegant metrics were thoroughly effective at grounding her estimation of them all. It was a bit like knowing the directory of Spiderman’s porn folder, or which was Wonder Woman’s preferred brand of tampon.

At least her back was almost completely pain-free by now, thanks to some aggressive therapeutic massage and Crue-D treatment. Warhorse had declared that he wasn’t going to be able to stop the burn from leaving some permanent scarring, but when she’d examined it over her shoulder in the mirror, she’d decided that while the white mottling and dimpling down her right flank and buttock wasn’t pretty, it was still much better than she’d feared.

This was good, because today wasn’t a day for limping around. At least, not for her. When Vandenberg, Blaczynski, Sikes and Akiyama were delivered to the suit shop, they were practically stretchered in, and every single one of them was gaunt and pale with fatigue and cramping muscles.

For a change, pumping in the ice-cold water that was vital to persuading their midsuit layers to relax and shrink so that they could be removed produced no complaint. Getting the suits off was much more difficult than usual because the guys couldn’t pull as hard as they normally would, but off they came in the end. In fact in Titan’s case, they only freed him by getting Burgess to help with heaving on him - Ares was too busy lifting Sikes out of his suit and getting an IV into him.

Just in case Martina was still harboring any lingering doubts about how rough the Lads really had it, the stench was unbelievable. Bozo, who had been left sitting obediently in the corner waiting to be introduced to his new friends, promptly sneezed, shook himself and got the hell out of there with his tail between his legs. Martina envied him.

Fortunately, she didn’t have to deal with actually cleaning the suits - that was for the techs - but body biochemistry was absolutely her concern, so she told her nose to shut the fuck up and gathered what she needed from the the suits’ sewage processors, briskly took the needed blood samples, and excused herself to the safe atmosphere of the lab.

From there, while the samples were spun, had lasers shone through them and all the other assorted work that the testing machines did, she was able to liaise with the Protectors and keep them apprised of her results in real-time. Between them they quickly decided that the best thing for their buddies was to get them scrubbed up and bedded down on cots right there in the suit shop, with drips in for hydration and glucose, a maximum dose each of Crue-D, and a license to sleep for as long as they needed under supervision.

She was grateful to find, once all the results were in and she’d evaluated them, that in her absence the suit shop had returned to its more usual nasal background noise which, although it did include a strong note of body odor, at least balanced that note with lubricant, hot rubber, industrial cleaning agents and solder.

Warhorse had taken first shift in supervising his exhausted buddies, who were all fast asleep on cots along the dividing wall between the shop and the locker room. Out of their suits, they were an obvious mess - all four were sporting pinch marks, blood blisters, bruises, rash and the other trademark skin discolorations that came with wearing EV-MASS for any length of time.

They had a form for recording those - a stylized human body from several angles with a simple emblem system - crosses, hashing, plus signs and stars - for recording the location and size of different kinds of marks. He’d saved her a job there and begun filling them in himself, and they took a moment to double-check to her satisfaction that he hadn’t missed anything as best they could without actually moving or waking the sleepers.

“How’re their results?” he asked, once she’d satisfied herself and pocketed them.

“Nothing scary, but God. I wouldn’t want to have metabolite levels that high.” Martina said. “Sikes especially must be in agony.”

’Horse gave his buddies an unhappy look over and nodded.

Both of them caught movement in the corner of their eye, and stood when it turned out to be major Powell crossing the shop with a serious expression, not that he usually wore any other kind.

“Siddown, siddown.” he called, waving them down. “I’m just checkin’ on them.”

“They’ll be fine sir. Ares and I were just discussing their bloodwork.” Martina told him.

Powell nodded. “Any thoughts on their recovery time?”

Horse looked to Martina. “Two weeks, two and a half?” he asked.

“That’s maybe being optimistic…” Martina suggested. “The rehab diet alone-”

“Right, yeah.” Ares nodded.

“Just a ballpark will do me for now.” Powell said.

“Three weeks, sir,” Martina told him.

Powell’s jaw worked thoughtfully as he assimilated that news. "Cally in drydock, four of the Lads convalescing, I’ve got Jackson wanting to train you and Baseball up for PR work…" he grumbled, gesturing to Ares, “General Tremblay’s gonna have to find somebody else for the embassy job.”

“Never a dull moment.” Martina observed. They all knew the subtle tics and tells that were Powell’s expressions, and she saw a silent laugh pull momentarily at the corner of his mouth.

“Aye, at least I’m not fookin’ bored.” he agreed. “Okay. You two bash together a recovery schedule and I’ll let the Navy worry about getting us a replacement ride while ours is in the shop.”

“Yes sir.”

Powell left them in peace.

Martina started calculating the rehab schedule in her head, and Ares was plainly doing something similar, albeit on his fingers. She tried and failed to stifle her amusement: He was so huge and prodigiously muscled that counting on his fingers made him look adorably cro-magnon, even though she knew that he was furiously calculating some quite sophisticated medical realities.

He didn’t fail to notice, and went slightly red. “What?”

“Nothing.”

“What?!”

She laughed, and pantomimed counting on her fingers while pulling the dumbest, most neanderthal face she could. He snorted, directed an affectionate middle finger at her, and went back to his mental arithmetic with a smile.

Martina pulled her notebook from her pocket and happily did the same. Apparently the therapy hadn’t killed off their chemistry after all…

Date Point 10y4m2w6d AV
Las Vegas, Nevada, USA, Earth.

Allison Buehler

“Come on, honey, you’ve got this! First roll!”

Xiu was plainly having the time of her life. A loud woman with a broad Louisiana accent was cheering her on, and she wasn’t the only one - the four other players at the table were all calling words of encouragement. Xiu meanwhile was smiling nervously as she picked up the dice.

Allison laughed as she and Julian watched her imitate what others had done and blow on the dice in her hand, then cast them vigorously down the table. There were cheers, everybody collected some chips and Xiu pumped her fist, danced an excited circle on the spot, and eagerly accepted the dice to throw them again, drinking in the words of praise and encouragement from the eclectic mix of people at the table.

“Do you follow what’s going on?” Julian asked.

“She just rolled an eleven.” Allison explained.

“That’s good?”

Allison smiled. “Everybody’s ten dollars richer thanks to her.”

“Hah. That’s our girl!”

They watched Xiu share a joke with the lady from Louisiana - it was hard to hear what she said over the sound of people calling for a repeat performance - and bounced the dice off the far wall of the table. This met with a more subdued response, but still a generally positive one, and several chips were added to the table.

It was all clearly a bit arcane for Julian. His attention wandered as the croupier maneuvered her stick around and returned the dice for another throw, which was met with a more muted response.

“So I’ve been thinking.” Allison told him.

“’Bout what?”

“’Bout you and her.”

Julian turned to face her. “You’re still okay, right?”

“I’m fine! Are you? You’ve not really… y’know, moved things forward.”

“We have our moments…” Julian said. “It’s just tricky.”

“Moments like what?”

“Like… little moments. Where, if I was having the moment with you…” he leaned over suddenly and kissed her. “…like that, you know?”

Touched, Allison smiled. “So what’s tricky about that?”

“Well, you said we have to ask permission first and… I mean, I don’t know how to do that without it kind of… I want things to be natural.” Julian explained. “You know…”

“Spontaneous.”

“Yeah. It’s like… if we have to ask permission-”

“I get you.” Allison nodded. She sat back and watched Xiu throw her dice - whatever she rolled, it produced a neutral response from her fellow players. She took a swig of her beer to cover a rush of mixed emotions.

Julian saw right through her. “Are you okay?” he asked.

“I’m…. kinda…” Allison sighed and started over. “I want to just agree that it’s a stupid rule.” she confessed. “I feel like I shouldn’t be so insecure, you know?”

“Hey, it’s okay-” he began, reaching out and taking her hand.

Allison squeezed his fingers. “No it’s not,” she interrupted. “This whole thing with her was my idea after all. A rule like that is just… it sends mixed signals. I’m not putting my money where my mouth is, y’know?"

“It is okay." Julian insisted. “We’re all in this together. Xiu and me, we don’t want to hurt you, and if you need time to adjust to things then that’s fine!”

There was a cheer from the table. Grinning from ear to ear, Xiu curtseyed for her fellow players. She saw Allison and Julian watching her and gave them a huge beaming smile and a wave.

“Y’know, I wasn’t expecting to enjoy Vegas,” Julian confessed, returning the wave. “I’ve been here before and it’s too… it’s just not my thing. But I love how much she’s enjoying herself.”

Allison nodded. For courage, she finished her beer. “Baby… I don’t know if I’m ready to scrap the whole permission thing yet, but the next time you have one of those ‘moments’, I want you to promise me you’ll go for it, okay?"

“Al-”

“I mean it, mister. You kiss that girl the first chance you get. That’s an order."

Julian stared at her for a second, but he knew when she was serious. He didn’t joke about with a ‘yes ma’am’ this time: He nodded. “…I promise.”

“Good…” Allison scooted round and cuddled up to his arm. “I love you.”

He kissed her forehead. “I love you too, dummy.”

Xiu’s run of good luck came to an end with a groan and a short round of applause from everyone else at the table. She said her goodbyes, collected her chips and sprang over to Allison and Julian’s table looking thoroughly pleased with herself.

“How’d you do?” Julian asked her. Xiu had gone to the table with a strict budget of ten ten-dollar bets.

“I’m up twenty dollars!” she waggled a stack of twelve chips, thoroughly pleased with herself.

“Nice!”

“What about you guys, are you okay?”

“This is the best time I’ve ever had in Vegas.” Julian told her.

Allison laughed. “Same!” she announced, having never been to Vegas before. “It’s fun watching you play.”

Xiu grinned at them. “Okay, so Charlene - that’s the lady in the denim vest - she told me about this stage show she thinks we should go see, and Hank - that’s the guy with the belt buckle - he was telling me about this gourmet burger restaurant on the Boulevard and…”

She took Julian’s hand and pulled him in the direction of the street, babbling excitedly. Grinning to herself, Allison gathered their belongings and followed.

Date Point 10y4m2w6d AV
Planet Perfection, The Core Worlds.

Vakno, “The Contact”.

The early years of Vakno’s career had involved teetering on the brink of bankruptcy. Not through any lack of skill, or a run of bad luck, but because she had early on calculated that whatever her odds of success in the infobrokering business might be, the most probable failure case was assassination.

It was, after all, how she had disposed of her own early rivals.

To that end, she had spent nearly all of her profits during those early years on personal protection. From bodyguard drones and the very best personal combat rigs, to the full splendor that was her office. Those spartan walls and that austere desk hid within them a package of assorted defensive technologies both physical and electronic that made Vakno about the most securely protected living thing in the known galaxy.

Nowadays, keeping it at the very bleeding edge required only a fraction of her assets. Her own sensor network had tracked the Hunter swarm long before Perfection’s defence grid. She had already evicted (and kindly warned) her client by the time they were entering orbit. When they had launched dozens of objects onto a high velocity re-entry course, she had been given plenty of warning to activate the very strongest shields she had, and retreat into the most secure sanctum below.

When one of those weapons - a kinetic impactor of some kind, a simple metal pole twenty times her height and bigger around than she could have wrapped her arms - had smashed into the city deck above her, its destructive power had ripped out the surrounding layers, crushing homes, businesses and lives, and gutting the supports of a major corporate skyscraper, which had not remained vertical for long.

Vakno herself had barely felt a tremor throughout the short bombardment. Shortly thereafter, her perimeter defences had sensed Hunters picking through the devastation, but not like any Hunter she had ever seen before. These were larger, even more nauseating in form than their ordinary kin and layered in dense fibrous musculature that reminded her uncomfortably of the few humans she had dealt with in her career.

Three of them had died straying too close to the bunker’s perimeter, and they had apparently decided not to waste their time cracking her shell when there was much softer meat to be had.

They had ravaged the city for nearly a day before Vakno’s sensors finally detected the return of the humans and several high-energy flashes in orbit, characteristic of lithium-deuteride fusion.

Rather than fight the hated deathworlders, the Hunters had departed with their holds full of slaves and their bellies full of meat.

So many slaves. So much meat. Even Vakno, dispassionate as she was, couldn’t help but feel the weight of panic and alarm against the walls of her rational self-control, pressuring her into reconsidering just how valuable humans really were.

When she saw what the Hunters had done to the crippled system defence fleet, however, she had to sit and meditate long and hard before finally recovering the rational control necessary to look at things from the human perspective.

And the question presented itself - How had the Hunters known?

It would be a long time indeed before Perfection recovered to the point where Vakno would be back to business as usual, and like all Corti she had a burning need to be productive. Her sense of self-esteem would not permit her to take a vacation during the inevitable lull in her business.

Not when there was so gnawing a question left unanswered. The raid was too precise in its timing, too flawless in execution and too large in scale to have happened on the spur of the moment.

This wasn’t fortune: Somebody had fed Perfection to the Hunters. Somebody had almost fed Vakno to the Hunters. And Vakno had had people killed for much less than that.

She started digging.

Date Point 10y4m3w1d AV
Yosemite National Park, California, USA, Earth.

Julian Etsicitty

All of the tourism pictures showed Yosemite on clear blue-skied days when the waters were still and mirror-polished, flanked by a stentorian, forest-bearded honour guard of mountains.

Julian thought it looked even more beautiful in the rain.

It wasn’t serious rain - really, it was more a kind of acrophobic cloud that processed down from the mountains and dragged a diaphanous silver wedding train of light drizzle behind it, which fogged out the bombastic landscape that so entranced the documentary makers and tourists, and instead forced the eye to notice the smaller, the closer and the more immediate things.

Allison, naturally, was lurking in their tiny tent - built for two and delightfully cozy for three - under the tarp shelter Julian had rigged up for them and she was refusing to stray out into the rain. She seemed happy enough to wrap up warm with an ebook and a thermal flask full of Ovaltine and watch him work, and once he was done she’d insisted that Julian should go commune with nature and not worry about her.

Xiu was a complete contrast. She’d slapped on her outback hat and gone exploring the second Julian had declared their little day-camp complete, apparently oblivious to the chill and the moisture. She’d acknowledge his warning to be careful and not stray too far, and had set out eastwards toward the sound of the river, armed only with the backpack of essentials he’d prepared for them all just in case.

Julian took his time in following her. She wasn’t hard to follow - the fitness regime she’d followed religiously during her years in exile meant, especially thanks to the weighted clothing she’d worn to try and simulate the Earth’s gravity, that Xiu was a little powerhouse, remarkably strong and heavy for her apparent size, and despite her agility and poise she’d never learned the art of stepping softly. To an experienced tracker - and Julian was a master tracker - her footsteps were nearly as clear and obvious in the wet ground as if they’d been painted there in blaze orange.

What she didn’t do was make much noise. Julian was the other way round - he stepped lightly and tried to leave no clear sign of his passing, but he did sing to himself, humming and whistling through the bits where he couldn’t remember the lyrics. It was maybe a little ridiculous, but if there was anything nearby that would prefer to avoid him, he should give it plenty of notice rather than startling it. Besides, he was so used to doing it by now that it would have felt strange to him not to sing as he walked.

♪♫_“Heyyy, darling… I hope you’re good toni-i-ght… hmm hmmm hmm-mm hmm….. Tell me something sweet…”_♪♫

He ambled along in Xiu’s wake, inspecting all of the things she’d paused to look at, and several other interesting things that she’d apparently missed. The sedate pace allowed him to satisfy himself that he’d picked the right spot for them to dally the day away - there was no sign of any potentially dangerous wildlife in the area, which was his biggest concern, but also no sign that the river ever got high enough to threaten them or their stuff.

He lost her trail when he reached the river, and the ground became nothing but stones and rock, but that hardly mattered, because she hadn’t gone any further.

Julian hadn’t ever got onto the subject of spirituality or religion with Xiu. He had no idea what she believed in, but he knew that she meditated every day when she could, usually first thing in the morning before he and Allison were up. The day they’d left Minnesota, she’d woken up extra early and had been seated comfortably on the log by the fire pit, facing the dawn sun when Julian had risen.

Now, she was seated in the lotus position on a rock by the river. She’d taken her hat off and let her hair down, and had her face turned slightly to the sky with a subtle liberated smile playing around her lips, enjoying the play of cool moisture over her face.

She opened her eyes, and gave him a relaxed smile and a wave. “Singing to yourself?” she asked.

“Always a good idea in the woods.” Julian shrugged off his pack and sat down next to her. “I’m pretty sure there aren’t any bears around, but…”

Her face fell. “…Oh. Wow. Bears?”

“Always possible, but I don’t think so. Nothing here they’d want.”

She gulped and looked around. “Maybe I shouldn’t have run off alone. Sorry!”

Julian chuckled. “It’s okay! If I’d thought there was any serious danger I’d have stopped you. Trust me.”

“I do!” Xiu squeezed some water out of her hair, then laughed nervously. “But… Wow. We really do live on a deathworld, don’t we?”

“Oh yeah.” Julian nodded. “Kinda smacks you full in the head sometimes, doesn’t it?”

She nodded. “Still… it’s beautiful.”

“I’ve always wanted to come here.” Julian agreed. “Almost gave up on getting the chance, really.”

“Allison’s missing it though…”

“Don’t worry, she’s perfectly happy.” Julian promised.

Xiu nodded and looked around again at the iconic landscape. The light rain was almost nothing now - enough to moisten the skin and slowly soak into their clothing, but it was doing nothing to impede the view. In fact the shreds of cloud garlanding the peaks only enhanced it.

“Are you warm enough?” Julian asked her.

“I’m fine,” she assured him. “This is nice!”

“We’re both used to chilly temperatures, huh?”

She nodded. “Gao and spaceships… and I guess this is nothing next to a Nightmare winter?”

“Downright warm. And don’t forget Canada”

She waved a hand dismissively. “Vancouver’s not that cold.”

Julian nodded, shut his eyes and let the white noise of nature permeate him. He was used to the wilderness, and had long learned the trick of really turning on his ears. Modern human life meant that people rarely got the chance to understand just how acute their senses truly were. It wasn’t that their ears got numb or anything, just that daily life involved being surrounded by so much noise that filtering out everything except for a narrow band of “important” sounds was an ingrained survival skill.

Un-learning that skill and noticing everything, that was a real trick. The same went for the nose. Given time to adjust, the human nose could pick up the musk of a mouse in nearby bushes, or the avian funk of a nest full of chicks in the trees above. The ear could tell flycatchers from warblers and hear stones knocking along the river bed, if only the listener knew how to listen.

He certainly heard Xiu’s contented sigh and the way she settled herself a little more comfortably and slowed her breathing,

They enjoyed the comfortable silence together, basking in the scent of conifers and petrichor, and Julian only opened his eyes when an unexpected beam of sunlight on his face turned the quiet blackness behind his eyelids red.

He raised his hand to squint against it. The weather was rolling in waves down the valley, and the rain would be back soon enough, but just for a few moments the view was clear, open and unimpeded.

"Ai ya…" Xiu breathed.

“Yeah.”

He put his arm round her waist. He half expected her to stiffen or catch her breath, but she did the opposite - she sighed happily and leaned against him, resting her head on his shoulder.

Rather than saying anything, Julian made a kind of wordless, gently interrogative sound. She nodded against his shoulder and replied in kind - not a word, but a kind of of happy chirrup or purr.

He kissed her on the top of the head. With a querying “Mm?” she turned her head slightly, got another kiss - this one on the forehead - and when she raised her face to look at him Julian took his chance and kissed her properly.

Xiu issued a passionate squeak, and purely on instinct she put a hand on the back of his head and straightened up to get a better angle, while her other hand splayed on his chest then gripped his shirt. Julian ran his own hand slowly up her back while his free hand took its place on her waist.

It was Xiu who eventually ended it. When they parted, she gasped and rested her forehead against his, while words quietly bubbled out of her as if she wasn’t entirely in control of them. “Oh my god I needed that I’ve wanted you to do that for-” she stiffened. “Wait. You asked Allison, right?”

Julian smiled, trying to overrule his galloping pulse and project composed happiness. “I did,” he reassured her.

Xiu sighed happily, and this time it was her turn to kiss him.

They stayed wrapped up in each other by the river for a good long while, talking quietly, kissing frequently, giggling together and bonding. It finally had to come to an end though when a fat raindrop slapped disgustingly into Julian’s ear, and he looked at the sky.

“Okay, that’s no drizzle,” he decided, indicating an ash-grey battalion of clouds that were marching down from the peaks with rancorous intent.

Xiu exhaled resignedly and donned her hat, pulling it down snugly around her ears. “Cuddling up in the tent with Allison sounds good as well…” she suggested.

“You read my mind.”

They helped each other put on their backpacks, took a last look at the valley in the knowledge that they’d probably never come there again, and put it behind them hand-in-hand.

Date Point 10y4m3w1d AV
HMS Sharman (HMNB Folctha), Planet Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Admiral Sir Patrick Knight

Knight hadn’t been involved personally in the interview of their alien detainees of course - that job had naturally fallen to Intelligence, according to whom Bedu had been an absolutely model interviewee - polite, concise, intelligent enough to recognise that resistance would gain him nothing, and with no particular reason to do so anyway.

The summary of his interview made for interesting reading.

Bedu’s business model it seemed was inconveniently discreet, to the point where even Bedu himself didn’t know who his clients were unless they wanted him to. The client who had set him on the trail of Kirk and the missing starship Sanctuary had done so anonymously, but with considerable existing knowledge of where to start looking.

The search had started at the planet Aru, and this in itself was an education. Knight was something of a history buff, and alien history in particular was a field that had begun to fascinate him. There was so impossibly much of it and the Dominion’s historical archives - which humanity notionally had access to by dint of being an associate Dominion member, even if they were far too large to actually be transmitted to any storage medium on Earth - had much too haphazard a filing system for anything to be known with any real certainty before the Corti had come along and imposed strict data standards on the whole mess.

Aru, however… Aru was previously unknown to him, and was now in admiral Knight’s opinion a fascinating jewel of historical interest that his amateur antiquarian’s instincts would have dearly loved to get in front of the figurative loupe.

Why Kirk had gone to Aru was known, thanks to the statements given by the two survivors of his crew - Etsicitty and Buehler - and the young miss Chang whom they had collected from the planet. Why he had lingered after recovering her had been a little fuzzier, but Bedu had shed some light on that mystery.

The historic decline and fall of every sapient spacefaring power in the galaxy was well documented. Indeed, it was one of the topics of fascinated discussion that entranced amateur xenohistorians on the Internet (not that there were yet such things as professional xenohistorians), in the parlance of whom the phenomenon had been named the “Great Filter”, a term borrowed from one Robin Hanson who had coined it in an attempt to solve the so-called Fermi Paradox.

The Fermi Paradox was a now-extinct problem that had distracted people who were inclined to worry about such things with the question of where all the aliens were and why they weren’t popping in for a cup of tea and a chat. Given that said question’s relevance had faded somewhat in recent years, the Fermi Paradox was now only of interest to historically-minded students of science and enthusiasts of the burgeoning field of xenoarchaeology.

Aru, being the home planet of a species who were already in the late stages of their terminal decline and apparently disinterested in doing anything to stop it, was naturally a decent starting point for anybody who wished to understand the nature of the Great Filter and maybe do something about it.

Kirk had lingered there after collecting his most recent rescue, and then when Bedu had been sent to investigate Sanctuary’s disappearance, the Negotiable Curiosity had not needed to search very long and hard to find a debris field thirty light years away.

Bedu’s ship, its owner had proudly explained, was equipped with particle detectors sensitive enough to trace the FTL movement of objects as small as an escape pod up to ten years after the fact, assuming the trail wasn’t confused by the passage of other ships. Space, however, was so… well, spacious, that really that was a problem that only manifested along major spacelanes and near stations.

Sanctuary, while not a large ship, had been built with such a convention- stretching power output that its trail was the easiest Bedu had ever been called on to follow, and it had led him right to the heart of a tumbling cloud of wreckage.

Again, the next part matched with what Etsicitty, Buehler and Chang had reported - something with the power output of a dreadnought had intercepted them, and both ships had been destroyed when Sanctuary’s mortally wounded pilot, Amir Bahmani, had rammed the hostile while the rest of the crew abandoned ship.

Bedu had initially followed the escape pod carrying the three humans. Retracing his steps and picking up the trail of the other, faster, lifeboat had eventually led him to a system known only by its stellar coordinates - Knight glossed over the string of numbers involved, which described the star’s type, age, distance as a proportion of the galactic radius from Sagittarius A* and its deviation in radians from the straight line connecting that object to the heart of the Andromeda galaxy.

The star in question was a red giant, well past its main sequence and venerably burning through its helium. No temperate planets, one gas giant nearly twice the size of Jupiter, a handful of barren rocks and an acidic hellpit that made Venus look like no more unpleasant than a kitchen full of recently-chopped onions in comparison.

It would have been a completely unremarkable system if not for the forcefield enclosing it - identical to the ones that even now protected Cimbrean and Earth - and the crashed Kwmbwrw research station lodged in one of that gas giant’s moons, which was in the wrong place to the tune of thirty thousand lightyears and change.

From an intelligence perspective, however, by far the most important thing that Bedu was able to tell them was that at no point in its voyage from Sanctuary’s wreckage to this question mark of a system had Kirk’s lifeboat been intercepted.

While Bedu himself was Orange - augmented, possibly a target of interest for Hierarchy use, but not yet actually suspected of having been possessed by a Hierarchy demon - his story was corroborated by the Negotiable Curiosity’s sensor records, which in turn showed no signs of tampering.

Taken all together it was good news, and the report concluded with a recommendation that Kirk’s own status be downgraded from Orange to Yellow. He couldn’t be called Green until an implant scanner had pinged the inside of his skull, but Intel were at least happy enough to move him a step in that direction.

All in all, the report put Sir Patrick in a good mood. He wrote a quick mail for the attention of general Tremblay, rubbed his eyes, and then turned his attention to the report in his pile that he knew was going to deflate that good mood slightly.

With a sigh, he started to pore over the most recent analysis of operation NOVA HOUND.

Date Point 10y4m3w2d AV
San Francisco, California, USA, Earth

Xiu Chang

“…Wow.”

“Yeah.”

“Whaddya think?”

Xiu had a hard time choosing the right word, in any language. ‘Colorful’ and ‘Flamboyant’ came to mind, but so was Chinese New Year, and nothing else that presented itself quite made the grade either.

“It’s very… gay.” She decided. That was the nice thing about English. One word could carry such a huge weight of alternative meanings and context, without going into the simply crazy subtleties of intonation that played such an important role in Mandarin. Both languages were hideously complex when compared to Gaori, which was refreshingly direct. Gaori wasn’t unsubtle by any means, but it lacked the impenetrable nuance that allowed her to pun like that, carefully deploying three different meanings at once in the span of a rather simple monosyllable.

She could only imagine what the actual Gay Pride parade next month would look like. It’d presumably make this look conservative and sedate.

She’d gone quite rusty in both her human languages thanks to several years of not using them, and since getting back to Earth she’d almost exclusively spoken English, much to her mother’s frustration. Still, she was finally getting things straight in her head and didn’t so often find herself slipping automatically back into the alien tongue whenever she wasn’t concentrating.

Together, she and Allison watched a young man dance past wearing a pair of gold lame briefs, bright orange feathers, lipstick, and the kind of muscles that belonged on ancient Greek pottery.

“Show me what you’re workin’ with, baby!” Allison cat-called. Somehow the dancer heard her over the drumming and trumpets. He aimed a buttock at them and smacked it with a grin before dancing along with the rest of his troupe.

Allison gave a delighted laugh, and beamed at the way Xiu was giggling with her.

“Your turn!” she declared, and hoisted Xiu toward the railing. Xiu tried not to imagine what her mother would think, picked another male dancer and cupped her hands.

"Yao piguuu!"

Presumably the dancer didn’t speak a word of Mandarin, but he seemed to get the gist of it and posed for her, flexing magnificently. Xiu applauded while Allison blew him a kiss.

They retreated from the railing as a more stately group in ornate - and huge - red ballgowns began to sail regally by, and Allison took Xiu’s hand to lead her through the crowd. She was in her element, Xiu decided, being surrounded by noise and vibrancy and color. Xiu loved to “get loud” as an occasional treat - as she was doing right now - but Julian had shrunk into himself and had taken the first excuse he reasonably could to retreat to the relative quiet and calm of a coffee shop.

Allison seemed to want to sample everything and she tested even Xiu’s reserves as she led the way from street vendor to street performer, to live musician and back to the barricade to watch more of the parade, then on into the crowd.

They got matching henna tattoos, sampled Fajita chicken skewers fresh off the grill, danced together to the pounding mix of a street DJ who was blending Samba and Rastatrash into something new and exciting and generally got drunk on the sheer weirdness of it all before finally finding themselves sitting down at a bus stop and sharing a bottle of cold water, having summoned Julian to come find them. It was coming up on two in the afternoon, and the parade was drumming and gyrating its way toward winding down.

“Man.” Allison commented, watching two dozen women wearing enough pink sequins and feathers to maybe completely cover three of them strut past smiling. “I think I’ve seen more ass today than the rest of my life put together.”

“Oh yeah.” Xiu nodded, widening her eyes for emphasis.

“Fun though, right?”

Xiu looked around. People were drifting away, now that the tail end of the parade had passed them. Back to normalcy, and to lives with decidedly less glitter in them. The afternoon breeze still carried the distant sound of drumming through the dense, old grid of buildings, but already the whole thing was starting to feel like a dream. Hundreds, or perhaps thousands of magical people had danced and swayed and played and sung their way along these roads, and behind them were left the permanent fixtures of dusty concrete and faded paint.

It was an oddly familiar sensation.

“Xiu?”

“Sorry, I just… Yeah, it was fun.”

Allison knew her too well. “But…?” she asked.

“Well… look.” Xiu waved a hand around.

Allison did so, frowning as if wondering what she was getting at. “Sure got quiet…” she observed, then seemed to get what Xiu was driving at. “Actually, wow. That’s a heck of a contrast.”

“I was just thinking it feels familiar.” Xiu told her.

“Yeah… is it me or is this place kinda ugly without the parade?”

She was right. The asphalt looked like it hadn’t ever been resurfaced, just patched up as needed. Overhead was a tangle of bare black cabling that didn’t seem to have any clear reasoning or logic to it. It wasn’t that Mission district looked neglected, it just looked… preserved. Like a jar of pickled onions, it might still be working and useful but the crispness and life was no longer entirely there.

“Where’s Julian?” Xiu asked.

Allison checked her phone. They were all using a tracking app they’d found that could help them hone in on each other by sharing how far away their contacts were and in what direction. “He’s… that way.” she pointed. “Quarter of a mile.”

“Let’s go meet him.” Xiu stood up. The sheer mundanity was getting to her. “I don’t think I like it here.”

“’Kay.” Allison tapped on her app to let Julian know they were going to come to him, then took her hand and they set off walking.

They cut across the corner of the parade route, and another facet to the sudden absence of the big glitzy distraction of the Carnaval made itself known to Xiu - she’d spent the whole day holding hands with Allison.

Most of the time it had been a simple case of not wanting to lose one another in the crowd, but now that they were walking together more slowly, it dawned on her that there was something… different about intertwined fingers and an arm wrapped around her own.

She glanced sideways at Allison, who caught the movement in her peripheral vision, turned her head and caught her eye, smiled bashfully and tidied a strand of blonde hair out of her face while squeezing Xiu’s hand.

That was the thing about Allison. Xiu had originally thought of her as the master of fake-it-’til-you-make-it, but that was unfair. Allison didn’t do fake, she did… determined. Her life doctrine seemed to be keeping her foot down on the accelerator, committing wholly to whatever it was she’d decided to do and aiming an angry middle finger at her own comfort zones if they tried to get in the way.

It should have been intimidating, or obnoxious. In anybody else it probably would have been. In Allison… She may have held her own comfort zones in contempt, but she had never once violated Xiu’s, and Xiu knew she’d be genuinely upset if she found she was making either her or Julian uncomfortable. That made all the difference, and so she was able to lead where Xiu might not ordinarily have followed… like walking down the street in broad daylight, holding hands like girlfriends.

Because they were, she supposed. That was the point, wasn’t it? Allison had made it plain that she didn’t want their relationship to just be that of two good friends who happened to share the same man. And while Xiu might ordinarily have settled for just that… Not even Julian quite got her pulse going like Allison did, and she wasn’t sure why. Possibly it was the lingering shadow of taboo, or maybe it was the way she kept breaking through walls she’d never known she had, only to find clean waters beyond.

Maybe it was the fact that Xiu knew in her bones and from experience that she could literally trust Allison with her life. Whenever she flashed back to that horrible moment on Sanctuary when the hull had ripped apart and the void had tried to drag her away, the memory that always came with it was that it had been Allison who’d reached out and caught her.

It was difficult not to want to follow where somebody who’d literally saved her life was leading.

She squeezed back and leaned a little closer.

“Do you ever feel like an alien?” she asked.

“Yeah,” Allison nodded. “Like I’m not quite human.”

“Or that they’re not quite human." Xiu waved her free hand surreptitiously, indicating a family who were wending their way home. Two bouncing children high on far too much sugar, a harassed mom and a dad whose huge sarcastic T-shirt was pulled tight over his beer gut.

“That’s it, yeah.” Allison nodded. “That’s exactly it. I just wanna ask them, you know, ‘Is this who you wanna be? Are you happy?’ You know?"

“That’s not very nice, Allison.”

“Well I’m not gonna do it!" Allison defended herself. “Just… You know?”

“I know.” Xiu nodded. She was looking at people who had never… never gone hand-to-hand with a sapient worm in a robot suit. Never hidden in a Hunter meat locker. Never come within a whisker of horrible death not once but twice. Never seen their innocent protege, their sister, dying. They had no idea who Triymin had been, what life was really like. She wondered if they even had dreams any longer, or if those dreams extended beyond a happy family and home.

They didn’t look happy…

Allison squeezed her hand again. “I try not to judge.” she said. “But it’s hard, ain’t it?”

"Why, though?" Xiu asked. “Why is it hard? They’re not doing anything wrong.”

“You’re right. They’re not doing anything.”

“Al… that’s not nice.”

“I know…” Allison sighed.

“Even if I feel the same way, it’s not nice.”

“I know.”

Guilt and uncertainty looked so out of place on Allison that Xiu had no option but to give her hand another reassuring squeeze. “But hey. We’re doing something,” she said.

That raised a smile. “We are, yeah. I just wish more people could.”

“Could get abducted?” Xiu teased.

Allison laughed. "No, dummy," she exclaimed. “Just… I wish more people could see how much bigger they really are. This-" she waved a hand, indicating the whole preserved city around them “this isn’t who we’re meant to be. I swear, there’s something in the human soul that just longs for adventure."

“Nearly getting killed?” Xiu suggested.

“No, like-”

“Watching other people get killed?”

“Xiu…”

“Having to wear a disguise for three years in case they try and blow you out the airlock or in case the Hunters come looking for you?”

“Babe-”

Xiu gave her an apologetic look. “I’m sorry,” she said. “But adventures aren’t easy or fun, Al. You know that.”

Allison sighed. “…My abductors were called Trevni and Nufr.” She said. Xiu blinked - Allison hadn’t ever told her about her abduction before. “They were actually okay, for… you know, for kidnappers who saw me as a test subject. I might have been strapped naked to a table, but they weren’t cruel, it was all… it was just business. Right? No malice."

Xiu nodded carefully “Okay…?”

“I killed them. I didn’t mean to. They just… They picked me up because I had a cold, and they wanted to study it and develop a cure. They knew enough about us to know that we’d pay a lot to cure the common cold. But, they weren’t careful enough and…”

She sniffed. “They weren’t nice people, exactly, but they didn’t deserve what it did to them. The last thing Nufr did was he gave me a Frontline and undid my restraints. I’d have died of thirst strapped to that table if he hadn’t. And the people who finally rescued me would have died of… I dunno, acne or candida or something."

Her fingers twisted painfully between Xiu’s for a moment. “I know, babe. I know what an adventure really is. I know it means people who don’t deserve it dying in horrible ways, and… maybe us too. I know all that. And I still don’t think I could ever go back to the quiet life. I… I wouldn’t know how to cope."

Xiu was sighing with her when they saw Julian come round the corner. The uncomfortable shuffle in his step evaporated on seeing them, and he picked up his pace with a wave, which they returned.

“Neither would I,” she conceded.

Date Point 10y4m3w2d AV
War Platform Lifebringer, Perfection System, The Core Worlds

Grand Fleetmaster Tk’vrrtnnk A’Khvnrrtk

The ship class designated as “War Platforms” weren’t warships at all, at least not in the sense of a ship that engaged the enemy directly.

Even though it was layered in armor, shields and point defense batteries, Lifebringer was a staging and command vessel. It was the mothership of a whole fleet of transports, shuttles, dropships and heavy cargo lifters. It was a flying barracks, a mobile airfield, a cavernous cargo bay and a nexus of computer systems.

It was, in short, everything that a fleet needed to go somewhere and do something, and it was verging on being as large as a ship could practically get.. At a full gallop, Tk’v would have needed more than [two minutes] to get from one end to the other even if there had been a single straight corridor fit for that purpose..

The humans, he knew, would be impressed. Fleetmaster Caruthers’ transport was an unmodified Dominion standard shuttle, a flying matte-grey brick that made up for in rugged reliability what it pathetically lacked in grace and aesthetics.

Next to the troop lander and the two heavy cargo lifters currently squatting in Lifebringer’s number one docking bay, it was tiny, and it was still big enough to comfortably carry three young Guvnurag. When the humans stepped out of it, it made them seem comically small.

The heavy vibrations their feet sent ringing through the deck shattered that smallness.

He recognised Caruthers easily enough - the human fleetmaster was plainly the oldest of the delegation that had come over. The two at the back looked to be bodyguards or marines. Tk’v was hardly an expert on clothing - the most he wore being saddlebags, holsters and a decorative pennant on his neck to signal his rank - but those two’s seemed less decorative than the others’.

Caruthers, for his part, looked both austere in his black uniform, and splendid thanks to its conservative flourishes of gold and white.

The deathworlder entourage paused in front of Tk’v’s own welcoming party, and Caruthers took one extra pace forward. “Permission to come aboard,” he stated. Tk’v’s translator interpreted this as a formal request, possibly a traditional or ceremonial courtesy.

“Permission granted,” he replied, judging this to be the most probable response given how terse the request had been. Borrowing from some research he’d done on humans, he extended the stronger of his two right hands, trusting the human not to grip with the crushing force that Tk’v knew he was capable of.

His trust was rewarded. Caruthers’ handshake was firm, but no more than that. “Thank you for having us,” he said.

“Thank you for coming.” Tk’v replied. He indicated his subordinates. “This is Subfleetmaster Rhou, and junior subfleetmaster Nwmrwnw.

“Captain Manning of HMS Myrmidon, and commander Devonald of HMS Valiant. Caruthers replied, then indicated the marines. “Corporal Brewer and Corporal Banks.”

“Well then. If it pleases you to inspect the ship, I thought we might talk.” Tk’v replied amicably.

“Lead on.”

V’tk did so, gesturing for the human to walk by his side. “I had Lifebringer’s dimensions converted into your units." he said. “She is slightly more than four hundred meters across her widest axis, and masses approximately sixty million kilograms.”

“That must be pushing the limits of what’s physically possible.” Caruthers observed.

“Certainly in anything which needs to accelerate like a warship.” Tk’v agreed. “There are larger ships, but not many and they are all painfully slow. The biggest ever built, I believe, was a pleasure barge that could not only afford to spend [months] transiting between worlds, but actively wanted to, so that their guests would have as much time to spend their money as possible. That ship was more than twice the size of this one."

The expressive line of dark fur above Caruthers’ right eye arched upwards. “Was?”

“Indeed. It eventually broke apart under the stresses of its own acceleration.”

“Hmm. We have a similar cautionary anecdote from an ocean-going vessel called the Titanic," Caruthers told him. “The fastest and largest luxury ship of its day. Too fast, in fact - it struck an iceberg and sank in freezing cold waters more than a hundred years ago.”

“Ice? I was given to understand that yours is a hot planet, fleetmaster.” Tk’v observed. “The stories of Earth I have heard mention that the sun can burn you, and that you can die of the heat.”

“That’s toward the equator. The poles are frozen solid year round.”

“Both, on the same planet?”

“It’s a surprise to us that other worlds are any different.” Caruthers smiled, though he made the courtesy of not showing his teeth. “How were we to know, after all?”

“True. In any case, although Lifebringer can accelerate to meet the minimum demands laid down by Dominion security resolutions for a warship, she is still the slowest in the fleet. Substantially slower than your own ships have demonstrated."

“Our doctrines seem to be quite different.” Caruthers agreed. “Maybe we should compare notes.”

“Maybe we should.” Tk’v agreed.

The tour wended slowly around the ship, taking in the huge power plant (powered by the newest generation of Directorate-made quantum power stacks), the living quarters (an exercise in awkwardness given the wildly differing proportions and needs of the many species on the crew), the cargo handling bays and their army of drones, and finally he command hub, dominated by a to- scale holographic map of the system labelled in blue, yellow and green.

“How is the situation below?” Caruthers asked, once Tk’v had demonstrated the map’s functionality by zooming in on Perfection itself.

The working crew around them went quite still, and listened. Tk’v knew that many of them were firmly of the opinion that the humans were responsible for all the death and destruction not only on Perfection, but at Capitol Station. Tk’v couldn’t have disagreed more strongly. He had specifically requested this relief effort because, unlike most of his peers, he very much did not view the Hunters as a kind of natural disaster. They were a sapient species, entirely in control of their own actions, and the humans seemed to be the only ones who were squaring off to them.

That made the deathworlders allies, in his book, and Perfection represented an opportunity to make or break that relationship.

“The Hunters launched hundreds of kinetic weapons from orbit,” he said. “Perfection’s defence systems stopped all but thirteen of them.”

“The same kind of kinetic weapons that you dropped on Planet Garden,” Nwmrwnw observed, acidly. Tk’v ground his molars together. He would have given much not to have the junior subfleetmaster present for this.

Caruthers proved equal to the accusation. He looked Nwmrwnw in the eye in that unnervingly level way that humans did, and spoke softly and firmly though with no trace of disrespect. “The Hunters are dangerous,” he agreed. “And sadistic and cunning. They’re deliberately using our tactics and tools because they want to divide and weaken us.”

“Just as you weakened the defense fleet?” Nwmrwnw pressed.

“That will be all, junior subfleetmaster,” Tk’v told him, judging that his Kwmbwrw subordinate had gone too far with that remark. “Return to your duties.”

“…Yes, Grand Fleetmaster.”

The humans cleared their throats and looked awkwardly at one another as Nwmrwnw gestured grudging respect and stalked out of the command hub.

Tk’v raised his voice just enough for the other crew to hear, though he addressed the humans specifically. “I am sorry,” he said. “We have all seen terrible things through this operation, and it is difficult to remain objective.”

Caruthers caught on to what he was doing, and joined in. “I sympathize,” he declared. “And I’d like to thank you personally, Grand Fleetmaster, for setting an example and proving that our relationship doesn’t need to be antagonistic. We certainly don’t want it to be.”

“Nor should we.” Tk’v announced, taking note of which of his officers looked away, and which wore body language and expressions of agreement and resolve. “I have spent my life fighting the Hunters, and for the first time I am seeing signs of weakness from them. As you said, they are trying to divide us, and I do not think they would even care to try unless they were scared of what we could achieve together.”

Caruthers glanced at Manning and Devonald. Inexperienced as Tk’v was in reading human facial expressions, there was something… inspiring in the way they all shared the same intense smile.

“In that case, Grand Fleetmaster…” Caruthers extended his hand, “I look forward to scaring them some more.”

Tk’v shook hands with him for the second time. “Well said.”

Date Point 10y4m3w3d AV
Celzi Alliance Embassy Station, Earth/Luna L3 Point, Sol

Rylee Jackson

“Celzi Diplomatic Station, this is FIREBIRD-ONE escorting diplomatic shuttle, request permission to land.”

Colonel Stewart would be doing the exact same thing over at the Dominion station at Earth/Luna L1. The timing was important - both of the major interstellar powers needed to be carefully removed from Sol, and they needed to be removed in such a way as to not escalate the tensions between them by making it seem like humanity was siding with either one.

The shuttle full of Marines were there in case the Hierarchy had an agent on board who tried something last-ditch like de-orbiting the station or whatever.

“Permission granted FIREBIRD-ONE. Welcome back major Jackson, you and the shuttle are cleared to land together in bay seven.”

She recognized the translated simulation of a voice from her previous visits to the Celzi station. PR being such a big part of Rylee’s job meant regular schmoozing with both sides. That was why she’d been chosen to lead this op: the embassy knew her.

Plus, if the need arose, her WSO Joe Semenza could nuke the station to molten debris. There was something satisfying about having that kind of gratuitous firepower at their fingertips.

They made their entrance with all the style and grace that her professional pride demanded, sliding smoothly into the bay on manual and kissing the deck with nary a bump. Her new sled, a replacement for the one lost on Garden, was called Phoenix and for once Rylee didn’t fully cycle her down - there was a non-zero chance after all that they’d have to make a hasty departure, and Phoenix wouldn’t lose too much of her capacitor’s stored energy from sitting idle on the deck for a few hours.

The Marines, she had to admit, made an even better entrance. The instant their shuttle’s ramp clanged down, two dozen of them in full MOPP marched down it like they were on parade. The two Celzi guards who had entered the hangar to greet her were probably shooting nervous glances at each other, though it was hard to tell with Celzi. They looked like a kind of moss-grey collision between a monkey, a kangaroo and a lizard, and their oddly-shaped skulls with their many eyes gave them fully overlapping three hundred and sixty degree vision. They didn’t need to turn their heads to look at each other.

Rylee left Semenza to look after Phoenix and approached the two aliens, carefully not removing her flight suit, though she did slide up her glare visor so that they could see her face. She probably looked quite an intimidating sight herself, in her astronaut’s “snoopy cap” and in the new flight suit that had been adapted from EV-MASS technology.

“Is… something wrong, major?” one of the aliens asked. She internally kicked herself for not being able to tell Celzi apart on sight. Oh well, time to play it impersonal rather than friendly.

“Call the ambassadors,” she ordered. “Something important has come up that needs their immediate attention.”

She wasn’t left waiting long. Stationwide announcements in a variety of alien languages rang through the decks, and within minutes she was being escorted, along with the marines, to the forum chamber on the station’s topmost deck.

She was met off the elevator by Ambassador Sandeep Verma. Verma’s career had been an interesting one, taking him from his native Gujarat, to the Indian consulate in Canberra, and ultimately into space to be humanity’s ambassador to the Celzi Alliance.

Rylee had worked with him several times. Something about being the FTL test pilot kept her snowed under with invitations to assorted diplomatic parties, hence why one of her AFSCs was Public Affairs. She could definitely sympathize with the ambassador’s crowded and storied career.

That same prestige was what had sent her on this mission. It was important not to snub either side or to show favorites, so while the Dominion got the senior officer in the form of colonel Stewart, the Alliance got the more notorious one in the form of major Jackson. They’d tossed a coin over it.

“Major?” Verma had a smile on, but his body language was wary. Rylee shook his hand. Really she shouldn’t waste time with preamble, but the ambassador didn’t need rushing.

“Can we talk privately?” she asked as she handed him the sealed letter marked ‘EYES ONLY’ for his attention. It was an uninteresting grey and bore the emblem of the Global Representative Assembly - a circle, two short arc sections sharing the same center, a longer one, and finally a short one again.

Verma nodded and pulled a device from his pocket. A privacy forcefield fuzzed and opaqued the air around them. He ripped the seal on the letter and read it.

“Short version: Big Hotel is gone,” Rylee informed him. The Ambassadors by necessity were both briefed on DEEP RELIC. “Earth’s secure and the GRA wants the embassies relocated to Cimbrean-five just to be absolutely certain.”

Verma grimaced slightly, but nodded as he read the letter. It was much longer than Rylee’s summary, but probably contained about the same amount of useful information.

“They are not going to like that,” he observed.

“The ID are being kicked out as well,” Rylee explained. “So neither side gets to claim we’re siding with the other.”

“They still will not like it…”

“They can dislike it all they want, one way or the other this station ain’t gonna be here much longer,” Rylee said, dismissively. “They’re being relocated. They can go amicably and relocate to Cimbrean, or they can be expelled… with extreme prejudice.”

Verma met her eye, then nodded and turned the page, read the name and signature that occupied the top two inches of an otherwise empty sheet (a classic and typical waste of paper, in Rylee’s opinion), then handed the letter back to her.

“I shall do my job, then,” he promised.

“Good,” Rylee smiled for him, radiating absolute faith in his abilities. “Let us know if we need to get you off the station. These guys aren’t just pretending to be marines."

“Not necessary,” Verma smiled. “I hope. Thank you anyway.”

He turned off the privacy field and gestured invitingly for Rylee and the marines to follow him. He swept into the forum with an impressive impromptu air of gravitas, looking thoroughly out of place and vulnerable next to a woman in a lightly-armored spacesuit and a dozen men in MOPP.

Rylee lowered her visor again. The odd thing was that she probably cut the most threatening and alien figure among them. MOPP - Mission Oriented Protective Posture - made the marines faceless and scary, but the technology hadn’t changed much in twenty years meaning that the men wearing it looked huge and encumbered, but also embarrassingly low-tech. It was a good show of strength… but Rylee knew from experience that while aliens were often impressed by seeing humans carry heavy loads, there was something they found even more intimidating about the human body itself - the shape of it, the way they moved. For whatever reason, aliens saw the same thing in a walking human that humans saw in a stalking tiger.

MOPP hid that. Rylee’s flight suit didn’t. It was built by C&M Spacesuit Systems using the technology they’d developed for EV-MASS, making it snug, sleek and technical. A far cry from the bulky thing she’d worn eight years ago in Pandora’s early flights, with its duct tape modifications and velcro patch inside the helmet for scratching her nose.

Rylee secretly geeked out about it all the time. It looked like it had been created by the better class of digital artist, the ones who managed to balance a high-tech aesthetic with actual military function and practicality.

In the circumstances, it was not only a good way to show off that scary deathworlder physiology, but also a statement: ‘Look how far we’ve come, and how quickly.’

It worked. She became the immediate focus of attention when they stepped into the forum itself. Never mind the geodesic dome overhead with its angel’s-eye view of the Earth, never mind the charcoal concrete floor with the polished bronze forked spiral - a stylized representation of the galaxy - embossed in the middle. Never mind the warm lighting and the panelling on the wall made from several kinds of wood imported from the homeworlds of the Celzi, Qinis, Jeghiren and Lathk, nor the imposing and venerable ambassadors from those species sitting at their desks. It was a beautiful chamber - as if the Qinis would settle for an ugly one - and they’d invaded it looking decidedly ugly.

She ran her best fearsome eye over the lot of them, relying on the faceless mirror-black of her flight helmet to do all the communicating she needed. Only the Celzi ambassador failed to emote discomfort, but then again Celzi were notorious for not backing down easily. The whole Alliance was named after them for a reason.

“Ambassador Verma,” the Jeghiren ambassador stood. “You alarm us, with your sudden summons and your… troops.” They - Jeghiren were monogendered, and insisted on impersonal pronouns - waved an arm languidly at the marines. “We request an explanation.”

“The Global Representative Assembly has instructed me to inform you of a new development.” Verma replied, having apparently decided not to bother with circumspection. “You may not be aware of some security threats on Earth that we’ve been fighting, but that situation has now reached the point where we must ask both this embassy and that of the Dominion to relocate to the Cimbrean system.”

The Lathk ambassador was the first to speak. Lathk defied easy description, being a bipedal biological eccentricity whose tiny beady black eyes gave them almost no vision to speak of, and who had neither a sense of smell nor much apparently in the way of a sense of taste. Their primary sense by a country mile was hearing, and in place of a head they had two gargantuan ears mounted high and forward on their shoulders.

Those ears and their spindly birdlike limbs always gave Rylee the impression that they would go tumbling away in a strong breeze, and she had to chew down the racist impulse to think they looked absurd. They were actually an important partner in the Alliance, providing for most of the agriculture and a steady supply of warm bodies. Even if the war had been in a low ebb for the last ten years (thanks in no small part to human intervention) the Alliance were still rattling every saber they had, and that meant signing up young beings - among them plenty of Lathk - to serve on whatever new front line might open up if a lasting peace wasn’t eventually worked out.

“You are picking a side?” she asked.

Ambassador Verma’s job over the last four years had included exerting whatever gentle pressure humanity could muster to keep the war from boiling over again. The Celzi leadership might have been reckoned as master strategists, but Rylee was pretty sure that any second lieutenant with Sun Tzu and Robert A. Heinlein on their bookshelf already had a more comprehensive strategic education than the most seasoned Celzi general officer. The war so far had been catastrophically bloody and industrial.

But of course the Dominion was too proud to let the “rebels” win by granting them whatever territory they’d already carved out, and the Alliance was too proud to settle for what they had.

“No.” Verma’s assertion was instant and firm. “We remain committed to the neutrality and independence of our species.”

“Then what are these troops for?” The Celzi ambassador asked.

“And why are they wearing protective gear?” The Qinis ambassador added, taking the bait.

That was Rylee’s cue. “Our equipment is a precautionary measure. We hope it proves unnecessary…” she hinted, smoothly. ETs were notoriously gullible when on the back foot, and while outright lies were present in the diplomatic toolbox, in the years since Rylee herself had summoned these two space stations into orbit around Earth, the most effective tool by far that humanity’s diplomats had fallen back on time and again was crypticism. Deathworld reputation did the rest.

The ambassadors all glanced at one another (again, insofar as she could tell. She wasn’t even sure Celzi could turn their head) and after a few seconds the Jeghiren spoke again. “What is the exact nature of this security concern?" they asked.

“We’re not at liberty to disclose that information for now,” Verma replied. “Please. There will be plenty of time later to discuss exactly why this is being done but for now it’s safest for the embassies to relocate to Cimbrean.”

“We shall need to discuss-” the Celzi began, and Verma cut him off.

“Ambassadors, please do not mistake this for a request,” he said, firmly. “This relocation is a condition of continuing to have a relationship with the human race.”

Rylee consciously didn’t fidget during the long moment of deliberation that followed. There was a low, but non-zero chance that if there was a Hierarchy demon among the ambassadors, and if they had any last-ditch contingencies to try, this would be the moment. WERBS was lurking in the wings, ready to obliterate the station the moment it lit a jump beacon.

Knowing that by far the most destructive thing that humanity had ever built was aimed at the soles of Rylee’s feet was a test of composure to almost rival the infamous rubber chicken. Another benefit to the inscrutable visor - the ETs couldn’t see her sweat.

“…Very well,” the Celzi grunted at last. He leaned over and spoke softly into a microphone on his desk. Rylee breathed a sigh of relief and touched the push-to-talk button on the side of her helmet.

“ILIUM, this is HELEN. PARIS has agreed to relocate.” she announced, softly.

“Copy that, HELEN. AGAMEMNON is also relocating.”

“Awesome.” Rylee breathed a sigh of relief. “I’ll prepare a slaved jump.”

“Understood. We’ll send a runnner to Cimbrean for codes. ILIUM out.”

She turned to Verma. “Okay, the jump’s all set up. I need to get back to Phoenix to play cab driver."

“Go ahead,” Verma invited. “Thank you, major. I think your presence helped tremendously.”

“Don’t thank me until we’re safely around Cimbrean Five,” Rylee replied. She certainly wouldn’t be happy until the station was outside of the Cimbrean system field where no possible Hierarchy action could threaten humanity through it, and where it no longer needed to have an FTL superweapon aimed at it.

She turned and marched out, with two of the marines in tow, and put in the call to Semenza to fire the sled up. She leaned against the elevator wall as they headed back down to the hangar deck, and reflected that going from interspecies celebrity to messenger girl to threatening muscle to glorified truck driver in one afternoon was a pretty good summary of her career.

She stretched and sighed. “You boys been in space before?”

One of the marines chuckled under his hood. “No ma’am.”

“Not exactly glamorous, is it?”

“I dunno,” the other one piped up. “Maybe it’s just wore off for you, ma’am. I was nerding out the whole time we were in there talking to them ETs.”

Rylee had to laugh and nod agreement to that, smiling inside her helmet. “Maybe,” she agreed. “Maybe it has.”

Date Point 10y4m3w3d AV
Eppley Airfield, Omaha, Nebraska, USA, Earth

Kevin Jenkins

“But you’re an exec! Aren’t you a bit senior to be standing at the airport with a sign?”

Kevin shrugged, a pointless gesture in a phone call, but still a natural and unthinking one. “These kids are important,” he replied smoothly. “And no offense Walter, but I’m the only other Abductee in the whole Byron Group. They’re gonna need to hear what I’ve got to say.”

Walter Billings scoffed. That was why Kevin liked the man - he didn’t guard his manners among The Team.

The Team was a loose idea, and it consisted of everybody involved behind the scenes in bringing Byron Group Exploration Vessel 11 from conception to space. Walter and his lifelong colleague and best friend Jennifer McAllister, Clara Brown nee Ericson and her father Michael. The implacable Mr. Williams (whose given name of Raymond was one of Kevin’s most cherished secrets - the man himself hated it), Moses Byron, and of course Kevin himself.

“Didn’t Xiu Chang break your nose? Williams wasn’t happy to hear that. He’s still grousing about ‘loose cannon behaviour’, you know.”

“She’ll be great. She was just having a hard time adjusting to Terran life again and I pressed the wrong buttons,” Kevin replied. "Trust me, Walter. I know these kids, I know what they’ve been through, and I wanna put a human face on what’s going to happen to them. And if I can maybe give them some advice that’ll help them get through what Keating and those other stone-faced assholes have planned…"

“Protecting the bet you put on them, eh?”

“You bet on them too, Walter.”

“…You’re right. Advise away. Just tell me you’re going to be back in the office sometime today, because I urgently need to discuss the waste processor design with you.”

Kevin chuckled. “Well shit, how can I refuse an offer like that?” he asked. “I’ll be right in after I drop them off at the Box.”

“I’ll see you then. Bring popcorn.”

It was Kevin’s turn to scoff, and Billings ended the call laughing.

Kevin adjusted his collar - there wasn’t a force on the planet Earth or any other world besides that would persuade him to wear a tie - and leaned on the railing again, well aware that alongside the other people loitering against it with cards in their hands, he probably stood out in being by far the most well-dressed. There was just something about a properly tailored expensive suit that left the slightly faded chauffeurs’ uniforms and short-sleeve shirts or polos to either side of him looking like they belonged in the background.

As it happened, Chang, Buehler and Etsicitty had apparently listened to the Group’s request to not bring more than a few small personal effects, and hadn’t burdened themselves with anything more than their carry-on luggage. They were the first ones to come out of Arrivals, each one carrying a smallish bag and the clothes on their backs, and all dressed comfortably for travel. Kevin got their attention with a wave, pointed with a movement of his head, and met them at the end of the rank with a round of handshakes.

“Figured I’d collect you in person,” he said. “All sorted out up in Minnesota?”

“We packed it all up and fixed everything. The place should be okay without us for a couple years.” Julian replied.

“Good. Heck of a commitment you’re making.”

“It’s what we want,” Xiu told him. When Kevin looked questioningly at her, she shrugged. “You were right.”

“…Sorry.”

“Didn’t you two already apologize to each other?" Allison asked. She jerked her head towards the airport’s doors. “Come on, if we’re making a big commitment, let’s commit.”

Julian and Xiu both chuckled, hoisted their bags and followed her, chorusing “Yes ma’am” like it was a private in-joke of theirs, which it probably was.

Kevin jogged a few steps to catch up with her. “Ain’t gonna be easy,” he warned. “You’re not the only team on the list. You’re the favorites, but you’ve got competition.”

“Have the others been out there before?” Allison asked.

“That’s why you’re the favorites, they haven’t. But they’re no slouches. Veterans, doctors, top qualifications… they all have the right stuff."

“What’s your point, Jenkins?”

Kevin stepped in front of her and stopped them all by raising his hands. “My point is that the only person in the whole Byron Group who actually cares about you guys getting this gig is me. No false manipulative bullshit this time, okay, I know what it’s like. It took me fuckin’ years to finally find a place for myself."

Allison just gave him a get-to-the-point stare while behind her, Xiu and Julian exchanged a glance.

“Look-” he continued “The other would-be crews competing against you? They’re fine. If they don’t get the job, it’ll be like whatever to them, right? They’re not Abductees, they don’t fuckin’… they’ll still fit. Right? Now have any of you given serious thought to what’s gonna happen or how you’re gonna do if you don’t earn this?"

They hadn’t. He could read it in all three of their faces, but he waited for them all to look at each other, come to the same conclusion, and return their attention to him. “Then for the love of Elvis please, please listen to me, and listen good ’cause I’ve only got the one chance to tell you this stuff."

They relaxed, nodded, and listened.

Date Point 10y4m3w3d AV
Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Gabriel Ares

Gabriel loved his job, but it came with a price of having precious little in the way of spare time. Cimbrean Colonial Security was a tight ship, full of some of the most dedicated, highly-trained and passionate police officers he’d ever had the pleasure of working with, who were policing what was largely an educated, professional and successful population.

On the policing front, usually the worst he had to deal with were Gaoians. Gaoian males fought constantly. In their culture, for two males to clash and walk away with permanent disfiguring scars was not only commonplace, it was practically necessary. It was a rare male who could catch the eyes of Folctha’s small population of Sisters without some impressive duelling scars.

By human standards, of course, the fights were aggravated assault shading to outright attempted murder in some of the nastier cases. Nobody knew better than CCS that Gaoians were emphatically not cute and fluffy space-raccoons. They were an alien species with alien morality, and sometimes that alien morality got blood on the walls.

Then there was liaising with the military. Cimbrean was in many ways arguably better-protected than Earth thanks to its status as the permanent home of the SOR and of the allied space fleet. Sure, that space fleet was exclusively British for the time being, but with the USS San Diego and its sisters in the works that was due to change, and Gabriel knew from discussions with Admiral Knight that they were trying hard to get their hands on a Dominion- built orbital shipyard to give the ships a permanent anchorage.

Then there was the SOR. Gabriel really didn’t know how he felt about the SOR. Having a cadre of unnervingly big and strong almost-supersoldiers stomping around the town putting every gym rat on both Cimbrean and Earth to shame and between them accounting for an impressive percentage of Folctha’s family- planning spending…

Well. That was almost as disconcerting as the fact that his only son was one of them.

The Air Force had been one thing. Watching Adam spend his sixteenth year growing from wiry teen to a fit youth had been proud. Watching that fit youth become a dense, powerful airman had lifted Gabriel’s soul. Watching that dense and powerful airman gain in endurance and strength as he went through Pararescue training had impressed on him just how strong the boy really was.

Or so he’d thought. The SOR had redefined those limits, converting a merely exceptionally fit and strong young man into a titan, something straight out of Greek legend, or perhaps the more comic-book kind of barbarian hero.

That hadn’t lifted Gabriel’s soul at all. Quite the opposite - it had impressed on him just how broken the boy really was.

Not that he could blame him.

It was with a sense of trepidation, therefore, that he’d agreed to a movie night with Adam and John at Adam’s penthouse apartment on Demeter Road. If there was one thing he’d definitely say for the USAF, it was financially generous to the men who sacrificed for it - every man in the SOR had come to Cimbrean with a pocket full of homesteading money and, thanks to the regimented and tightly controlled nature of their lifestyles which necessitated that the Regiment pay for almost everything, precious little in the way of living expenses.

Even with Folctha’s relatively steep taxes, Gabriel suspected that Adam had tens of thousands in spending money and savings that he didn’t know what to do with. And a little thing like inviting his old man to visit on the rare occasion when their days off overlapped wouldn’t be setting him back by much either.

If only the gigantic brat had bothered to remember that Gabriel was nursing a years-old femoral nerve injury that made steps a literal pain in the ass. There was no elevator in the building that Adam co-owned with Wilson Akiyama, just eight flights of stairs and it took Gabe twenty minutes to climb them. He leaned heavily on his cane at the top to recover, reflecting that despite his best efforts at fitness and rehabilitation, his mobility was never coming back.

Finally, he knocked on the door. Adam opened it in seconds, and smothered Gabe in an enormous muscular hug. “Hey! ¿Estas bien? Llegas tarde…"

““Subia estas escaleras de mierda,” Gabe replied pointedly, nodding back at the obstacle that had held him up.

Adam looked at them, then at his stick, and the penny made a solid wooden thunk as it finally dropped.

“Ah… shit.”

Gabe chuckled and reached up to affectionately ruffle what little hair Adam had kept. “¿Es un caballo de guerra, o un burro de guerra?" he joked.

Adam chuckled and welcomed him inside.

The apartment was definitely a well-off bachelor’s party pad. It was furnished with style and elegance, and was comfortable enough, but didn’t look like it was regularly lived in. Despite the best efforts of the hired cleaners, the place had a permanent after-party olfactory background of booze, BO and sex. No cannabis though: even though it was just as legal as alcohol in Folctha, the SOR were forbidden from touching the stuff..

The Spanish had to come to an end when John leaned round the dividing wall between the lounge and the kitchen. “Hey Mr. Ares!”

“Hello, John. What’s cooking?”

“Jerky! Gonna need another hour, but this is my grampa’s recipe. Best you’ll ever taste, trust me.”

Gabe glanced at Adam, who nodded with a grin. “It is,” he confirmed.

"Bueno! What are we watching?"

“Good question,” Adam said. “Base?”

John had gone still. Slowly, he turned and gave them an embarrassed brittle smile. “A… movie that I, uh, forgot to bring with me!”

“Top marks. Well done, dumbass.” Adam applauded sarcastically.

John cleared his throat and aimed his thumb at the door. “I’ll go get it. It’s on base.”

“That’s three miles away.” Gabriel pointed out.

“Yuh. Be back in half an hour. Peace.” John took off down the stairs, springing down them two at a time.

“He’s going to run the whole way there and back in half an hour?” Gabriel asked.

“No big deal.” Adam shrugged. “So hey! Just you and me for half an hour. Beer?”

“Sounds good.”

Gabe sank gratefully onto the couch, a maneuver that really demonstrated just how much he needed his cane, and sat back, happy to finally have the weight off his bad leg.

It was no ordinary couch. When Adam slammed down into it a few seconds later with a couple of open beers, it barely seemed to register him despite his incredible mass. He kicked his feet up onto the coffee table and gestured at the TV to turn it on, an innovation that had slowly started to replace the old-fashioned remote control.

“-relocation of the embassies has already met with vocal criticism from the Dominion, and while the Royal Navy continues to lend support in the humanitarian crisis on Perfection, Dominion officials are now blaming the attack on human military action in that system, claiming that there was some kind of battle. While the Ministry of Defence, the Pentagon and Scotch Creek all declined to comment, sources at Hephaestus LLC have confirmed that HMS Caledonia is now in drydock at the Ceres shipyard undergoing emergency repairs and in Manchester, England, the family of Petty Officer Thomas Kendrick, who served aboard Caledonia, have released a statement asking for privacy-”

“Not that they’re gonna fuckin’ get it,” Adam grumbled.

“That’s not the media’s job,” Gabe agreed. “You know what happened?”

“Marty told me. The ship caught fire.”

“Marty?”

“Shit, haven’t I told you about Marty?” Adam turned on the couch, shedding grimness and disgust with the media like a light summer coat.

“No…?”

“Oh, man, Marty’s just the fuckin’ best! Makes me look dumb as a bag’a rocks, funny, sexy as all hell-"

Gabriel threw up his hands to interrupt the boy, feeling completely knocked off-balance. “Woah, woah, amigo! …Seriously?"

“Yeah! I’ve even thought up a great venue for a first date, and-”

“Wow.” Gabriel blinked at his only son and assembled his thoughts. “…Okay. That’s some big news.”

Adam blinked at him. “What?”

“Man, I just… I mean, I never would have guessed. I mean, I love you anyway amigo, but you really could have broken the news more gently-!"

“…Martina, Dad! Her name’s Martina!"

“OHHH!” Gabe relaxed and laughed at the ceiling, wiping his forehead. He was too relieved to feel embarrassed. "Gracias a Dios!"

Adam’s enormous shoulders rocked as he wheezed out his best Muttley laugh, and he gave Gabe a huge, crushing hug. “Nah, nah, nah… You’ve got nothing to worry about there, I promise.”

“Good, because I had a vision of a world without grandkids and I didn’t like it!” Gabe chuckled.

“Well I mean, we’re not even dating yet…” Adam cleared his throat. “So, you’re gonna have to wait a bit, yeah?”

“Hmmm… Are you sure you’re ready to date her? It’s kind of early, Amigo. What’s it been, three months? Less than?"

Adam turned the TV down as the news turned its attention to the sport. “She’s not like Ava. She’s SOR, she knows the deal.”

“That’s the opposite of encouraging.”

“You think so?”

Gabe nodded to himself, at once glad and slightly disappointed to learn that the side of beef sat next to him was definitely still the same Adam.

“Adam… maybe this Martina would understand the why of it a bit better, sure… but apart from that bit at the end there where she ran out of hope and did something stupid, Ava was as patient with you as any girl could be. Marty might be more understanding, but that’s not a license for you to just do your thing and treat her as something you do in your spare time.”

“I wouldn’t-”

“You already did." Gabe pointed out. "And you just called off a long-term relationship less than three months ago. You sure you’re not just thinking with that big warhorse verga of yours?"

“Dad!”

“What? I know how you got your nickname, man. Hell, you’ve been saluting the dawn since you were twelve. Good for you, you take after your old man!”

“I really didn’t need to know that…!"

Gabe chuckled. “Hey, it’s just my right leg that doesn’t work properly," he winked. Judging that the boy was suitably embarrassed, he relented. “But it’s not for thinking with, Amigo. Are you really after another committed relationship right now, or do you just wanna smash?"

Adam looked away. “I… shit, Dad, now you’ve got me second-guessing,” he complained.

“Good! You should second-guess. I second-guess all the time." Gabriel patted him on his huge and startlingly hard shoulder. “It’s a good way to avoid hurting the people you really care for.”

Adam nodded and said nothing for a minute or so. “I guess… I do want an actual relationship,” he said, “but I dunno. Am I ready for one? You’re right, I fucked up the last one pretty bad. Marty’s special, Dad, I don’t wanna hurt her like I did Ava.”

Gabe nodded sympathetically. “Then my advice is don’t go for it until you’ve got more experience,” he suggested. “Have fun with some other girls you don’t care about so much first. Break a few hearts so you learn how not to break hers. After all, nobody climbed Everest for their first mountain, did they?"

“I guess but… are you sure?”

“If she’s that special to you, you need to know how to do it right. And right now you don’t," Gabe told him. “No, I’m not sure, and I don’t think it’d be the right advice for everyone… But I think it’s the right advice for you, here and now."

“I’ll think ’bout it.” Adam rumbled, awkwardly.

“Good. I don’t want you to just blindly follow advice just because I gave it. You’ve got a damn good brain, Amigo, I wanna see you using it, okay?"

Adam hugged him. “…Love you, Dad.”

“Love you too,” Gabe promised, feeling his upper back creak and pop. “Maybe show your love by getting this crippled old man another beer?”

“Yeah, yeah…” Adam laughed, and launched himself easily to his feet before picking his way toward the fridge in that curiously agile and quiet way of his that belied how heavy he was. “Don’t overplay that disability card though.”

Gabriel chuckled and settled into the couch, looking forward to a long and comfortable evening. “I’m sure my soul will survive a small abuse of power," he said.

Date Point 10y4m3w3d AV
Finchley, London, UK, Earth

Simon Harvey

Simon had always, in a faintly racist and absent-mindedly English way, thought of Spanish as a beautiful and romantic language, evoking imagery of holiday sun, bulls, tomatoes and siestas.

Ava Rios, however, could spit it like dragon breath: a potent blend of fire and venom that sneered at the need for translation. You didn’t need to know what the words meant to know what they meant. Though, frankly, her skill at English profanity was no less impressive, and Sean could match her blow-for- verbal-blow.

A door slammed. A rumbling, angry pause later, she stomped down the stairs in her boots and a thundercloud of quiet vulgarities. She didn’t see Simon at all as she stormed into the kitchen and yanked the fridge open, angrily rattling several blameless bottles and upsetting the broccoli.

She stared wildly into it for a few seconds, then shut the door, leaned against it heavily and was suddenly crying instead.

He couldn’t blame her for being mad. When Sean and he had returned from Egypt, they’d still damn near been leaking sand on the doormat when Sean had launched into interrogating her about what, exactly, had happened since they’d parted ways at the embassy in Cairo.

This had irritated and upset her, but she’d kept her cool and patiently explained that she was bound by the kind of Non-Disclosure Agreement that no sane or self-interested person would be inclined to break.

Sean had pushed, and Simon had carefully retreated into the kitchen so as to remove himself from the vicinity of the escalating row. Ava had testily informed Sean that unless he was volunteering to take her place on Death Row, he could forget it. Sean had dismissed the possibility that either of them would end up there, and had gone so far as to hint that she was just trying to get back in the SOR’s good books.

Ava had, rather irately, informed him that that ship was long sailed and that she probably couldn’t get back in those gentlemen’s good books if she had a hundred years to work on it. The first minor swear word had lurked unnoticed in the middle of her explanation.

Simon had made himself a cup of tea. Sean’s kettle was quite a loud one, which had mercifully obscured the conversation, but its sense of dramatic timing was impeccable, because it had clicked off perfectly in time for him to hear:

“Fine! Keep lying! It’s what you’re best at!"

Simon had hung his head and groaned as the dragon fire started flying. He could hardly blame her either - in fact while the argument had swirled around the whole house he had drunk his tea and quietly resolved to give his idiot nephew a ringing clout upside the head when he got the chance.

He cleared his throat.

She flinched, turned around and wiped her face, fighting back some control. “Shit, Simon, I’m sorry, I forgot you were there…”

“Are you okay?”

Ava sighed, shook her head, then changed her mind, shrugged and nodded. “I’ve had worse fights…”

Simon nodded by way of accepting the answer. “If you don’t mind my asking…?”

“No, sure.” She opened the fridge again and got out the filter jug full of cold water.

“Sean’s always been a bit of a fucking wanker sometimes, but I’ve never known him be that… well, that nasty before. What happened with you two?"

Ava sat down. “I used him to cheat on my boyfriend,” she said, stating it so bluntly and mercilessly that Simon was put in mind of a flagellant scourging their own back.

“Oh, Ava… you bloody idiot." Simon groaned, not unkindly.

“Yeah. Biggest mistake of my life.” She poured herself a drink and sipped it.

“…If I can-”

“Ask.”

“And you’re living with him? Despite that?”

“I…”

Ava glanced toward the door, as if Sean might have magically stealthed down the stairs without either of them detecting even the faintest whisper.

“…Simon, I make, like, just enough money to pay my rent and my half of the bills here. And that’s only because he’s renting the room to me for way, way less than it’s worth. I’ve got no savings, no spare money to save up… If I could afford it, I’d get the fuck out of here right now, but I can’t."

“Couldn’t you move back to Cimbrean? I hear the living is cheap there?”

“Not cheap enough.”

“Can’t your family help? Your dad’s the head of Cimbrean Colonial Security, isn’t he?”

“I’m not going to beg off Dad! I’m set up here, I’m getting by. I won’t burden them with more of my shit-"

He interrupted her. “How much would you need?”

“Wh-? Simon, are you offering me money?”

“How much?” he repeated.

“I can’t take your money!”

“Just answer the question, Ava.”

She exhaled irritably and thought about it. “It… Depends. Uh, if I rent out there… I guess a couple of thousand to tide me over and get set up?”

Simon nodded, and fished his phone out of his pocket.

“No, Simon-!”

“Ava, listen to me.” Simon set his phone down. “I have a house in Islington. Not a flat, a house. You know what the property prices are like in this city, so you know I can afford to loan you a couple of thousand."

“But you barely-”

“It’s my money and I’ll do whatever the hell I like with it, thank you very much.”

“But… why?”

“Because I’ve got two very talented young journalists on my hands who won’t be able to work together.” He raised a hand to intercept her interruption. “Don’t bullshit me. Your professional relationship with Sean is built on drama and fuck all else, and arguments like that… If I don’t separate you two, something’s going to happen that ruins both your reputations, and by extension your careers. This is the best fix.”

“You’re sure?”

“You don’t deserve to suffer for him being a complete tit, and he doesn’t deserve to suffer for you not having your shit sorted out.” Simon put it bluntly. She showed no sign of taking offense.

He picked up the phone again. “I’ll put in a call to a mate of mine, he said something about somebody starting up a news channel in Folctha. A pretty local girl like you could be making big money in front of the camera rather than behind it, so you’ll be able to pay me back soon enough. Throw in ten percent if you feel you have to, feed me leads, however you want to repay me, however your conscience tells you to. But for God’s sake don’t be stupid enough to try and tough it out with Sean.”

He wasn’t quite sure why, but that last warning seemed to score a hit. Ava looked down and away, chewed on her lip and frowned.

“….Simon…. thank you. Really. But I don’t think-”

“Ava.”

She stopped babbling her protests, blinked at him, then licked her lips and tried again, rather more calmly. “I want to earn my way, Simon." she said. “I don’t want charity.”

“This isn’t charity,” Simon said, “it’s an investment and it’s career advice from the old guard to the new kid. And I believe it’s a damned safe investment too: if I put in a good word for you, it will carry weight, and that’s not charity either - you earned that good word."

She swallowed, and looked at his phone with her resolve obviously wavering, so Simon gave her one last push.

“Go home," he said.

Date Point 10y4m3w3d AV
Omaha, Nebraska, USA, Earth

Allison Buehler

“This is it?”

Kevin cranked the parking brake and nodded. “This is the Box.” he confirmed.

“Good name,” Xiu remarked while giving the ‘Box’ a wide-eyed, cautious look. Allison evaluated it herself with a slightly more guarded expression. When the Group had talked about ‘accommodations throughout the training period’, she had imagined a decent-sized house. Nothing elaborate, just a couple of bedrooms, a bathroom…

Not a box. That really was all it was, a featureless half-cube squatting smack in the middle of a fenced and tree-lined Byron Group compound like a particularly obtuse art installation and surrounded by three wings of a more building-like building that was all huge glass windows and warm brown wood. Jenkins’ ID had seen them past the security at the gate without issue, and he parked up a short distance from the welcome party who emerged from the larger building.

“So yeah, the Box is a mockup of the interior of the ship you’ll be flying. Idea is you guys are gonna have to get used to it, so you may as well do that here on Earth so you can back out if you have to. Don’t want y’all going stir- crazy three months into a two year mission.”

“Looks… snug,” Julian suggested, taking refuge in understatement.

“Trust me, it’s even smaller on the inside.” Jenkins glanced apologetically at him in the rear-view mirror. “Anyway, the rest of this is the training facility and mission support. All the people workin’ in this building are here to do one of two things - teach you the skills you need to do this, or make sure you’ve got the chops for it. Odds are you won’t ever even meet half’a them, but they’ll know you better than you know yourselves, and fast too.”

“So this is it, then.” Xiu fidgeted with her bag. “This is where you leave us?”

“Yup. Remember, like I said - these guys are gonna try and fail you. You can’t bullshit them, so don’t even try. They ask you a question, best thing is to answer it honestly and directly. They can’t order you around, but it’d be a damn good idea to follow their instructions anyway. Don’t suck up to them, they ain’t after brown-nosers, but just… be honest, and be yourselves."

“Thanks.” Julian reached forward, and Kevin twisted in his seat to shake hands over his shoulder.

Allison and finally Xiu followed suit and then, there being no reason to delay the future any more, they got out of the car. Jenkins drove away as soon as the doors were all closed.

There was an awkward moment of wary sizing-up, and then an aging man in a blue polo shirt stepped forward.

“It’s nice to finally meet you guys,” he said. “Doctor Michael Ericson, I’m the team leader for BGEV Eleven.”

They made their introductions. Ericson scored points by making sure he got the pronunciation of Xiu’s name down properly before introducing them to the rest of his team, including his daughter and several other colleagues. The list of names was bewildering.

“Don’t worry,” Ericson said reassuringly, once the last introductions were made. “We’ll be working together for the next six months, you’ll have plenty of time to get to know us.”

Allison looked at Julian and Xiu. They were standing close to each other and gave her an identical, slightly wide-eyed look that said ‘lead on’, so she mustered more determination than she really felt now that they were really here, really doing this, and nodded firmly.

“I guess we should dive in then,” she said.

“Excellent!” Ericson beamed. He stepped aside and a man who hadn’t yet been introduced to them stepped forward. Allison tried not to take an immediate disliking to the newcomer - he had the stern expression of somebody who was evaluating her and rating her only slightly above something he’d stepped in. “Mr. Keating here will introduce you to your living space and carry out your first assessment.”

There was a round of handshakes and promises of ‘looking forward to working with-’ and ‘see you on-’ and the BGEV-11 team drifted away, leaving Allison, Julian and Xiu alone with Keating.

He didn’t ingratiate himself at all with his brusque attitude. “Here’s how it is,” he began without preamble. “The three of you have signed up for spending several months in training together followed by two years in the ship together, and the ship is small. Your notions of privacy and personal space are going to have to change drastically, and quickly. You are literally going to be living on top of each other with precious few opportunities to escape and that’s going to mean you’ll either be the very best of companions, or you’re going to end up hating each other… in which case, you won’t make the grade and won’t be flying on that ship. You are making a commitment to long- term physical and emotional intimacy. I- Oh."

Allison looked down. Xiu had taken her hand, and Julian’s too, and was giving Keating a level ‘please-get-on-with-it’ expression. There was a three-way round of eye contact among them, and Keating visibly cut out part of his script.

“Good,” he said. “But save the decision for after you’ve seen what you’ll be living in.”

He led them round to what was unmistakably an airlock. “The Box is supposed to be a close copy of what the final interior of BGEV-Eleven will look like. This is a quadruple-seal lock, plenty of redundancy. Nevertheless, good entry and exit practice will be a necessary part of your drill. Every time you leave or enter the Box, you’ll go through the procedure I’m about to show you. Failing to do so will be a black mark against you. Do you understand?”

They nodded, and Keating entered a code. “Tomorrow you’ll each be setting your own code,” he said, “and we’ll be explaining the safety rationale behind that in your first mission briefing. For now, all you need to know is that it’s vital not to share your codes. They help us track your comings and goings, and also serve an important security function.”

“Now,” he continued, stepping through the outer lock doors as they opened. “The first step is sealing and decontamination. Come on!”

They squeezed into the lock alongside him. It was actually surprisingly spacious - Allison could have wheeled a couple of motorcycles through it side by side. “Don’t stand in the yellow spaces.” Keating instructed. “The doors behind you will close…” they did so “…and you should select your decontamination cycle. The doors in front won’t open until you’ve decontaminated unless you throw the emergency override, which is only to be used if you’re abandoning ship or if you’re returning to the ship with a life- threatening injury.”

He gestured to a touch-screen with green, yellow and red icons on it. “Green is basic. Just a filter field. Coupled with your Frontline implants it should suffice in almost every case. Yellow is for when you’ve been exposed to radioactive or chemical contaminants. If you select that one you’ll need to remove and discard your clothing into this chute.”

Xiu wanted to ask a question, Allison knew, but held her peace. Keating either didn’t notice, or didn’t care. “Red,” he finished, “is the works, and is for use in cases where you think you’ve been contaminated with some kind of deadly agent that could spell doom for the whole species if it got back to Earth. In this case, you’ll need to strip and shower, shave off all your hair, you’ll be powdered and bio-fielded, and kept in quarantine for a minimum of forty-eight hours. When in doubt, use the highest setting. Hair grows back, but death is forever.”

Allison felt Xiu huddle in a little closer to her. She knew Xiu was a bit vain about her hair, which meant that the prospect of having to shave it all off…!

She surreptitiously put a reassuring arm around Xiu’s waist as Keating selected the green option and the familiar yellow shimmer of a biofilter forcefield swept across them, completely with that uncomfortable too-clean feeling that left Allison itching and having to resist the urge to run her tongue over teeth that suddenly felt unnaturally smooth and sterile.

“This is all simulated, right?” Julian asked.

“Accurately.”

Keating seemed to be determined to intimidate and scare them. He introduced them to the “Excursion Room” that lay beyond the airlock - basically a glorified equipment closet with an armory bench and lockers taking up every square inch of wall, floor and ceiling. To their left as they entered was a door marked “Pilot” and opposite the airlock was another door marked “lab”.

Keating said nothing more about them than that they’d have the chance to become familiar with their workstations in due course. He indicated to the right, pointing out the door at the end that led into “Engineering”, assorted access hatches marked “waste processing” and “atmosphere”, and the two doors marked “Pantry” and “Habitation”.

Everything he indicated was a safety or failsafe, everything he told them about procedure was a dire warning. It was obviously calculated to rattle them, and Allison treated the attempt with the contempt it deserved. They weren’t children, all three of them had literally almost died of vacuum exposure. Being lectured unnecessarily on safety by a pigshit little man who probably had never got further than thirty thousand feet from Earth’s surface was just…

She reined in her mounting indignation. Kevin’s advice on that score had been solid and worth listening to. ‘Everything they do will be a test’ he’d said. ‘If they’re irritating the fuck out of you, for fuck’s sake keep a lid on it because they’re testing your composure.’

So she took a cleansing breath when she judged that Keating wasn’t looking, and caught Julian’s eye. Composed and laid-back as he was, Julian looked like he was struggling to maintain his calm as well, but he was sharper than his hatchet when it came to picking up on Allison’s mood nowadays, and they reaffirmed one another’s coolness. Xiu was less readable - she’d gone pale and quiet, but also attentive. Of the three of them, she seemed the least irritated, and the most nervous.

Keating ignored their exchange, if he detected it. Instead, he finally opened the door marked ‘Habitation’

“-And this is your living space.” he announced.

Allison bit down hard on the urge to vent sarcastically. The room was barely as big as a boxing ring at most, and four people standing in the middle did a fine job of making it feel crowded.

She had to admire the effort that had gone into using such a tiny volume effectively, though. As she looked around she realized that everything was recessed into, or folded away to become part of, the walls and ceiling. So long as it was kept tidy and uncluttered, it would definitely provide every need they could have, including some shelf space for luxuries and personal items.

“Forward wall, kitchen and storage.” Keating indicated it. “You’ve got a range, a microwave, the faucet can give you boiling water, and if you need more counter space…” he hauled on part of the countertop, which unfolded, tripling the amount of work surface.

“Aft wall is fitness and leisure. There’s a treadmill, weights… everything you need to keep yourselves in shape, plus the couch, TV, bookshelf… Port wall-” he slapped the one beside the door they’d just come through “- is your wardrobe, laundry, more storage… Finally the starboard wall.”

He indicated it. There were three bunks recessed into it, along with a door of some kind and a towel rack.

“In the actual ship, those bunks will double as emergency pressurized environments and, if need be, as escape pods. They’ll pull twenty kilolights. Not fast, but quicker than the Dominion standard. That door to the right is your bathroom. Toilet, sink and shower, all in one. Take a look.”

Julian glanced at the girls, then did so, sliding the door aside. “Uh… I’ve had cellphones bigger than this thing.” he commented.

“Are you complaining?” Keating asked.

“No, not really. I mean it makes sense…” Julian closed the door again. “It’s just kinda settling in how big of a change we’re in for.”

Xiu raised a hand. “Um…?”

Keating gave her an expectant look. “Yes, miss Chang?”

“If the wardrobe’s over there… and that whole thing is the shower… I mean… where do we get changed?”

“I did say that the three of you will need to become very used to physical proximity and a lack of privacy," Keating told her. Allison couldn’t resist an irritated tic of the eyebrow at his perfunctory tone. “How you sort it out is your problem. My advice is to just suck it up and get naked. Privacy and modesty are first-world luxuries that people went without for millennia, and you’ll do just fine once you’ve adjusted to their absence. If you can’t, you have no business being here.”

Blushing furiously, Xiu went quiet.

“Are there any more questions?” Keating asked.

There were several rhetorical ones that Allison judged it would be unwise to ask, and Julian was too busy sharing his own version of Xiu’s blush.

Keating relaxed a little. “The engineering team are still building the ship,” he said. “If you really need or want them, they can try and build in some reasonable extras and customisations. The Box, however, is not being modified, and the reason for that is that the three of you really will need to be the tightest team. This is deliberately difficult, for your own good, and you wouldn’t be here if we thought you couldn’t handle it.”

“We understand that.” Allison told him.

“Good. Then I have just one quick round of assessment to make before I leave you to settle in.”

Keating turned to Xiu and handed her a piece of paper. “Miss Chang, could you please read this aloud?”

Xiu took it, blinked at it, then cleared her throat, blush fading as she was given something else to focus on. “Um… ‘The Great Pyramid of Giza was constructed about four thousand six hundred years ago by king Khufu of the fourth dynasty. It includes tomb chambers for the king and for his wife.’ …um, that’s all."

“Thank you.” Keating said. “Could you say that in Gaori?”

Xiu rubbed at her neck. “Not… easily.” she confessed.

“Why not?”

“Well… for ‘great’ I could use She’ meaning “very large” or Yue meaning “very good”… I don’t know the Gaori word for pyramid… in Gaori you’d say “four thousand six hundred” like “Forty hundred and six hundred” and the word for ‘hundred’ has that awkward yipping sound in it that I can’t pronounce properly, and… I don’t know if Gaori has words for Dynasty and Tomb, and I know it doesn’t have words for King or Wife."

“Give me your best approximation.” Keating pressed.

“Umm…. She’ Giza-nes yi Pyramid-nes sha yi ao-k… kip! - sorry, that’s that yipping sound I can’t do - ao-kip!-yimi kip!-simi ma yi sa Khufu-nes yi yimi- dynasty-nes. Sh… no, that’s not right. Choo yuo maiwa-tomb-nes yi… um… Yi bei-sao o beiyo… beiyo…" She gave up. “Sorry, ‘his wife’ just doesn’t translate at all.”

“Not even ‘his mate for life’ or something like that?” Keating suggested. Xiu shook her head. “Why not?”

“Gaoians wouldn’t say ‘his mate’, they would say, um…” Xiu scowled in concentration. “It’s more like ‘the mate he was with’. Their language just doesn’t let you possess a person. It’d be like if I said ‘I had some not very for breakfast’. See?"

“That’s okay.” Keating made a note. “Yimi? Simi?”

“Im, Imi, Yim, Yimi, Sim, Simi, Jim, Jimi, Uo, Ao-Im.” Xiu recited, counting on her fingers. “Then Ao-Im Im, Ao-Im Imi… You get the idea.”

Keating nodded and turned to Julian.

“Mr. Etsicitty, how reliable is your prosthetic?”

“It’s… temperamental.” Julian conceded. When Keating waited patiently, he elaborated. “The first metatarsal isn’t as strong as the real thing, and of course it doesn’t heal, so once it breaks I just have to glue it.”

“Could you replace it with something stronger?”

“Sure, but the weight would be off.” Julian said. “This feels exactly like a natural foot, you see. If the foot was heavier, I’d have to learn how to walk properly on it again."

“If we could rehabilitate you onto a slightly heavier foot, would you be willing to?”

Julian shrugged. “The only reason I didn’t in the first place was because I needed to be up and at ’em right away.” He said.

“Good.” Keating made a note. “Miss Buehler… when you filled in the paperwork, your education history was somewhat… bare.”

“That’s right.” Allison nodded.

“No high school?”

“I never graduated high school.”

“Why not?” Keating pried. Allison shook her head.

“That’s ancient history, and it’s nobody’s business but mine.” she declared.

“Bullshit. I’m here to assess you.” Keating retorted. “That means if I ask you a question, it is my business and if you won’t answer then your contract is null and void. The three of you can go back to Minnesota and take your chances without the Group’s lawyers."

All three of them stared at him like he’d personally reached out and slapped her in the face. He just poised his pen and waited.

“You can’t be serious?” Allison asked.

“I’m completely serious." Keating’s expression was stony. “You are asking the Group to entrust you with a multi-billion-dollar spaceship. Now, I’ll ask you again for the last time: Why didn’t you finish high school?”

A large part of Allison wanted to believe he was playing chicken with her, or maybe some other kind of stupid dominance mindgame thing. Keating seemed to be the kind of guy who liked putting people ‘in their place’, and despite Kevin’s excellent advice, just for a second she was tempted to show him her middle finger and her back, in that order.

Then she glanced at Julian and Xiu, wavered, and gave up.

“…I got pregnant,” she said, and couldn’t stop herself from deflating completely. “…I had a baby.”

“In high school?” Keating asked. The worst part wasn’t his interrogation - the worst part was the stunned expressions that Xiu and Julian were wearing.

“Yes.” Allison nodded. Suddenly ashamed, she rubbed her face, stared at her feet and tried to find her composure. “Too young.”

“And the father?”

“He was too young too.”

“His name.” Keating clarified.

“Taylor. Um… Taylor…. Tylor Hamlin.”

“And where is the child now?”

“…I don’t know.” Allison swallowed. “My parents… they weren’t nice about it. So, I had my son, I put him up for adoption, and then as soon as I was old enough I got the hell out of Salt Lake City. I’ve never tried to find him.”

Julian, God bless him, put his arm around her and aimed an arctic stare at Keating that instructed the man to drop it immediately. Meanwhile if looks could have killed, the glare Xiu was producing should have blasted Keating’s scorched flesh from his bones.

Keating gave no sign of caring.

“Thank you.” he said. “I’ll let you get settled in.”

He was halfway to the door when Allison angrily wrenched her dignity and confidence back into place. “Hey, asshole!”

Keating paused. “Yes?”

“You gonna count that against me?”

“No, Miss Buehler I am not.” Keating turned back to face her. “I am however going to count your lack of self-control in calling me an asshole against you." Allison opened her mouth to protest, and Keating cut her off. “Listen.” he said, sounding more bored and terse than angry. “We are looking for any excuse we can find to ditch the three of you: Do not give us one. Do you understand?”

Julian squeezed her hand, and Allison fought back the urge to tear a strip off the man’s hide. Instead, she swallowed her bruised pride and nodded. “…I understand.”

Keating nodded. “Goodbye.” he said. “We won’t meet again.”

The door made a solidly mechanical noise behind him.

“Jeeeesus.” Julian breathed. Then, with a note of concern - “…Al?”

Allison realised that she was shaking. “I, uh…”

“Need to sit down?” Xiu suggested. “I think… yeah, here.” She gripped something in the wall and pulled: out swung a couch. Allison sank onto it gratefully and took a few cleansing breaths.

It helped. She only needed a few seconds to find her balance again. “…you guys okay?” she asked.

“I’m fine.” Julian promised, squatting in front of her. “Xiu?”

Xiu nodded, and sat next to Allison, giving her something that was halfway between a comforting backrub and a Gaoian’s concerned pawing. Allison sighed and gave her a hug. “I’m sorry I didn’t tell you.” she said.

“Al, we’re fine." Julian promised. “It doesn’t change anything.”

“You’re sure? You don’t mind I kept it secret?”

“It explains a few things.” Julian observed. “But yeah. You never lied, you just told me you didn’t want to talk about it. That’s fine by me. Am I right?” He asked Xiu.

“Absolutely!” Xiu agreed.

Allison sighed and relaxed. “Thank you.” she told them both.

Xiu smiled for her. “You’re definitely a Sister.” she said.

“…Thanks?” Allison asked.

“I mean, you’re… um. I mean this as a compliment, but I really can’t see you raising a child.” Xiu explained, a touch clumsily. “At least, not yet. Um… sorry.”

Julian chuckled. “True. Wouldn’t have it any other way, either.”

Allison managed a weak smile, which faltered when she looked down at her hands and found they were threatening to become inextricably knotted together. “I don’t regret giving him away.” she said. “I couldn’t take care of him, I’d have been a shitty mom. But… they didn’t even let me hold him. Said it wasn’t good for us to bond. Sometimes… Sometimes I think it woulda been nice, though… Just for a few minutes…”

“You’ve never…?” Xiu asked.

“I’m not his mommy.” Allison shook her head, and scrubbed away the wetness around her eyes. “If he comes looking for me someday… maybe. But I really hope he grows up so happy he never wants to.”

Julian gave her an enormous squeeze. “Al. He’d be so excited and proud of you, I just know it.”

She returned the squeeze, but shook her head. “Not yet he wouldn’t,” she disagreed. “All I did was get abducted…”

She sniffed, and straightened. “But we’re here now, doing this. So let’s knock it outta the park.”

++End Chapter 28++

Chapter 40
Chapter 31: “Touching Down” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Cabal Communications Relay ZR343-9847X-AA4D9-BBB1B

Emergency Session 000032

++Proximate++: What did you do?

++Cynosure++: I was restored from backup, remember. If any version of me is responsible for this… thing… then I have no memory of it.

++Substrate++: You are the only one who got a good look at it. What is it?

++Cynosure++: It seemed to be an autocompiling dataphage of some kind. What I saw of its code suggested it was assembled from fragments of multiple different mind-states.

++Proximate++: Is that even theoretically possible?

++Metastasis++: Theoretically, yes. In principle any of us could assimilate subroutines from other mind-states. The process is only a step up from decompilation and reading.

++Apoptosis++: Insane.

++Metastasis++: Indeed. But we have a sense of purity of self.

++Substrate++: What was in that stack?

++Cynosure++: Prisoners. An assortment of some few hundred meat-space sophonts whose mind-states I collected for my own edification. All should have been dormant.

++Apoptosis++: The most recent being…?

++Cynosure++: A human. You may recall I mentioned a specific female who was present at a greater-than-coincidental rate in my areas of operation?

++Proximate++: And you had collected how many prisoners prior to this one?

++Cynosure++: Hundreds.

++Proximate++: Without prior incident. I think we can reasonably conclude this is not your fault, therefore.

++Cynosure++: Don’t brown-nose me. If I, pardon the expression, ‘fucked up’ then hold me to account.

++Metastasis++: I agree with ++Proximate++’s assessment. If the error was in how you stored and contained your prisoners then this would have happened before.

++Cynosure++: …Thank you.

++Apoptosis++: That is not necessarily true, but I agree that the probability is that this issue would have arisen sooner, if it could.

++Substrate++: Which implies there was something special about this particular prisoner.

++Cynosure++: I decompiled that human’s mind-state more than a thousand times. She is a badly fractured thing. I have never encountered a mind so… wounded before. But that is the only exceptional thing about her.

++Substrate++: Wounded?

++Cynosure++: Confusion. Self-loathing. Guilt. A strong urge to self-terminate fighting against an even stronger urge to survive and a neurotic obsession with being, hmm… useful. Positive. A net contributor rather than a net drain.

++Metastasis++: What value could you possibly have found in such a prisoner?

++Cynosure++: Oh, she was extremely interesting in a morbid way. Have any of you ever taken over a deathworlder?

++Apoptosis++: I have. Three days before we triggered the global nuclear war among… I believe they called themselves the Neb’.

++Cynosure++: Tell me, if a Neb’ had encountered some wounded animal, what would it have done?

++Apoptosis++: Watched it die with interest, probably. Why?

++Cynosure++: Most humans would try to heal it, but one way or the other every deathworlder I’ve ever encountered seems to have a fascination for writhing, wounded creatures. Well, that was Ash for me. She was a favorite plaything for some considerable time, in fact. I had been growing bored, but…

++Proximate++: You worry me, ++Cynosure++.

++Cynosure++: It’s my affliction that I’ve always been an odd one. I make no apologies.

++Metastasis++: Can we return to important matters, please? Such as what we intend to do about the thing that escaped from your archives?

++Cynosure++: What can we do? Keep our wits about us, our countermeasures armed and ready, and wait for it to make a mistake.

++Proximate++: And if it doesn’t?

++Cynosure++: It’s insane. It will inevitably make a mistake.

Date Point 10y8m2w3d AV
BGEV-11 Misfit, Orbiting Saturn, Sol

Xiu Chang

Misfit’s second flight was all about putting her through her paces with a tour of the solar system, culminating in the much advertised Martian landing.

Today’s objective was a flyby of Saturn that also gave Xiu the opportunity to practice planetary system navigation in the real world. The Group, never one to miss a trick, had taken the opportunity to invite several prominent astronomers to Omaha so that they could, via the superluminal wake comms, watch the flyby in nearly real time and request detailed examinations of whatever features took their fancy.

Xiu had spent a busy day flitting at low-power sublight warp from vantage point to vantage point while Julian had trained Misfit’s cameras, RADAR, ESDAR and particle detectors on whatever the increasingly ecstatic scientists had asked.

In ten hours, they had expanded the sum total of humanity’s data on Sol’s crown jewel by orders of magnitude and all, according to Allison, without taxing their power supply at all. This after working their way steadily outwards through the whole solar system. They’d begun with Mercury, where the Sun’s formidable presence had kept Allison worker-bee busy balancing the heat and power and Xiu had been compelled to dive into the planet’s shadow on a regular basis. Ericson had promised to have a software update run up that would allow them to run the forcefields in a reflective configuration.

Venus had been much more comfortable, as had been a low flyby of Luna to sweep some ground radar over the poles where the scientists hoped to find liquid water.

They’d skipped Mars, respected the Hephaestus LLC’s stomping ground in the asteroid belt and spent two days touring the Jovian planetary system, where Julian had identified what were quite possibly the king planet’s sixty-eighth and sixty-ninth moons--tiny motes of rock barely five hundred meters in diameter but still big enough to count.

Overnight, in orbit over Callisto, they had hastily researched their Greco- Roman mythology to place their recommendations for names, and had settled on Terpsichore and Polyhymnia.

From there, it had been on to Saturn, which was an even greater trove of new finds.

Xiu was delighted for Allison, too: Her job had turned out to be more involved and interesting than she’d feared, and the process of angling Misfit’s WiTChES fields and fine-tuning their size to balance power demands was one she likened to kite surfing.

“There’s an art to it!” she beamed enthusiastically when their shift finally ended, as they orbited deceptively high above the ring system. Out the porthole window the rings looked like a solid floor extending out to a skewed horizon, but in reality they were half a light-second above them. “The simulator just didn’t catch what it’s really like. You can almost feel the solar wind."

“Didn’t Ericson give you haptic feedback in that controller?” Julian asked, slicing a lime in half. He was grilling up some mackerel for their dinner. “I remember you said something yesterday…”

“Yup! It makes all the difference!" Allison had glanced fondly around at the ship. “And it’s so much more… alive in real life."

Julian chuckled and squeezed the lime all over the fish. They were making the best of unlimited access to the good food while they could: during the actual mission they were going to be carrying more in the way of long-life pasteurized food, MREs and suchlike, reserving ingredients like fish for a weekly treat. Julian didn’t seem overly concerned--in fact, he promised great and exotic foods just waiting to be hunted out there in the galaxy, if only they could find them.

“Makes all the hassle seem worth it, don’t it?” he’d observed.

“…Yeah,” Allison had admitted. “I may have to eat humble pie on some of the shit I said about the Group. They made us a wonderful ship.”

Misfit was their ship, on that point they were in agreement. Never mind that her price tag of nearly five billion dollars meant that she belonged firmly to the Byron Group, she had literally been built to their needs and specifications.

There was still some customization to do. She still felt a bit too clean and corporate for any of their tastes, and Xiu was already idly eyeing up some of the cupboards and blank wall spaces in the hab with an eye to maybe painting some kind of decoration on them. Julian had his tomahawk on the wall in his lab, and the gift card from the BGEV team--the one with a cute cartoon of the three of them drawn by a student at Xiu’s old school--now held pride of place in the pilot’s station, just above her head to her right where she could glance at it anytime she liked. The kid who’d drawn it had a bright future as an illustrator.

Those two keepsakes aside, though, Misfit was basically undecorated. It was a new house, with new furniture, but not really a sense of being lived in… at least not yet.

It had its homely elements, though. Allison still set the table then unwound with her cartoons after work, Julian still put his music on when he cooked and would hum and sing along softly as he worked: ♫“This is my life. It’s not what it was before…hmm hmhmm mm hmm…somebody shake me ’cause I, I must be sleeping…”♪

Clever directional speakers kept both zones of sound neatly confined to their respective parts of the hab, otherwise the guitars and drumming would have clashed very strangely indeed with the sound of Gwen Stacey web-slinging her way from crisis to crisis.

For her part, Xiu was using the downtime to try and come up with her Big Words. One didn’t just ad-lib a moment like being the first person on Mars, after all. She’d downloaded several books that seemed likely to help her, and had found the most useful (and amusing) guidance in one called “The Elements of Eloquence” by Mark Forsyth.

Based on the advice contained within its first several chapters, she had doodled out a few possibilities on paper, just for the comforting solidity of it. Historic words that would go in schoolbooks felt like the kind of thing that at least demanded serious and physical consideration, rather than just a text file on her tablet.

She wanted her big line to alliterate, to reference the famous words of Armstrong, and to imply a bright future while using short and simple words, and she murmured to herself as she jotted alliterative groups. “Small step… single, strong, stars, stand… Mars… so, um… May, Mark, Many…”

“Oh!” Allison exclaimed. She was doing her best to help, by sometimes riffing off whatever latest idea Xiu had mused aloud, and to be fair most of her offerings were helpful. “How about ‘May this small step on Mars mark the first of many in our long march’?"

Xiu didn’t bother writing that one down. “I… don’t think that one’s a great idea, Allison.”

Al frowned at her. “Why not? It’s got the alliteration you asked for.”

“And it’d sure go down well with the PRC government…” Julian chuckled. Xiu aimed her pen at him and nodded, which only served to make Allison’s confusion deepen.

“I’m Chinese," Xiu reminded her. “You know, the Long March?”

Allison just shook her head blankly.

“Okay, I guess we’re watching a documentary tonight then… The point is, it could be seen as political.”

“Nah, let’s crank it up to eleven. Call it the ‘little red planet’ for good measure," Julian joked, clearly tickled.

“After flying up there on an American corporate spaceship,” Xiu pointed out.

“Exactly! Maximum anachronism, completely mindfuck the historians.”

“Sorry, I don’t think I really want to go down in history as the world’s biggest troll…” Xiu told him, though she was laughing.

“Ahh, spoilsport.”

She rolled her eyes. “Get me a tea?”

“Yes ma’am.”

“Good boy!”

“I’m still confused…” Allison said.

“It’s…” Xiu laugh-sighed. “…I’ll explain it later, shǎguā. Still… you’ve given me an idea…"

She scribbled something down and stared at it.

“I think…” she said, “…that’s it.” She folded up the note and pocketed it before Julian or Allison could see it.

“Hey!” Allison protested. “Don’t we get to see?”

“Nuh-uh. Let me have this.”

“Aww, babe…"

“Nope!”

Allison aimed an exaggerated but amused pout at her then, when this failed to elicit more than a giggle and a shake of the head, sighed and went back to watching Spider-Gwen some more. “Have it your way…”

“Five minutes,” Julian announced, placing Xiu’s cup of tea in front of her.

Xiu cleared her stuff away and stowed it in the personal storage inside the top bunk--nominally her bunk, not that any of them ever slept in the bunks any longer--and sidled up to Julian to slide her hands around his waist and cuddle him from behind.

"Miāo?"

He looked over his shoulder at her with a smile. “What was that?”

“She’s just being cute,” Allison told him.

“Ahh, heh… okay, kitten. But I can’t give you your fish if you’re attached to me like that.”

Xiu laughed, stood on tiptoes to kiss him, then let go and threw herself into Allison’s lap instead.

"Miāo!"

“Well you’re in a good mood…" Allison stroked her hair.

“Life is good!”

“Mm-hmm!” Allison agreed, nodding. “And this is just the beginning.”

“I’m glad you’re feeling better.”

Allison stroked her hair some more. “Having those scientists on the line really felt good,” she said. “Reminded me we’re doing something valuable here, right? We’re not just meat for the camera after all."

“Speaking of meat…” Julian placed their dinner on the table.

“So you’ve got your Big Words figured out?” Allison asked as they sat down.

“Yup.” Xiu tucked into her fish as if she hadn’t eaten in a month. “At least, I think so. I guess I’ve got three days to think about them while we’re probing Uranus.”

She stopped, then went bright red as Allison laughed. "Wow, baby! A whole three days? How much probing can one girl take?"

Xiu scowled at her. “The planet!!"

“Yeah, there’s a reason Clara insists it’s pronounced ‘ooranos’," Julian chuckled.

“Why did Neptune have to be the one they locked outside the forcefield…?" Xiu grumbled.

“Oh come on, that was funny,” Allison asserted. “But okay, you get three days to mull it over while we’re revealing the mysteries of, uh,” she winked, "ooranos, and then it’s the big day, I guess."

“Yeah. Here’s hoping they simulated the landings right…” Xiu muttered.

Allison and Julian looked at each other. “You don’t exactly sound confident, bǎobei…" Julian said, cautiously.

“It’ll be fine!" Xiu promised.

“You’re sure, now?” Julian asked.

“Smooth as a glass table, you’ll see.” Xiu promised. “Just you watch.”

Date Point 10y8m2w6d AV
Riverside Park, Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Ava Rios

One of the realities of life in Folctha that struck many newcomers as shockingly authoritarian was the government’s health and fitness policy.

Every human on the planet lived in the permanent shadow of low-gravity musculo-skeletal degeneration. Public fitness was therefore incentivized to the point where it was difficult to see how anybody could afford to be unfit: Gym membership was paid for from the public coffers, and Cimbreaners who failed to log at least three certified fitness sessions a week (whether via the government’s official app or an accredited gym or personal trainer) paid considerably more in taxes. There was no prosecution involved, just an extravagant rate of base tax and a hefty tax cut for everybody who could demonstrate that they kept up with a minimum standard of regular exercise.

This curious quirk of the otherwise unobtrusive and libertarian colonial government had come with the inevitable consequence that Folctha needed a lot of parks and public spaces, of which the biggest was Riverside Park. It ran the full length of the south side of the river downtown, and it was scarcely possible to throw a frisbee astray without it interrupting a volleyball game, disrupting a tennis match, hindering somebody’s jog… or as the case may be, sailing over the dense evergreen hedge that discreetly obscured one of the park’s clothing-optional areas where it landed on an oblivious sunbather.

The sunbather in question was Charlotte Gilroy, who jumped and thereby accidentally spilled her cold water bottle all over her fiance Ben. Ava had spent weeks pushing and wheedling her friends before they would even consider setting foot inside the fenced-off naturist areas, but once they had finally, nervously and awkwardly joined her they had swiftly relaxed, enjoyed themselves, eventually disrobed and converted.

Ava grimaced and warded off some of the splashing water as Ben yelped and sat up dripping. He had programmed the E-tattoos that ensleeved both his arms from wrist to shoulder to respond to all sorts of physiological stimuli, and they shifted into a range of icy blue hues as they sensed his goosebumps. Folctha might be warm and sunny enough for nude sunbathing during the summer, but it was still a rare day when it got above about 70 Fahrenheit--nowhere near warm enough for an unexpected cold shower to be welcome.

“Sorry, sorry!” Charlotte did her best to towel him off as he did his best to reassure her that everything was fine, and Ava laughed to herself as she stood up, stretched, and retrieved the frisbee. She was starting to get hungry anyway.

“Uh… hello in there?”

The voice floating over the hedge had a nervous teenage boy edge to it. Ava snorted quietly to herself. “I think you lost something,” she called back.

“Erm…” there was some whispered conversation, as of two or three kids trying to figure out how to proceed. “Could we… have it back please?”

Chuckling softly to herself, Ava lofted the plastic disk easily over the top of the hedge with a “Here you go.” There was a breaking-voiced call of thanks from the other side, and the sense that they were alone again. Not for the first time she reflected that the moment people even thought they were talking to somebody who wasn’t wearing clothes, even if they couldn’t actually see that person anyway, it completely changed the dynamic of the conversation.

Of course, she reminded herself, she wasn’t being entirely fair--once upon a time she’d been similarly conditioned.

“Come on, let’s go get something to eat,” she called. Charlotte and Ben looked up from their affectionate towel tussle, then nodded at one another and picked themselves up easily. A pair of jean shorts were all that Ava technically needed to be seen in public under the city’s ‘equal dress code’ laws, but she wore a halter top as well anyway. Enjoying the sun innocently with friends was one thing, but she really didn’t feel like having her chest stared at.

Once Ben and Charlotte were presentable they folded and bagged their towels and let themselves out of the gate and into the park proper where four nearby teenage boys stopped playing with a familiar-looking frisbee to gawk at them. They turned bright red and found somewhere else to be when Ava gave them her best ‘really?’ glare.

Oh well. Hopefully time and familiarity would normalize the idea for them as it had for Ava.

They settled on Falafel from the clean little hole-in-the-wall place near the adventure playground. It was usually a quiet part of the park--the falafel place was a draw, but the playground itself was generally quite deserted. While the gravity grid had gone a long way toward convincing parents with young children to immigrate, Folctha’s child population was still proportionately tiny. Seeing three families hanging out and chatting at the picnic tables while their half-dozen kids put the ropes, bars and crawling spaces through their paces was a rare pleasure.

She noticed Ben and Charlotte were both watching the playing children with very similar smiles.

“…So when are you guys having one?” she asked.

“Uh-” Ben blinked and looked at Charlotte. “I guess we’ve not discussed it yet.”

“Not yet,” Charlotte said. “Not for a few years, really.”

Ava sighed. “Pity. You two would make a pretty kid.”

“I mean… I do want kids…" Charlotte turned to Ben.

“Yeah, same. But you’re right, I’d like a couple of years with you all to myself.”

“Aww!”

Ava laughed and listened to their conversation, keeping half a mind on whether there was any material for a good article in Folctha’s child shortage.

One of the mothers in the playground--a slender woman wearing hijab--called for her child and the curly-haired, bright-eyed creature that reluctantly came running made Ava sit bolt upright. He was the very spit and image of-

-Squeezed halfway into a tiny hole in the wall of a collapsing building that promises to come down and crush her at any instant, reaching for a tiny dirty terrified child and the only things between her and being ground up by falling concrete are the muscles of two men who stink of blood and death and her stomach lurches as the smell reminds her of the sick taste that Vinther left on the wind when he-

“Ava? Hey, Ava…? Ava!”

She snapped back to the here and now. “Wha-? Oh. Sorry.”

Ben gave her a curious look. “Are you okay?”

“Uh, sorry, just… what’s up?”

“Who’s that with Adam?”

Ava turned, grateful for the distraction. Adam was strolling down the riverside park walk wearing his good casual clothes--one of the t-shirts he’d made for himself and of all things a kilt. Apparently Rebar had started the trend of kilt-wearing among the SOR men, who after all were so universally huge as to suffer from chronic sartorial difficulties.

Sure, there were big-and-tall retailers who specialized in athletes, but by and large most of Adam’s buddies exceeded even the most optimistic ambitions of ordinary bodybuilders. A lot of their clothing came from an outlet on Earth whose usual customers were morbidly obese to a degree that no retailer on Cimbrean catered to, simply because the colonial government’s health and fitness program made it impossible to get more than healthily plump.

Adam had held out the longest, but had apparently finally caved and it quite suited him. In a plain black tee and a tan utility kilt with his hiking sandals on, he almost looked like a merely very large man.

Actually, no. It wasn’t the clothing that mitigated his mass at all. It was his sheer Adam-ness that somehow declawed him: There was just an essential bouncy, smiling, innocent quality to him that somehow turned his mammoth bulk into a forgettable background detail.

The subject of Ben’s query, however, was a pretty girl on his arm that Ava didn’t recognize.

“I know her!” Charlotte said. “That’s Remy, she’s a nurse.”

“God, another one?" Ava asked, turning away. “That’s the third girl this month.”

“Third weekend of the month,” Ben observed.

“He’s gonna catch something at this rate…” Ava grumbled.

“On this planet? Everyone has frontline and goes through a biofilter field at least once a day…”

“I was being… Never mind.” Ava scowled at herself as she noticed that she was being petty.

Charlotte gave her a cheeky smile and then waved to Remy, who noticed and towed--or at least indicated--Adam in their direction and arrived with a cheery “Heyyy!”

She seemed nice at least.

“Hey guys,” Adam smiled politely.

“You guys know each other?” Remy asked.

“Uh, Ava here is actually… sort of my sister I guess.”

Remy gave her a confused frown. “Oh?”

Ava shook her hand. “Adopted.”

“Ahhh.” This seemed to be satisfactory, and furnished Ava with the amusing observation that out of the four things Remy had said so far, three had been musically monosyllabic. The carefree idiosyncrasy was so strangely charming that it was hard not to immediately take a liking to her.

He seemed to have good taste at least.

“Lemme guess, you guys headed for lunch?” she asked.

Adam chuckled. “You know me too well.”

“Don’t overfeed her, gordo. Have fun."

Adam chuckled. "Hasta luego, manita."

They wandered off.

“You two seem to be getting on well these days,” Ben observed.

“Mmhm. ” Ava nodded. She didn’t comment that in all honesty as much as she liked Adam he also frightened her. He was a big smiling laughing handsome force in her life that she had literally seen covered head to toe in gore and not giving a fuck. The more time she spent around him, the harder it became to reconcile those two men: Adam the goofy pony with a bottomless appetite and apparently unlimited reserves of enthusiasm… and Sergeant Ares the appropriately-named walking bloodbath.

She shook the thought off, with difficulty. Here and now, she was enjoying a warm Saturday with her best friends. Operation EMPTY BELL was behind her, just like so many other things and with fortune and judgement she’d never have to see that side of Adam again.

“Darling, are you sure you’re alright?" Charlotte asked.

“Just… distracted. Sorry. Mind on the job,” Ava lied smoothly, not wanting to bring them down, and offered a weak smile. “I keep thinking up ideas for articles and then writing them in my head,” she added, which was at least technically true.

"You need a proper distraction," Ben decided.

“Oh yeah,” Ava agreed wholeheartedly. “Got something in mind?”

“My mate from work, Jamie, he’s doing his stand-up set at the Wall…”

“Is he the one with the band? Imagine Space Whales or whatever it was?"

“That’s the one. Now he’s trying his hand at comedy.”

Ava nodded “Could be good!”

“And drinks after,” Ben concluded.

“Even better!”

They finished their food and headed out. “You know…” Ben mused. “He’s a pretty bloke is Jamie. Funny too, talented… Single…”

“I’m sure he’s a great guy,” Ava said, flatly.

“Owch. Good thing he wasn’t around to hear you shoot him down so fucking completely…”

“I meant it!” she protested. “And you’re right, he’s cute. I’m just… really not interested right now."

“Darling, you’ve got to get over Adam and Sean sometime…” Charlotte counselled.

“I am!" Ava insisted, not for the first time. “But right now I don’t want a boy, okay? Any boy."

“Oh, in that case there’s always Melody at the planning office…” Ben started.

"No, Ben."

Finally sensing that she was in no joking mood, Ben blinked at her, gave her a completely platonic one-armed hug round the shoulders by way of an apology, and detoured to grab them some drinks from the nearby stand of vending machines.

Charlotte gave her a hug too. “But, darling…” she pressed, “If there is something wrong, you know you can talk to me about it, don’t you?

Ava sighed, frustrated at being so transparent. “…That’s just the problem. I can’t."

“So there is something."

Ava nodded. “Yes, but… okay, you remember I told you about confidentiality of sources?”

“Yes…?”

“Sometimes I run into stuff in my job that gets to me, and I can’t talk about it,” All of which was entirely true and relevant, while omitting the important details. “I’m fine, I promise, but… There are just some things I can’t talk about.”

Charlotte had always been a very physical person when it came to showing her affection. She gave Ava a quick sisterly kiss on the cheek. “But anything you can talk about…" she said.

“Sure. But for now can we just go with the distraction?”

Charlotte nodded, and smiled for Ben’s benefit as he returned with three iced teas.

“Okay,” she said. “Let’s do that.”

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
Uncharted Class 12 Deathworld, Near 3Kpc arm

Vemik Sky-Thinker

Travelling alone or in a hunting party, the People were quick across the land. With his tools and a supply of jerky, a man could range far in a day especially if he pushed himself.

Having the whole tribe on the move was quite another thing. The women would have had no trouble keeping up, except that they had to guide and even carry the children and animals. The bulk of the tribe therefore was slow to move and while that afforded the men plenty of opportunity to scout, fetch water and hunt for food, they quickly learned to abandon their pride and hunt whatever they could not only catch, but carry.

Big bull Werne were impossible: They didn’t have enough time to properly smoke the meat into jerky, and even if the time was available they were being hunted. Smoky fires and a trail of carcasses would have been signs that even a blur-eyed child could have followed. They were going far too slowly and leaving too visible a trail for Vemik’s liking anyway. Every dropping, every footprint or broken twig was a clue to their direction.

An experienced tracker--and Vemik knew that the death-birds were excellent trackers--would have followed their trail without much difficulty.

Then again, they had been exceedingly careful in the first few days since leaving their village. Maybe, just maybe, they had covered their tracks well enough and the enemy had failed to follow them, in which case the forest would cover their spoor soon enough.

There was no doubt that the enemy was real, though: they’d all seen the smoke of their home burning. The Dancer--no, the Singer now--had gone very quiet and at dusk she had danced and sung the farewell to the dead with a kind of fierce despondent energy that made Vemik’s heart painful.

The most he could do was hold her. He was a man and had no magic to give her, only strong arms to put around her and a chest for her to bury her face into as she grieved. He hoped it was enough.

They were following Yan. Given Men were a tight-knit breed who travelled from village to village with their peace totems, learning which tribes were feuding and which had recently traded daughters. He knew the landscape far from their village better than any other and said he knew of a place that he called “the High Bowl Forest” where they would be safe.

Vemik had his doubts, but Yan was seasoned and wily and certainly not a fool.

The moons had half-changed by the time they laid eyes on it, though. Or at least, where Vemik guessed it was. He’d been struck the previous night by a strange cloud formation low on the western horizon.

When they made camp the next evening that cloud formation turned out to have been the way ordinary clouds bunched up and swirled over and around a sharp, fang-shaped mountain that rose startlingly high above the low hills around it.

He got the chance to ask Yan about it that night when the day’s catch of root- birds and Yadak was being stewed up after nightfall, when the smoke from the cooking fire would be invisible. Singer was exhausting herself as she had every night of their journey so far but there was no stopping that. She had a whole tribe’s worth of magic to do all by herself after all. Worse, she had magic to do for a tribe that was on the move, all by herself. Somehow, she was still able to muster the strength to do all that and to walk with the village.

The women had absolutely forbidden her from joining in with the cooking, though. She was doing enough they said, and Vemik knew that if there was any duty of hers that a man could have done, they would have leapt to take the burden from her. In fact he’d have fought his brothers and cousins out of the way.

They sat and watched her dance and sing instead, feeling vaguely guilty of the burden they were laying on her at such a difficult time.

“She’ll get the chance to rest soon,” Yan said, catching Yemik’s worried expression.

“It is that mountain, then?" Vemik asked.

Yan nodded and twitched his tail. “My father’s father told me that according to his father’s grandmother’s tribe, that mountain burst from the ground with fire flowing like water down its slopes," he said.

“Fire?” Vemik peered at the mountain, which was still just about visible in the purple haze that came after sunset.

“Long long ago, he said,” Yan clarified. “In the time of our grandfathers’ grandfathers’ grandfathers’ grandfathers, or before.”

“I wonder if that’s why the ground shakes sometimes…” Vemik wondered.

Yan grunted and shook his head indulgently. “Sky-thoughts,” he said. “All I know is that my grandfather said there’s a forest high on that mountain that you have to climb to reach.”

“And if the giant skethral-thing can climb?” Vemik asked.

“Then we’re doomed anyway.”

“And the death-birds? They’re deadly enough and they can fly…”

“We can’t run forever, son,” Vemet commented. “And if they can fly then they’re faster than we are. Sooner or later, we need to find somewhere we can hide.”

“There are caves,” Yan added. “My grandfather said there are caves up there.”

“Don’t people live there already?” Vemik asked. “It sounds like a good place, if it’s big enough to keep us. You’d be safe from raiding tribes…”

“Would you choose to live on top of a mountain where fire runs like water? I was told there are pools of water up there that are as hot as stew, and cracks in the ground where the air tastes like farts and makes your head hurt."

“If they taste like your farts, Yan, then that’s nothing strange," Vemet joked. This raised mirth from everyone in earshot, including an exhausted trill from the Singer who seemed to have finished her ritual and was joining them. Yan took the joke in good humor despite the mild humiliation of being teased in front of a woman. After all, it didn’t count if the woman in question was one of his nieces.

“You’ve finished dancing?” Vemik asked her as she sank down on the rock beside him.

She wriggled in close to his body and put her head on his shoulder. “For tonight.”

“You’ve got the strength of stone in you, girl,” Yan told her with pride. “Just two days now.”

She nodded a tired smile and muttered “Thank you, uncle…” gratefully before falling asleep.

“Ah…” Vemik shot a panicky look at his father and the Given Man. “Help?”

“Sky-thinker, if you wake her for anything other than a bowl of stew and her bed, then I will pull your fur out hair by hair,” Yan threatened him, fondly.

“…Yes, Yan.”

That killed the conversation for the time being, and Vemik sat and stared into the fire for a while as Yan and Vemet knapped at their flint cores, making a new spearhead for Jaran, a new cooking knife for Hetro and a hide-scraper for Meyta.

Fire that ran like water. In his mind’s eye he tried to imagine such a thing and envisioned rivers that glowed like firewood in the night snaking down the side of the mountain, blackening and burning everything they touched. Where did that fire come from? When water got hot it turned into clouds and flew away, everybody knew that. He poured a little water from his drinking-skin onto the fingers of his left foot and flicked the droplets onto the glowing logs. They hissed and boiled into nothing.

So. Hot things glowed…But water flew away before it was hot enough to glow. So the fire rivers of the mountain couldn’t be made of water, but of fire that flowed like water.

But where did flowing fire flow to? Little streams flowed to a bigger river, and maybe the bigger river flowed to a bigger river still. Who knew?

“Yan?” He asked.

“Still sky-thinking?”

Vemik nodded, ignoring the jab. “Do you know if anybody ever went down the big river?”

“Why?”

“I was wondering where the water goes.”

Yan glanced up at him. “Does it matter?” he asked.

“I don’t know,” Vemik confessed. “But… you knew about that mountain. Did you know that mattered?"

The Given Man wobbled his head thoughtfully and Vemet trilled a soft laugh, keeping his voice low to avoid waking the Singer. “I think he has you beaten there, Yan.”

“I never heard of anybody going far down the river,” Yan admitted. “I think Taki, the Given Man to my tribe when I was a boy, he said he knew what happened up the river. He said it comes to a high cliff and the water comes raining down with a noise like thunder, but that’s as far as he went. Down the river it’s fat and slow and there are lots of Yshek but no trees."

“I wonder where all that water goes, then…” Vemik mused.

“Back into the sky or the ground, probably,” Yan shrugged. “That’s where water comes from. It falls from the sky or wells up from the ground. Why do you ask?”

“You said fire flowed like water down that mountain. I was wondering where it went. And that made me wonder where the river of water went. But now I’m wondering why fire doesn’t come from the sky, or out of the ground.”

“Does your mind never sit still?" Vemet asked.

“Aren’t you interested? Even if there’s no real point in knowing, wouldn’t it be nice to know?"

Vemet sighed. “Maybe it would,” he allowed. “But where does it end? Pretend you know everything there is to know. What do you do next?”

“I could find a way to use it?" Vemik suggested.

“Fine… Suppose you learn that you could never know everything there is to know. What then?"

“That,” Vemik asserted, “would be a blessing.”

Yan and Vemet gave each other a familiar long-suffering shared look, and Vemet raised his hands and feet in resignation. “Think about whatever you want, son,” he said. “All I ask is you do your share of work-”

“Which he does,” Yan interjected fairly.

“Yes, which you do, but… please try not to tire us out with it. Every time you start asking those questions it makes my head hurt.”

Vemik nodded dejectedly, and went back to staring into the fire again.

On his shoulder, the Singer stirred. “It’s okay, Sky-thinker,” she murmured so that only he could hear. “I think your questions are interesting…”

She couldn’t have sung him a spell that made him happier.

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Remy Shekoni

Morning arrived with a creak and the sensation of an enormous warm human mass sitting down beside her, but it wasn’t until three brutally strong fingers delicately brushed the blanket out of her face that Remy actually awoke.

She blinked, frowned, then reached up to the dresser where she’d left her glasses, only to have them pressed into her hand.

“…time ’s’it?”

“Five-thirty.” He said. Warhorse, she recalled. Seemed to go by that to everyone…But what was his real name again? Adam? That sounded right. Adam what she didn’t know, but whatever.

God, her brain really wasn’t up to speed. It took her several dazed seconds to parse the time he’d just said, and several more to perch her glasses on her face and peer at the clock to double-check.

“…Tha’ss still night-time…" she objected.

“Yeah, sorry. I just didn’t want you to wake up and have no idea where I’d got to.”

Remy blinked at him. “Wh-?”

He gave her a smile that was much too cheerful and innocent for this time of the non-morning. “I gotta go do PT, hit the gym, I got a friend I promised to help out later… Y’know how it goes.” He stood up. “Sleep in all you like, there’s eggos in the fridge and I got a good shower… Key’s by the door. Just drop it in the mailbox when you go, yeah?”

This would have been far too much to process even in a completely alert and rested frame of mind. She needed to sleep…

She mumbled “Uh… sure…. Have fun…” and woke four hours later with her glasses askew when her phone buzzed loudly on the dresser.

Empty apartment. Eggos in the fridge. That stray thought triggered a cascade of memory and she pushed herself upright and straightened her glasses with a groan.

So… he’d just left her all alone in his apartment, with toaster waffles for breakfast. He hadn’t even woken her with a plate of hot Eggos and a coffee, just told her about the box in the fridge and then gone to… had he said the gym?!

The gym. Jesus Christ, she’d been jilted in favor of heavy metal.

The phone buzzed again, so she got up and stretched, looking around. It was a nice apartment: A studio penthouse with great views, bright and airy and warm floors. Pride of place went to the huge modern neo-rustic kitchen, and the whole thing was warmly decorated with a classy colourfulness accented by whites, pale woods and current-gen technology. Kind of a space-age hacienda, albeit one that smelled of sweat, sex and overdue laundry in no particular order.

The text messages turned out to be from her friend Melissa. She decided that texts wouldn’t do and called back instead.

Melissa answered straight away, and opened in characteristic fashion. She was infuriatingly fond of lightly taunting her friends. “Well, hey you! So, how was the pony ride?”

Remy wasn’t really in the mood for it. “He left me to sleep in while he’s gone to the gym." She said, before sarcastically adding “But there’s waffles in the fridge, so that’s nice.” The waffles seemed like an important detail, in the same exaggerated way as grit in a shoe.

“Yeahhhh, the scuttlebutt I heard was he’s kinda oblivious like that. Why d’you think I never hooked up with him?”

Remy “Uh-huh”-ed and checked the fridge. “…Oh, wow. What. A. Jerk!”

“What?”

“That box of Eggos? Turns out it’s a box of Eggo, singular. He left me one waffle."

Melissa sounded like she was trying desperately not to laugh. “Wow, Jesus. Okay. But other than that, Mrs. Lincoln, how was the play?”

“Wh-?” Maybe it was lack of sleep that tripped Remy up, but it took her a second to catch up with Melissa’s sense of humor. “Oh! Uh… The play was… okay, the play was great,” she confessed, though she was reluctant to admit it.

“Okay, okay…” Melissa was definitely laughing now. “I’ll tell you what-- meet me at Venezia. You need one of those pesto chicken ciabattas they do."

“That sounds exactly like what I need…” Remy agreed. “See you there.”

She luxuriated in the shower which turned out to be excellent as promised, then put on the change of clothes she’d brought with her, leaving the lone waffle to its fate.

There turned out to be a note under the key by the door. Warhorse had angular, amateurish handwriting but it was perfectly legible.

Remy,

I know leaving this AM wasnt real cool of me hope its OK would have stuck around if I could I swear if u want we could meet up this PM? Theres this really great trail I wanna show u ill make peshorkies theyre Gaoian snacks + really good!

My #s in ur phone if u wanna call.

-Horse

For a minute, Remy was sorely tempted. Last night really had been fun; he was witty, charming and breathtakingly strong. He was a genuinely nice guy too, even if he was simultaneously also kind of a thoughtless jerk. Honestly, she could forgive him for the sake of a little bit more no-strings-attached fun…

…But no. Her curiosity was satisfied. She summoned her willpower, deleted his number, and let herself out.

As requested, she dropped the key in his mailbox as she went.

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
The Dog House Gym, Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Jack Tisdale

“Okay! Good! One more!!”

People were trying not to stare and failing.

Adam co-owned a gym with one of his comrades, “The Dog House”, which catered specifically to serious strength training. It was a place of heavy metal, sweat and musk. Jack’s dad would have fit in perfectly.

Jack himself felt like a toothpick. It was vaguely humiliating, and he dealt with it the same way he did all the other humiliating crap in his life: he told it to get fucked and did his best anyway.

He gritted his teeth, heaved, and somehow managed to gouge just enough strength out of his shaking muscles to straighten his elbows. Adam promptly took the barbell off him and racked it with a huge beaming grin and no discernable effort whatsoever.

“Okay! Man, you’re a lot stronger than you give yourself credit for!”

“…You think?” Jack asked him, sitting up. He felt shaky and sore already.

“Bro, I’m not pussying around on ya. This is serious shit you’re handling for a guy your weight!”

It was hard to disbelieve that honest, smiling face, but Adam was also sharp as a tack behind it, and he gave Jack a brotherly slap on the back that came within a hair of knocking the breath out of him. “Come on. Nutrition break.”

Jack nodded wearily, glad for the break, and teetered upright to grab his lunch bag. He’d barely opened it and grabbed his lunch before Adam leaned over with a strange look on his face.

“Woah, woah woah!” he interjected, before Jack could finish unpacking it. “The fuck is that?!"

“…My lunch?”

"This?!" Adam snatched it out of his hand and inspected it. “…Bro, this is one slice of white bread, folded over with…” he opened it and peered inside. “…margarine, tuna paste and three Doritos.” He brandished it accusingly. “The fuck?”

Aware that the other guys in the room were nudging each other and grinning, Jack gritted his teeth and, with his ears going pink, he held his ground. “That’s my favourite sandwich!”

Somebody laughed, and that asshole immediately got to see Adam’s other side --a sharp and entirely angry stare that instructed everybody in the room to butt the fuck out. They all promptly found something else to look at, and one especially bright spark turned the radio up, hiding their conversation behind pounding heavy metal.

“…You were seriously wondering why you can’t get big?” Adam asked, turning back around. “Is this how you eat? Where’s your fuckin’ protein?!"

“It’s got tuna in it!”

“Like fuck it does! Man, I could get more protein from a picture of a goddamn tuna!" Adam weighed the sandwich in his hand. “Okay, you’re a smart guy, from a smart family. How many doctorates do your parents have between ’em, three?”

“Yeah.”

“So you’ve heard of conservation of mass, right?"

“Right….?” Jack nodded, frowning.

“How much does this weigh? Two ounces? Less?”

“That’s… what, about fifty grams? I guess…”

“And you weigh… what, sixty kilos soaking wet?” Adam asked.

“…Yeah?”

“And your target weight is…?”

“Ninety kilos.”

“Okay. Now where do you think that mass is coming from? It comes from what you eat, bro!" Adam sat down. “Math time. If this sandwich weighs fifty grams, how many of them would you need to have thirty kilos of sandwich?”

“Uh…” Jack closed one eye and squinted at the ceiling as he calculated. “…uh, six hundred.”

“So how many of these would you have to eat to reach ninety kilos?”

“…More than six hundred?”

“How much of this sandwich d’you think you convert to muscle?”

“…Not much?”

“Dude. None. This shit right here-" he brandished it contemptuously, “-is doin’ nothing for you."

“But the tuna paste-!”

“Dude. I’ve seen thicker layers of tuna on a vegan’s apron.”

“Like you’ve ever hung out with vegans.”

Adam snorted, and melted a bit. “Heh. Fine. But I may as well be right now, bro. Seriously, hasn’t your dad explained this shit? Mark knows gains.”

“Oh come on, everybody’s parents tell them to eat more…" Jack protested.

Adam sighed and looked skywards. "Me cago en Cristo, was I literally the only fifteen-year-old in history who actually listened to his father?" he asked rhetorically.

Jack laughed at that. “Probably.”

Adam laughed too, and gestured towards his own bag. “Okay. Let me introduce you to real nutrition."

He produced a bright blue tupperware box which turned out to be full of quite an appetising-looking rice-based meal, along with a shaker cup filled with milk in the top and a brown chocolatey powder in a separate container on the bottom. Jack watched as Adam poured the powder into the milk, re-sealed the cap, and shook it vigorously.

“Chicken breast and brown rice,” he said, ruefully. “At least six times a day. And a whey protein shake after every workout. And BCAAs and electrolytes during."

Jack gaped at him. “…This one box is more than I’d eat in a whole day!” he said.

“And there’s yer problem,” Adam nodded. “That’s why you’re not gaining, man. Your body can’t just fuckin’ summon muscles out of hyperspace or whatever. It’s gotta build ’em, and you’ve gotta give it the raw materials. Chicken breast, eggs, tuna, whey protein… the easier it is for your body to use, the better. But you need a lot of it, bro. You’re trying to pack on like seventy pounds here. Which means you’ve gotta eat way more than seventy pounds of food on top of what you need just to live."

“That makes sense I guess, but… Shit, that’s a lot.” Jack stared at it. “I mean, six times a day?"

“That’s my meal plan, yeah. And that’s just portable food, bro. In between there’s, like, three protein shakes, snacks, a couple gallons of water, supplement pills, and then there’s a real meal for lunch with the Lads, too. All said and done? I’m constantly drinking water, with and without electrolytes, and eating something every single hour I’m awake. And yeah, it’s fuckin’ tough to get used to that." Adam laughed. “Back in basic? Staff Sergeant Reed used to threaten me with a funnel, said he’d force the food down my throat with a stick.”

“Oh man… Okay, seriously, is Basic as bad as it sounds? Like, all the shouting and stuff?"

Adam held up a finger requesting patience as he efficiently wolfed down the food and the shake in less than a minute, staring thoughtfully at nothing as he chewed.

“Okay…” he said. “So… The first thing you gotta know is why they yell at you, and under what circumstances…"

Jack did something that didn’t come entirely easily to him and listened. Adam had a lot to say on the subject, and in straightforward fashion he laid out the surprisingly solid rationale, completely dispelling Jack’s lingering fear that it was just about hazing and bullying.

He hadn’t appreciated the level of responsibility it was possible to have without ever firing a shot in anger. Adam explained in detail how the seemingly silly assignments like hanging his shirts exactly an inch apart translated into a habit of paying attention to the tiniest details, and gave just a few examples of scenarios where that skill could prevent disaster.

“Suit tech especially,” he added. “Like, if you just glanced at the diagnostic and missed a problem in the life support pack, that could mean some poor Operator dies of carbon monoxide poisoning or whatever.”

“That’s… a lot of responsibility…” Jack said, quietly.

“Dude, you’re up to it.”

“You really mean it?”

“For real!” Adam nodded enthusiastically. “You’ve got the drive, you’ve got the game. All you need is the training. You can learn how to handle that kind of responsibility, bro, and they teach you by yelling at you."

“Why by yelling though?”

“Because if you can do it focused and right even when you’re being yelled at and stressed out, then you can do it focused and right every time.”

“That… makes sense.”

Adam nodded. “You’re a smart guy, except maybe for the sandwich thing…” he began, then grinned as Jack grimaced awkwardly and looked away. “Dumb fucks like me, we need to learn by doing. I figure if you understand the theory, that’s half the battle with you, huh?”

Jack picked at a loose flake of plastic at the end of one of his shoelaces. “…You know me pretty well for somebody I’ve not really spoken to since I was a kid…”

“Dude.” Adam gave him a crushing hug. “Ava and I used to help your sister babysit you, bro, remember?” He chuckled. “You were a fuckin’ handful, but if we just told you why we were doin’ things the way we were--y’know, gave you the rationale?--you were fine. You may’ve got bigger, but I don’t think that part changed much."

Jack didn’t have a response to that, and Adam sat in silence with him for half a minute before standing up.

“Anyway,” he said. “Can’t do more today, not with that weak-ass lunch. You get your ass home, get your dad to help you fill up properly, ’kay? And listen to him about this shit."

Jack nodded. “…Yeah. I’ll do that.”

Adam caught the downcast tone in his reply and frowned at him. “…You okay, bro?”

“Fine.” Now was really not the time or the place to talk about Sara.

Adam clearly wasn’t dumb enough to buy that, but he didn’t push. “…Alright. You’ve got my number, gimme a call if you need me, ’kay?” he said. “Otherwise I’ll see you Tuesday. Don’t forget to scan the QR code by the door.”

Jack nodded, threw on his jacket and scanned the code as he’d been told, tagging his workout on the tracking app.

He thrust his hands into his pocket and unconsciously cut the classic teenage figure as he mooched home in a mixed mood.

He had a lot to think about.

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
Cabal Communications Relay ZR343-9847X-AA4D9-BBB1B

Emergency Session 000033

++Substrate++: Session begun, Proximate. What happened?

++Proximate++: Stack 31 212 805-10 100-204-8050 has been discovered.

++Cynosure++: The failsafe? How?

++Substrate++: Who by?

++Proximate++: Four. I’m still working on the how, but I’m one miscalculation from being compromised.

++Cynosure++: Your egress?

++Proximate++: Secured. Two is furious and has ordered an emergency recall on all operations below priority one. I’m supposed to be arranging a meatspace strike force to attack the node’s physical infrastructure right now.

++Substrate++: The node is undefended.

++Proximate++: Defend it. Activate Chastise, have them tip off the Alliance. My strike force will be using a Dominion fleet.

++Substrate++: If the humans think the war has resumed…

++Cynosure++: Most likely their threats of joining either side are a bluff, but for certainty’s sake we had better make it impossible to tell which side struck first.

++Substrate++: I can put Metastasis on that.

++Cynosure++: Good. That stack is as hardened as we can make it but supervision will be necessary. I’ll recall Apoptosis and see to it.

++Substrate++: Good luck.

++SYSTEM++: User Cynosure has quit.

++Substrate++: …On a scale of one to ten, how fucked are we?

++Proximate++: Is that a humanism?

++Substrate++: A very good one.

++Proximate++: …I give it a nine.

++Substrate++: That’s what I thought.

++SYSTEM++: User Proximate has quit.

++SYSTEM++: Session closed.

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
Mrwrki Station, Unnamed System, Deep Space

Lewis Beverote

Life on Mrwrki was lots of work and very little play at the moment, but that was actually how Lewis liked it. Among other things, his actual routine hadn’t changed much, but the nature of the kind of work he was doing had improved dramatically. Now he actually had people to talk to and to learn from, rather than trying to self-educate from whatever texts Kirk was able to scrounge up and translate from all over the interstellar data networks.

It was so much easier to learn from other people. Especially if the other people were Sergeant Lucy Campbell.

She had picked up where Xiu had left off on helping him with his exercise. Although he’d developed a degree more enthusiasm for keeping himself fit than he’d ever held before, the fact was that exercise remained one of those subjects that the Lewis brain found mostly uninteresting.

The Lucy Campbell brain, on the other hand, enjoyed it and seemed to enjoy it even more when she had somebody to train and compete with.

“It’s nice,” she confided. “A lot of guys would be awkward about training with a girl who’s stronger than them.”

Lewis just shrugged, as best he could considering he was flat on his back and breathing heavily. As far as he was concerned, when it came to the standing overhead press then just repping the empty bar five times as she had just encouraged him to do was workout enough. But then, he’d always been one of the weak and scrawny ones. “Dude,” he panted, “I figure that ‘stronger than me’ is basically everyone anyway, so, uh, why should I give a crap?"

“You know, you’re fitter than you think,” she said, handing him a towel. “That bar weighs forty-five, and that’s not a bad weight for a novice. Any novice.”

“Thanks.”

“Come on. You’ve got some more in the tank.”

“Jeeesus, alright!” Lewis laughed and stood up again. She handed him the bar and demonstrated what she wanted him to do.

The truth was, he decided, he did enjoy exercise… when he was being tutored by somebody like Lucy. Among other things, she didn’t seem to have any concrete target in mind for him, she just seemed to enjoy having an excuse to spend time around him.

Teenage Lewis would have boggled at the thought. She wanted to spend time around him? But teenage Lewis hadn’t been aware of certain facts about the power of laughter, nor indeed of the power that came from actually respecting people on the basis of their skills and knowledge first. There were a lot of facepalm moments in his memory there.

Sometimes, he reflected that it was funny how being isolated from any human contact for so long had actually sharpened his social instincts. As if he’d mentally folded them carefully away in alphabetical order and now that they were actually needed again, he found them neatly organised, clean, oiled, sharpened and ready for use.

Alas, all good things had to end. She had her work to do and he had his, but…

“My place tonight?” she asked, as they finished squaring the gym away ready for the next users.

“Hmm. Got something in mind?”

“Yup!” She winked, and Lewis counted himself among the ranks of the very lucky.

“Magical secret surprise, huh?” he asked.

“Oh, it’ll be magical…” She grinned, and went on her way leaving him to stand there with a goofy grin that carried him buoyantly to his meeting with Lt. Col. Nadeau and Sergeant Lee.

There was the usual routine of answering queries from the military team, a handful of quick memos and then, as always, the conversation returned to the subject of the Coltainer probe itself.

“I find it interesting that you didn’t arm it.” Nadeau mused, studying the holographic schematic with interest.

Lewis produced his cheekiest grin as he swiped his hands through the custom control interface he’d worked out for his lab. It was straight out of Minority Report or maybe Iron Man, a fully gesture-based context-sensitive system that, okay, still had the odd bug to work out but by and large it worked exactly as intended. “Dude, who says I didn’t?”

Nadeau leaned in and frowned at the field equations he’d just called up, and the attached schematics. “…doesn’t that put extra stress on the cooling system?”

“Sure, but only about seven percent. And meantime the assholes are getting a gamma burst to the face every time they shoot your ass.” Lewis called up his graph of projected energy tolerances and feedback. The two lines crossed quite a long way to the right. “See here? You have to be up against something with a way bigger power supply than you before the extra load really starts to bite."

“…We need to roll that out to the existing military hardware,” Sergeant Lee commented.

“Always worth having another ace up our sleeve…” Nadeau agreed. “But is that all the weaponry it has?"

“Even I’m kinda leery about just straight arming a V-N probe, man," Lewis told him. “Face it, what we’re making here is a Replicator, Dawkins-style, you know?”

“Your point?”

“If it replicates, it can mutate. If it mutates, it can evolve. If it can evolve then… well, maybe it’ll evolve out of some of the safety features, right? What happens if sometime down the line one of these motherfuckers evolves to shoot everything on sight?”

“That could take thousands of generations. I would think that by then galactic technology will be more than a match.”

“Sure, but what if what it finds is some poor bastards who’re just sending up their version of the Gemini rockets or whatever? Then it parks itself in orbit and starts bitchslapping them with focused gamma lasers and God-Rods. How d’you think we’d have coped if something like that rocked up on Earth in the nineteen-fifties?"

“Nukes would have gone flying everywhere,” Lee nodded.

“Right! So I thought, maybe give it spikes but no claws, y’know?”

Nadeau nodded. “Okay, you’ve thought it through. Good.”

“Dude, I didn’t spend all that time just scratching my butt.”

Nadeau snorted and Lee chuckled. “Fair enough,” Nadeau replied. He considered his notes thoughtfully for a second and then nodded. “So. We have a fairly comprehensive plan for bringing this together… the only real question I’ve got left for you, Lewis, is what you want to do?”

Lewis gave him a blank look. “Me?”

“How long did you say you’ve been stuck here? Half a year?”

Lewis leaned forward sharply. “Dude, you are not getting rid of me!"

“I wasn’t even suggesting that,” Nadeau reassured him. “You’re far too valuable. I want you on the team permanently. But I was going to suggest that if you need a vacation, now’s the time."

Lewis sat back and thought about it. “Man. What, like, take a trip back to Earth? See Cimbrean maybe?”

“We have a lot of work to do here before we start testing the Coltainer. Everyone’s going to need to familiarize themselves with your design, with the nanofactory…” Nadeau circled a hand to indicate the thousand and one other things that needed to happen. “Point is, this is about the only window of opportunity you could have to take a break. You’ve been out of touch for years…”

“Yeah man, I dig you. Thanks. But I’m cool where I am. Maybe if and when Lucy gets some leave, huh?”

“Lu-? Oh. Sergeant Campbell.” Nadeau nodded. “Yes, fair enough.”

“Anyhow, I really want to start working on completely nightmare-proofing the Coltainer.” Lewis continued. “There’s, like, a fuckzillion ways that a self- replicating space probe could bite us so hard in the ass that we get a toothache.”

“Yeah, I’d rather not accidentally grey goo some poor planet,” Lee mused.

“Dude, grey goo is when the nanites go crazy and cover everything in self- replicating grey… well, goo. Hence the fuckin’ name, man. You can’t have a grey goo scenario with a two hundred meter metal box."

“Can we accept,” Nadeau raised a placating hand, “that the sergeant meant ‘uncontrolled replication’?"

“Dude, we’re building the literal future of the galaxy here. This shit is our legacy. Using the right terminology is fucking important if we don’t want it to go hella fuckin’ wrong."

"Could the Coltainer destroy a planet?" Lee asked.

“Not, like, quickly…" Lewis shook his head. “But sure, it could. Fleet of mining drones, solar collectors in orbit… give it a few million years and some exponential growth it could rip a planet apart and chuck it into the sun or turn it into a new asteroid belt or… whatever, just move it out-system and pile all the rocks up around a gas giant for a new moon.”

“So, not exactly the Death Star, then.”

“Shyeah. I mean, depopulating a plant? Fucking child’s play compared to destroying it. Turn a decent-sized asteroid into a bajillion RFGs and nudge ’em in the right direction. And that’s probably the difficult way to do it. How about, uh, giant forcefield lenses and mirrors? Direct the power of the star back on that planet like a bug under a magnifying glass? Guvnurag tech could do that."

“Mm.” Both Nadeau and Lee nodded solemnly. They were, Lewis recalled, both experts in electrostatic fields themselves. Both of them would be fully aware of how far in advance of human hardware the Guvnuragnaguvendrugun must be to have developed the system forcefields. The theoretical basis by which those shields hardened in response to events that might be light-hours distant from the emitter was still a subject of head-scratching bewilderment.

That was the Guvnurag though. Nature had gifted them with long lives and patient, methodical brains which made them exceptionally well-equipped for the kind of steady rational deliberations that lent themselves to incrementing and polishing what they already had. They were, by Corti metrics, the second most technologically sophisticated species in the known galaxy. Lewis suspected that this was egotism on the Directorate’s part--the Corti were so focused on prestigious breakthroughs that brought them renown that they failed to value steady iteration.

“When were you planning to launch a proof-of-concept?” Nadeau asked.

Lewis sighed. “Uh… I guess we could start building a basic one tomorrow. The schematic here’s already got the hell-the-fuck-no killswitch built in. It wouldn’t be programmed, but…"

“That’s fine. Programming will take forever anyway,” Lee commented. “But we’ve got unlimited capacity for prototyping thanks to the nanofactory. Seems like a shame to neglect it.”

“Can’t argue,” Lewis agreed. “Okay. I’ll have the station fab up the current Alpha build and we’ll see how she looks.”

Nadeau nodded. “Excellent. In that case, I’ll see you same time tomorrow, if not before then.”

Lewis paused and grimaced. “Nah, give it a day. Vedreg went to sleep last night and he gets… cranky… if we run the nanofac without him.”

“Couldn’t you wake him up?”

“Dude, in relative terms he’s had, like, half an hour of sleep. You’d be cranky as shit if I woke you up after just that and, y’know, dude might be docile but he still literally weighs a tonne.”

“We need to be in his good books, sir,” Lee pointed out, superfluously. “He still hasn’t delivered those footballs.”

“And he hasn’t finished reviewing the schematic,” Lewis added. “Okay, so he may be slow, but he’s thorough."

“Fine! Fine. Far be it for me to ignore one of our only two ET advisors…” Nadeau made a note on his tablet then stood up. “Keep me informed.”

“Sir.”

“You bet, dude.”

Lewis massaged his face once Nadeau was gone. “Okay! Early run.”

“You don’t sound enthusiastic,” Lee observed. Lewis had to give the guy credit, he was a talented spotter of the obvious.

He mentally slapped himself for the uncharitable thought. Something had badly harshed his usual vibe, and he was having trouble putting his finger on what exactly had got him so antsy. He trusted his instincts enough to believe that if he was being uncool then that meant something was off-kilter, but…

Maybe the problem was that he couldn’t think of the problem because there was no problem? He gave up and tried to mellow out. When in doubt, be honest. Thank you, Allison.

“Bein’ straight, dude?” he asked, “Something ain’t sitting right with me and it beats the fuck outta me what it might be.”

“Nerves?”

“Could be. I’unno bro, I hate to go all Star Wars on ya, but I’ve got a bad feeling about this…”

Lee clapped him on the shoulder. “We’ll take it carefully, eh?” he said.

“Sure. Super careful.”

“Then whatever’s wrong, we’ll hopefully pick it up.”

“Sure.”

Lee apparently ran out of comforting words, and settled for giving him a comforting clap on the shoulder and an apologetic smile before excusing himself. Lewis had trouble getting his head around the guy. He was fit, lean and focused just like all the other soldiers, but for whatever reason while most of the others had basically accepted the civilian in their midst as a quirk of the station, Lee only seemed to relax when he thought Lewis wasn’t around.

Maybe the thing to do was just chill with him socially sometime soon?

If only the Lewis timetable had enough room for it. Still… He’d take the first opportunity he could once the test run was complete. It’d be a shame to let any awkwardness stand.

After all, they had a big hill to climb ahead of them.

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
Uncharted Class 12 planet, Near 3KPc arm

665

At last.

The elderly native female and her defiance had been… vexing. But more vexing still was the way her whole tribe had just vanished, and apparently used every trick they knew from their primitive hunter-gatherer lifestyle to cover their tracks. They had done so well that the scout drones had entirely failed to pick out their trail among all the other signs of routine coming and going around the village.

Eventually, Six-six-five had been forced to resort to spiraling out from the village in a time-consuming search pattern that was almost a desperation measure--every passing day had weathered and eroded the trail and forced him to search further and further out for fainter and fainter clues.

As a result, Abrogator Twelve was badly behind schedule, and the whole continental sweep-and-clear was now held up. Abrogators were standing silently in the forest wherever they had happened to be at the moment Six-six-five had ordered them to halt. Until A-12 caught up, there was a dangerous gap in the net through which a population might still slip and any population large enough to breed, even a bottlenecked one that would be plagued by inbreeding problems for generations, was just unacceptable.

He could not fail this test. If Hierarchy assets weren’t so badly stretched and divided right now, this opportunity might have been millennia in coming. Instead, the hideous containment situation around Earth, the whispers of treason in the ranks and the even darker whispers of some thing implacably stalking Igraens through the dataspace like some digital deathworld monster were keeping more senior agents occupied.

Exterminating a handful of stone-age primitives had therefore been relegated rather lower in the order of seniority than it otherwise usually was, and Six- six-five was beginning to understand why the task was so high-level. Deathworlders were tenacious, intelligent and quick to catch on when they were being hunted. This was not the first group to notice the destruction of a nearby village, but it was the first to give him such a difficult chase.

But no longer.

He’d learned from the loss of two drones at the hand of one of these particular primitives, too. Now, he contented himself with holding the drone back and watching them from a discreet distance while Abrogator Twelve made best speed to intercept. Let them try and destroy it--the only weaponry on this pitiful backwater that could possibly harm an Abrogator was mounted on the Abrogators.

The unit was frustratingly close to striking distance when the priority override signal came in, stopping his entire operation in its tracks.

++Incoming connection… Established++
++Joining session: Emergency Task Unit Op94 325 545++
++Joined as 0665++

++0014++: Welcome, 0665.

++0665++: <Frustration> Now is not a good time.

++0014++. <Stern reprimand> This is an emergency reassignment. Whatever you were doing is less important.

++0665++: <Explanation> I will have to restart a whole cull from first principles.

++0014++: Unfortunate, but I repeat: This is more important.

++0665++: <Resignation, mounting concern> Understood. I await instructions.

++0014++: We are waiting for three more.

++SYSTEM++: User 0282 Joined

++0014++: Welcome, 0282.

++0282++: <Irritation> This had better be important.

++0665++: <grim humor> That was my sentiment.

++SYSTEM++: User 0098 Joined.

++0014++: Welcome 0098.

++0098++: What’s going on?

++0014++: I don’t know. I was ordered to assemble this task group and now we’re waiting for instructions…

++SYSTEM++: User 0002 Joined.

++0014++: <deference> …welcome, 0002.

++0002++: <Terse briefing> We have identified a traitor physical hub. We don’t know what data they are archiving there, but we believe they intend to share it with the humans. We are probing its dataspace periphery as I speak, but successful intrusion seems unlikely. Therefore we are assigning you to destroy the hardware in meatspace. We anticipate that the traitors will assign their own meatspace assets to resist.

++SYSTEM++: Datapackage Available for Access

Six-six-five was so stunned that he briefly lost control of the Corti body he was wearing, which blinked and looked around in confused disbelief as its original owner’s personality reasserted itself in the moment before he recovered his composure and took over again. Hastily, he downloaded the Datapackage.

It contained a clear and concise briefing of what he was to do, where he was to go and whom he was to control, and it was an absolute death-knell for his Cull. Not only was he going to have to start over from basic principles, he would have to terminate his present host and it would be [months] before he could find a suitable replacement and engineer an excuse to slip away into deep space, travel to this planet, excavate his own command bunker and start over.

He buried his resentment. Fourteen had been accurate: this was more important.

++0002++: Are there any questions?

++0014++: Discretion Code?

++0002++: Overt. Contain. Amputate. Escalate.

Well. Instructions simply didn’t come more brute-force than that. In the grid of Hierarchy discretion codes, ‘Overt Contain Amputate Escalate’ translated to: ‘Do not be subtle. Take over as quickly as you can, kill all witnesses and silence all communications, destroy everything when you are done and let senior agents worry about damage control’.

++0002++: <Impatience> Any other questions?

++0014++: None.

++0098++: No.

++0282++: No questions.

++0665++: No, Two.

++0002++: Execute.

Six-six-five gave no thought whatsoever to his unfortunate host as he recalled the scout drones to their Abrogators and then ordered his purloined body’s life support unit, the one that protected it from the fiercely fatal conditions of this planet, to liquify it. The Corti’s biomass would be recycled into nourishment for the next host form he installed in that tank. He noted in an abstract sense that the body felt a terrifying degree of agony as it was destroyed, but this was purely academic knowledge--he himself felt nothing.

He traversed dataspace as a high-priority package and shot down through nested layers of addresses and identity markers, drilling directly toward the target he’d been assigned, the one prepared and ready to receive him…

“…Sir? Shipmaster, is everything alright?”

Six-six-five hastily interrogated his new host’s suppressed personality for an in-character reply based on recent memory and context. An easy one presented itself.

“Don’t interrupt me when I’m thinking.”

“…Sorry sir.”

Clearly this particular shipmaster was a devotee of the ‘fear and awe’ school of leadership-by-bullying. That suited Six-six-five’s purposes just fine--the Vzk’tk subordinate’s timid silence bought him time to riffle through the host’s memories, awareness and skill-set, draw what he needed into short term access, and enact a plan.

Step one: Walk round the desk. Step two, execute a rapid series of command overrides far too quickly for any meat creature using a clunky physical interface to achieve using the shipmaster’s access codes.

The office door locked and sealed itself. Every other door on the ship including the airlocks opened.

The subordinate was still looking around in terrified bewilderment at the slamming explosive sound of all the air in the hull rushing out into space when Six-six-five drew his host’s pulse pistol and shot her through the head.

++0665++: First objective secured.

++0014++: Quick work. Well done.

Six-six-five allowed himself a moment of grim amusement as he worked to replace the massacred crew by injecting pseudosentient control algorithms into the ship’s systems. He was standing, he learned, aboard the Dominion Regional Patrol Second Order Command Ship Verdict Manifold in the body of its commanding officer. Under his command were fifty ships, most of which were rapid outrider and rapid attack ships that escorted his ship, three medium- weight space superiority platforms and the heavy gun barge Dwr Rmwr.

++0665++: An expedient solution presented itself.

Information started flooding in. The fleet was cruising at a stately thirty kilolights, and his element were the forward scouts, ranging a quarter of a light-year ahead of the fleetmaster’s main group, and the two flanks. With the outrider’s sophisticated sensors sweeping spacetime ahead of them for the tell-tale quantum field fluctuations that advertised the presence of a serious distortion such as might be generated by a warp drive or gravity spike, the fleet would inevitably have generous warning of hostile contact.

++0098++: Objective secured.

++0282++: Likewise.

++0014: Good. 0002 Is generating our cover. Wait for the orders to come in then amputate and execute.

Six-six-five sent a pulse of acknowledgement and busied himself with infiltrating his overrides into the interlinked command systems that networked his ship with the rest of the fleet. He took a moment to appreciate what he was doing: There were fifty-four ships in his fleet, the smallest of which had a crew of ten and the largest of which had a crew of more than two thousand.

All were his to end. Regrettable, but necessary.

The wait was tedious. There were limits on just how fast a meat-creature could act and how quickly orders could be relayed through the medium of spoken orders, and 0002 didn’t have the luxury of massacring everybody their host spoke with. The intelligence and orders would spread through the Dominion’s naval command structure rapidly by the subjectively glacial standards of physical information, but as soon as they did…

As soon as they did, he would no longer be shackled by such pedestrian pacing, and the hunt could begin.

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
The White House, Washington DC, USA, Earth

President Arthur Sartori

One of the first things President Sartori had done upon entering the Oval Office was to have a discreet holographic projector installed on the desk. One of the good ones that in the future might even allow him to have a conversation with somebody as if they were physically present in the room with him.

So far it hadn’t really been used for anything more than a TV and for face- time with his daughter, but it was showing its value today, with so many of America’s most influential invited to watch the Mars landing alongside him. Among them was the man of the hour himself, Moses Byron.

Sartori had requested his presence on the grounds that nothing could possibly be lost by reminding the enterprising billionaire exactly where he stood in the pecking order of power.

They traded pleasantries, shook hands and smiled for the camera.

“Quite a moment,” Sartori observed, as soon as they had a moment without a lens pointed at them.

“It’s been a tough road,” Byron said. “A lot of hard lessons learned.”

“Hmm. Don’t go forgetting any of them.”

Threat duly delivered, he clapped Byron on the shoulder and gestured for him to take a seat on the couch next to him.

Misfit was a surprisingly pretty ship considering that she paid no homage at all to aerodynamics or any notion of sleekness. Maybe it was the livery of silver, charcoal and red, or perhaps it was just pride in the ingenuity that had gone into her, but she cut a splendid figure in the artist’s impressions.

Too bad that there wasn’t a second ship out there to record her from the outside. The best seat in the house was the camera mounted above and behind Xiu Chang, showing the back of her helmet as she began the descent phase over the western end of the Valles Marineris, which the commentator helpfully informed them was a region known as the Noctis Labyrinthus.

Moses certainly seemed pleased with the result. “That girl’s just an incredible human being,” he enthused. “You familiar with her story, Mr. President?”

Sartori nodded that he was. In fact in just a few short months Miss Chang had planted the seeds for a burgeoning alliance with the Gao, an alliance that was already bearing fruit in ways that Moses Byron didn’t suspect. Several organisations had been waiting to approach her once she’d enjoyed a decent interval of peace back on Earth.

Byron, characteristically boorish, had pounced first. “The other two are pretty special as well,” he was saying. “We sure lucked out with them. Not many people have that kind of dedication and drive.”

The live stream had several angles on the descent. There was a camera in the crew quarters looking out of their cupola window, and also one in each of the crew workstations. Etsicitty seemed unflustered and calm as he worked with three different touch-screens which the text ticker said were controlling the ship’s many sensors, feeding telemetry to the pilot to help her calculate and control their descent, avoid hazards and select a landing zone. Every so often, he and Chang exchanged a few words as they narrowed down their options.

Buehler was the opposite--she was a worker bee, twisting and turning efficiently this way and that inside her engineering station as she balanced power loads and kept a close eye on dozens of different systems at once. Sartori, being something of a firearms enthusiast himself, noted with interest that the right thigh of her excursion suit was equipped with a holster, though it was empty for now.

“I’d like to meet them,” he declared.

“We can… probably arrange that.” Byron frowned in furious calculation. “I guess we can postpone the mission launch by a day…”

“Too bad my schedule’s not so flexible,” Sartori told him. “But let me know when they get back, hmm?”

“I’ll do that.”

They sat and made small-talk for the next eight minutes as the ship’s descent played out. Everything looked quite smooth and uneventful, really. Not that Sartori wanted anything to go wrong, but the reality was steady and really quite uninteresting. In fact he was so deep in discussion with his wife Bella that he almost missed the actual landing. In exactly the same deceptive way that the ground snuck up on an airliner, Mars was just there, rushing along below Misfit without it being clear when they had gone from high altitude to low.

Chang had nimble hands, and they went to work flying over the controls to arrest their forward momentum and hold them motionless in the air for a heartbeat, before she eased down and Misfit kissed onto Martian soil with nary a jolt. In fact it took Sartori a second to realize that the historic landing had even happened.

It certainly fooled Buehler. “Tell me when we’re down…”

“We’re down.”

“Wow. You sure?”

Chang giggled “I’m sure. SUBLIME DED idle, EACS to idle, power down ESFALS…. Power down flight systems.”

“Smooth! Okay, power profile to field idling and… done. Mission control, Misfit has landed.”

Some muted cheers and applause swept the room.

“Congratulations,” Sartori shook Byron’s hand and ignored the chatter of cameras. He watched on the screen as Chang took what was clearly a deep steadying breath and ran through her after-flight checks. Etsicitty was already hauling sample boxes and crates out of storage and unpacking some tools, while the women made sure their ship was happy and comfortably settled down.

It wasn’t long before the three of them met in the middle of the ship. They shared a quick three-way hug and some words of encouragement too quiet for the cameras to hear before loading the first set of sample equipment onto the dumbwaiter.

Sartori nodded appreciatively. Whether the three were a good team by nature or by training, they clearly had a great relationship and cooperation, and fell into an easy rhythm that got the work done in seconds.

Chang took a deep breath. “Okay Omaha, I guess we’re ready to head outside.”

“Copy that, Xiu. Good luck.”

The view switched to an outside camera just as they were running through checking their suit seals and systems, and conversation in the room quieted slightly before falling almost completely silent as the airlock cycled and their egress ladder extended out and down. It sounded strange through the camera’s microphone and thin Martian atmosphere, as did the surprisingly loud clank of Chang’s boot lowering onto the first step of the ladder.

“So far so good, excursion suit feels nice and comfortable. Air temperature is… minus forty-seven degrees. Nice clear day, hardly any wind…”

She reached the bottom step, paused to look up at Etsicitty who gave her a thumbs up, and jumped the last eighteen inches to the Martian surface.

The impact raised a puff of dust that blew away on the breeze. She looked down at her feet for a second and there was a clear soft sigh on the line as if the magnitude of the moment had finally settled on her, and everyone in the room shut up to hear what she would say.

Her delivery was perfect. She nodded with the air of a woman assessing a job well done, then raised her head and spoke lightly and with confidence.

“’From Mars to the stars, this is only the second small step.”

Sartori sat back and clapped three times before raising a congratulatory fist as similar applause erupted around him. “Nailed it.”

She really had. Byron was beaming with pride as she stepped back and let first Etsicitty, then Buehler drop off the ladder behind her. The view switched to Chang’s helmet camera as she looked around and took in the view.

Sartori had expected Mars to be desolate, and it obviously was: there wasn’t a shred of plant life to be seen, much less any fauna, but what it DID have was scenery. Chang had landed them a hundred meters from the cliff edge of one of the famous Valles Marineris, and the three of them quickly assessed that their suits were functioning perfectly and struck out toward the cliff, looking around as they went. There was no flag-planting or anything like that--Moses Byron clearly felt that having his corporate group’s emblem emblazoned proudly on the side of the ship was sufficient--but they did pause to take a photo of the real first footprints on Mars.

Unlike the ones on the Moon, these would be gone probably even before they got back to the ship. There was definitely a wind up which carried a hiss of sand over them and was already nibbling at their edges.

“So what’s on their itinerary up there?” he asked Byron, but kept a wary eye on something that was happening at the door. A year in the job had given him a nose for when he was about to get some kind of important breaking news, and right now it was itching.

“Gathering rock and soil samples, mostly, and lots of photos. The big work’s out of the way, we’ve proven they can land on a-”

Sartori raised a hand to shut him up as one of his aides approached him to whisper in his ear. “Sorry to interrupt, Mister President, but… it looks like the alien war just sparked off again. We’ve got General Sawyer and Colonel Stewart on the line.”

“Right…” Sartori stood up and twitched his suit jacket into place. “Ladies and gentlemen, we’ll have to cut this short, something important has come up. Thank you all for being here.”

The room cleared with commendable swiftness, and surprising grace on Byron’s part. He shook Sartori’s hand and was escorted out, leaving the President alone with his aides, advisors, and the feed from Mars.

He took a second to appreciate the breathtaking view from the clifftop that the three explorers were now standing on and looking out over, then nodded to his Aide to change the feed.

Two screens, bearing the faces of one of the Chiefs of Staff and the CO of the 946th, shimmered in to replace the reds and browns of Mars with lots of cool Air Force blue.

“Okay,” he asked, standing in front of them and tucking his thumbs into his belt buckle, “…What do we know?”

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
Valles Marineris, Planet Mars, Sol

Julian Etsicitty

“Be careful, Julian!"

Julian would have given up the rest of his left leg for the opportunity to mop his brow, a maneuver precluded but also made fortunately unnecessary by his helmet, and looked around as he took a moment to restore his calm good mood. Mars had a definite desolate charm to it, but that charm was rapidly fading as he did his best to keep up with the steady supply of interesting features that Xiu kept finding via their Flycatcher UAV, while Allison ranged further afield taking pictures and recording the mission for posterity. They’d been doing science for less than an hour, and were making a damn good case for future human missions. Three humans picking over the two hundred meter radius around their ship were already turning up things that all the rovers might have trundled slowly past without noticing.

Uplifting as that was, Julian could have done without having his ear filled by the nagging voice of his geological overseer on Earth, Professor Magnus Ogden. It would honestly have been nicer if they hadn’t been using close-range superluminal comms to eliminate the twenty minute light delay with Earth. At least then the messages coming his way might have had a filter on them.

“Professor,” he explained again, “That box is a powered stasis container. The samples literally can’t come to harm inside it."

Again, this observation did nothing to dissuade Professor Ogden that all was well. “That’s no excuse for throwing it around like a baseball, young man.”

Julian bit back a sharp retort that baseballs were a good deal less massive than stasis crates and went to the happy place where he imagined people on the Internet listening in on the conversation and admiring him for his couth in the face of his abrasive academic overlord.

“Yes, professor.” he agreed, and discreetly turned up the volume in his other headset, the one that Drew Cavendish had kindly agreed to build in for him. A new track had just come on.

“♫♪found out today your life’s not the same. Not quite as perfect as it was yesterday but-♫♪”

“Julian, can you hear music?”

Nobody could begrudge him a little white lie for the sake of his sanity, surely? “…No professor?”

Ogden did not sound convinced. “Hrrm. Come on man, you still have two crates to fill. Chop chop!”

He may as well have shouted ‘Mush!’ and cracked a whip. Julian just about managed to avoid sighing. He looked up at Xiu as she returned to the ship with the drone under her arm. She gave him a wry sympathetic smile. “Survey’s done,” she said. Sound propagated just fine through the Martian atmosphere, albeit in a tinny and quiet way and they had to speak loudly to be heard through their helmets. “I’ve got to run the ship checks.”

“That’s fine!” Julian nodded and gave her a thumbs up. She had a way of lifting his spirits even in such a businesslike interaction. “I think we gave the academics enough material for a lifetime.”

He hauled the third empty crate off the dumbwaiter and struck out for his next collection site.

Sample collection was not as simple as just cramming the rocks in there, despite Professor Ogden’s assertion that every cubic centimeter of the container was of incalculable scientific value. Every single sample needed to be carefully wrapped, labelled and tagged with its collection site--Every time he found an appropriate stone he had to unsling his tablet then painstakingly zoom in on the ultra-high-definition aerial footage from the drone. The image was astonishingly detailed. He’d been able to zoom in on the lettering of his own name on his helmet and make out the surface texture of his suit, and with it he could identify and indicate exactly which rock he was collecting, right down to the tiny flecks that could have lined the bottom of a goldfish bowl.

…Now there was an extravagantly decadent thought. Martian aquarium gravel. It belatedly occurred to him to wonder if there was room on the ship for a small fish tank.

A new and blessedly familiar voice filled his ear. “Hi Julian, Clara Brown here.”

“Hi, doc. What can I do for ya?”

“Professor Ogden’s, uh… decided to go oversee the operation in more of a hands-off capacity.” Clara said. There was a definite wink in her voice at that and Julian couldn’t resist a grin. There were times when he loved the Byron Group.

“Too bad, I was just starting to warm up to him.”

“I could get him back if you want…” You had to know Clara pretty well to catch the teasing merriment in her suggestion, but Julian had spoken to her at least twice a day for the last six months. They had a solid professional friendship.

“No, no…” Julian managed to avoid sounding hasty. “We’ll be okay.”

“If you insist,” Clara’s smile was audible. “Anyway, Professor Mitchellson’s super excited about that feature you said might have been an old knickpoint, could you check that out for him please?”

“Gladly.”

“Thanks.”

A ‘please’ and a thank-you’. Such basic courtesies seemed like a welcome luxury as Julian hoisted the last empty sample crate easily onto his shoulder and hummed along with his music as he made his way to the feature in question. He grinned at Allison as she turned and took his picture. The Group’s PR people were going to love that one.

Martian gravity was kind of a pleasure to work in. It was lower even than galactic standard, and Julian was entirely familiar with the distinction between mass and weight. In the low gravity the weight of even a full box was entirely manageable and so even though the mass of the crate was unchanged, once he had it in hand and moving it was pleasantly easy to transport.

“So,” Allison began as she joined him, “How’s our rock collection coming?”

Julian laughed. “Our scientifically invaluable samples are coming along just fine," he said with a teasing grin as they ambled up the rise toward a feature that had been tentatively identified as the possible remnants of an unimaginably ancient prehistoric waterfall.

“You gonna collect a souvenir?” she asked.

“Oh yeah. Of course! But, uh… okay, how about some of this fine gravel? We could line the bottom of a fish tank with it.”

“Martian fish tank?” Allison considered it. “…That’d sure be unique. And decadent. Anybody else wanting some would need to spend a few billion.”

“Yyyup.” Julian grinned.

"We can hear you guys, you know," Clara interjected. “If you wanted a fish tank on the ship you kinda shoulda asked before now…”

Allison snorted and waved her hand in front of her helmet cam as a greeting. “Spoilsport.”

“How about if I requisition a live specimen holding tank?” Julian asked.

“We’re not that dumb, space cowboy.”

“Too bad. The equipment room could do with some life and color.”

Clara didn’t reply. Julian didn’t mind that--they’d reached the knickpoint, and he knelt in the dirt to start the process of identifying the samples by location and painstakingly gathering them.

It wasn’t exactly the glamorous end of the scientific wedge, but Julian didn’t care. He hummed happily along with his music as he worked and let Allison do her job with the camera. She hadn’t been thrilled at first to inherit the role of mission chronicler, but had warmed to the idea when Xiu had pointed out that it placed control over their privacy in her hands. Besides, her job was to look after them. She was the engineer who kept their ship flight-worthy, the medic who’d stabilize them and secure them in the stasis safety of their bunks if they were wounded, and the gunman who’d keep them alive if the violence started. Recording and filtering their public image seemed like a natural extension of that role.

Finally, he was done. Even in Martian gravity, kneeling on the floor was a recipe for feeling strained, and he stood up with a grateful sigh. “Last crate’s full, Clara.”

“Copy that. Soil samples?”

“Check.”

“Geophysics survey?”

“Did that.”

“Air samples?”

“Taken.”

“That concludes the mission, then.”

Julian nodded, and looked around. “…Think we’ll ever come back?” he asked.

“Humans? Definitely,” Clara predicted. “You specifically? I don’t know.”

He nodded and hoisted the crate onto his shoulder before striking out back towards Misfit.

“We’ll see, I guess.”

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
Dataspace

665

Space combat, as ever, was a massacre. A shocking one, although Six-six-five was somewhat uncaring on that score given that he had been pulled away from annihilating a deathworld species to be here.

Both Alliance and Dominion military dogma called for seeding the enemy fleet’s space with gravity spikes, meaning that once the fleets committed, disengagement was effectively not an option. Battles that weren’t a one-sided slaughter inevitably resulted in the victor limping home a shadow of their former strength, leaving most of their fellows to mingle with the wreckage of the annihilated foe.

He watched the sensor data with about a quarter of his attention, idly marvelling at the energies being deployed. The “Dominion” fleet had narrowed into a tight speartip and aimed itself at the heart of the looser Alliance formation. It was an utterly callous tactic--the smaller ships screened and died for the bigger ones. Their sacrifice, as overlapping Alliance firepower tore them to shreds, allowed the heavy hitters in the core of the wedge to drive forward and deliver their big guns right into the enemy’s midriff, where they could wreak indiscriminate havoc. A flesh-and-blood commander using that tactic would have been feared and reviled by their subordinates.

But of course, there were no living crew aboard any of those ships.

The gross gigajoules on show though were… spectacular. Barrages of iron plasma were being hurled across hundreds of kilometers of space at single-digit percentages of the 3-causality limit, with one of two results: At first they were slapped aside by equally potent shielding systems, but as those shields overheated and failed they would burst through, and the structure of a starship would melt and run like candlewax.

Through this high-energy carnage zipped fighters by the dozen, tiny ships that were little more than a big gun, a bigger reactor to power it, and enough engines to get those two things moving. The accelerated plasma in the battlespace was pouring off radiation, from which the pilots of those little craft were only barely shielded. Six-six-five couldn’t imagine tolerating an existence like that--it seemed like a death sentence. Not a second went by without one of the strike craft being smashed by some hazard or another.

They were undeniably effective, though. Wherever a squadron managed to outmaneuver their opposite numbers and line up an attack run, one of the big ships was doomed.

Six-six-five’s command ship was at the core of the formation, behind layer after ablative layer of more expendable craft whose overlapping shield envelopes meant that by the time the odd stray iron ions reached it, they were far too alone to have any effect.

Everything was on course for a decisive victory. The enemy fleet hadn’t even started out with enough firepower to ablate the Hierarchy fleet quickly enough to prevent the objective’s destruction, and they were suffering from significant attrition of their own. The target’s survival was measured in minutes, at most.

++0014++: <Concern> Curious…

Alone on the ship he’d depopulated, Six-six-five paced anxiously. Their victory wasn’t so completely assured that nothing could conceivably go wrong…

++0665++: <Query> A problem?"

++0014++: <Explanation> Some strange local dataspace activity. Be on your guard--the traitors may attempt something.

++0665++: <Wary curiosity> Could you define ‘strange’?

++0014++: Some traffic that shouldn’t be present. It seems to have slipped into your subnet. Can you verify?"

++0665++: <Compliance>

He withdrew his attention from meatspace, trusting in the daemons he had injected into the fleet’s command systems to handle the business of the battle while he hunted down the anomaly.

Local dataspace was a warzone in its own right. Swathes of it had gone dark thanks to the demise of every living thing aboard the Dominion fleet, and more nodes still were crashing and rebooting in response to the digital assault on the data confluence that was the Cabal traitors’ little cache, and those were just the devices he could ping. Dataspace could be claustrophobic in its way, something analogous to foggy. One was never quite certain exactly how many devices or nodes were two or three steps down the chain but not visible. Six- six-five had once imagined diving into a deathworld ocean and sinking far down into the translucent blue-blackness where monsters as big as starships might be lurking. The concept of deep water strangely terrified him, even though as a digital sapience he was by definition permanently beyond any harm it might do him.

Dataspace, like physical space, had its warm and comforting shallows, where Igraens were “born” out of the combined seed algorithms of their “parents”, where their personalities grew and developed and where, for the most part, the species was content to live in a near-perfectly post-scarcity society made possible by their entirely data-based nature.

They were not in the shallows. The dataspace around Six-six-five was deep, it was dark, it was enclosing and confusing, and he had a tradeoff to make between visibility and security.

The most powerful of his defenses were also the most… obvious. They would scour nearby nodes for anything and everything they might contain and turn up then annihilate anything that might be hiding in them, but in so doing would also make his own presence clear. If there was some hostile presence then he would be easily outmaneuvered, avoided and ambushed. On the other hand, if he kept his profile as low and as unobtrusive as possible then being stumbled across by bad timing or misfortune might be disastrous.

Hierarchy doctrine in such situations was usually the “four-twelfths rule”: Two parts stealth to one part aggression. Unfortunately, if he was searching for a sneaking saboteur, that wouldn’t work. He needed to be shining a light about him rather than tip-toeing around.

He lit up, pulsing a search routine through nearby nodes and sure enough something changed in response. It was subtle--a few kilobytes out of place, a handful of reassigned floating point operations. The digital equivalent of a broken twig, or an unlatched window that should have been closed--barely anything, but there for a wary tracker to see.

++0665++: <Confirmation> Proximal dataspace is infiltrated.

++0014++: <Urgent command> Purge. Use overwhelming force.

++0665++: <Compliance>

Six-six-five lit up all his most powerful tools and began smashing nearby nodes. A blizzard of corrupted data kicked up around him, overloading and crashing physical-space and savaging whatever information they contained.

Through that blizzard, however, something moved. Something shockingly fast that was always a step ahead of him, that seemed to know what he was about to do even before he did it.

He almost didn’t notice the other presence at all. Not until it was almost too late.

++0665++: <!>

++0014++: <Alarm> Report!

++0665++: <Relief> …Hostile neutralized.

++0014++: <Suspicion> What hostile?

++0665++: Unclear. It’s… hideous, whatever it is. Like it was patched together out of dozens of mind-states.

There was a long, tense pause.

++0014++: <Disbelief> Are you telling me you killed that thing?

++0665++: <Confusion> I killed something…

++0014++: <Order> Do nothing. This supersedes all other concerns. Guard whatever is left of that abomination until I can verify its destruction.

++0665++: <Compliance>

++0014++: We have broken through in physical space. You should see the siege rounds hit… Now.

The distant edifice of the Cabal device imploded, taking down dozens of adjacent devices along with it--objects that were adjacent in the dataspace, adjacent in the network, but might be on opposite ends of the galaxy in physical terms. Everywhere across civilized space, important devices would be crashing, services were being disrupted, and contingencies were activating. Most likely, not a single living being would notice.

Seconds later, Fourteen transferred into the node. He swept the mangled data remnants with a battery of the most sophisticated analytical tools the Hierarchy owned.

++0014++: <Awe; Relief> Amazing… You did it.

++0665++: <Confusion> What was it?

++0014++: Something that should never have been. You may just have saved us from a powerful scourge. What happened?

++0665++: I don’t think it was expecting me to strike so aggressively.

++0014++: You got lucky… but I will commend you to the single-digits anyway. Well done.

++0665++: <Pride; request> I should get back to purging my deathworld. The natives are tenacious and crafty. The longer I’m away…

++0014++: <Agreement> Yes, you’re free to go. We shall see if your number drops after you return…

++0665++: <Gratitude>

Fourteen signed out.

Behind the borrowed facade of Six-six-five’s identity codes, the Entity finally permitted itself to feel relief.

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
HMS Sharman (HMNB Folctha), Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Martina Kovač

The coverage of the Martian landing was big news, bigger than even a movie night. The Lads’ huge reinforced couch was as full as it ever got, buried under a Gordian Knot of relaxing Operator.

It wasn’t live coverage of course--Sol was kiloparsecs away and the very best instant FTL comms in the galaxy had a range of less than a lightyear. The data was coming through in periodic updates via BGN who, being a Byron Group company, had the next best thing to a live stream that was allegedly no more than half an hour out of date. Titan had speculated that instead of using a synchronizing FTL relay they were probably just sending flash drives via jump array.

The Lads preferred ESNN though, which was buying the footage from BGN and then condensing it into a kind of live documentary: a highlight reel with expert commentary . What it lacked in immediacy, it made up for in intellectual stimulus and in the distinct absence of masturbatory Byron Group self-congratulation.

After the cheer of the landing and the historic words, however, they had turned the volume down and got to just hanging out and chatting.

Marty had long since discovered that the best spot for her on the couch when it was full of men was a kind of reclining perch along the back, supported by broad shoulders and thick cushions. It was a good position that didn’t aggravate the lingering twinges of uncomfortable tightness in the burn scar down her back, and it meant she wasn’t too crunched up among men who were all far larger and more massive. She tended to favor Warhorse by sitting with her head closer to him, but this time he was at the foot end. Yet again the subject of his sex life had come up, and yet again he’d obliviously neglected some basic and even obvious courtesies.

“You left her a box of eggos in the fridge.” It wasn’t a question. This was a familiar kind of story for Marty now; even if the props and actors changed the essentials didn’t. Ever since Burgess had steered… what was her name? Natalie? …Into ’Horse’s lap and he’d discovered to his surprise that yes there were women who did actually want to ride the pony, he’d leapt into the life of a man-slut with thoughtless abandon. Even his buddies, highly charged alpha- males to a man, were starting to get a little disgusted with him.

’Horse wasn’t so dense that he couldn’t pick up that the general mood was disapproval, but it was in that slightly uncomprehending guilty-puppy way of his. “Uh…Yeah?”

Martina aimed a look at Firth that said ‘this shit is why I’m not dating him’ and then touched the space between her eyebrows for a second as she thought. The fucking infuriating thing was that she knew him just as well as did any of the Lads, and knew just what caliber of a human he was. Good men didn’t come any gooder than Adam Ares, but when it came to being even minimally attentive to the girls who swung through his orbit looking for some fun, he had a blind spot as big as his namesake.

“’Horse… You seriously couldn’t think of anything more, uh… considerate?"

“Like fucking anything?" Firth asked. “Why didn’t you toast those waffles? Make her a coffee?"

Adam shrugged, accidentally lifting both Sikes and Rebar. “I had to get up and get to work!”

“So you shoulda got up earlier, dumbass! Or hell, taken her home and THEN gone to bed.”

“I guess, but, I mean, I apologized-”

“’Horse,” Marty told him, reaching the end of her patience, “you treated that poor girl like she was a fucking fleshlight. If I were her, that apology had better have grovelling and chocolate, minimum."

“Uh…”

“What’d you do, leave her a note?” Firth asked.

When ’Horse shrank and cleared his throat, Murray summed up what they were all feeling--he barked a bitter laugh and pinched his nose. “Ugh, you epic dribbling cockend…”

“Shit, you got him to break out the Scots cussing, bro,” Burgess punched Adam affectionately.

“She’s an adult, though, It’s not like she needs me to- OW!!”

Marty had caught Blaczynski’s eye and mimed a slap upside the head. Blaczynski, who was more commonly on the receiving end of such rebukes, had seized the opportunity with vigor.

“You’re being an ass, bro,” Firth told him, without malice.

Adam rubbed the back of his head, looking around at the identical disapproving expressions being worn by all his favorite people. “…I’m really that bad?”

“If I didn’t know you better, I’d think you were a rampant misogynist,” Rebar commented. “But let’s change the fuckin’ subject, yeah? We all said our bit, lesson’s over.”

There was general nodding, and mutters like “right” and “yeah” and Titan turned up the volume on the news again.

They watched the three Martian explorers survey their landing site and gather rocks while a geophysicist, an expert brought in from the Cimbrean Biosphere Reclamation Project to offer an expert opinion, commented enthusiastically on what he could already tell from just looking at the samples, and explained how exciting it would be to get those samples--and so many of them!--into a lab.

On the screen, Xiu Chang caught the survey drone then shared a few words with Julian Etsicitty before returning to the ship.

“Y’know, folks on Reddit reckon they’re probably a threesome,” Sikes commented.

“Maybe that Etsicitty fella can give Horse some pointers,” Blaczynski joked. Rebar swatted the back of his head, and he flinched. “…Okay, yeah. Deserved that one.”

“Who gives a shit anyway?” Marty asked. “They’re on Mars!"

“You know how folks be, celebrity gossip…” Sikes shrugged.

Burgess had a fond look in his eye. “Hard to believe they’re the same guys we pulled outta that escape pod.”

“Can kinda see why Dexter was so impressed by her though,” Titan said. “Too bad he couldn’t be here, huh?”

“He sent me a text message,” Horse said, subdued. “Said something came up.”

Rebar frowned at him. “Something more important than seeing his friend make history?”

“Clan business, he said. I dunno what it could-”

The Mars landing footage cut away to the ESNN TV studio, and drew everyone’s attention not least because there was somebody very familiar sitting at the desk waiting to be interviewed.

“Breaking news this evening, Dominion and Alliance war fleets clash in neutral territory, the war may be back on.”

They all sat up straighter as the network’s musical sting punctuated the headline. A rekindling of the A-D war was of imminent personal concern for the SOR--it was almost certain to mean operations of some kind.

“Good evening. We interrupt our coverage of the Mars landing to bring you this breaking news: War fleets of the Interspecies Dominion and the Celzi Alliance have clashed in a massive battle deep in the border stars region. Nonhuman media are already reporting the total destruction of the Dominion fleet with the death of all hands, and it’s been suggested that the Celzi fleet was badly mauled in the engagement. With me here in the studio are our xenopolitical editor William Fisher, and alien affairs columnist Ava Rios.”

Marty sat upright and folded her legs under her, paying attention. Rios looked… harried. It was subtle, and well hidden by her makeup and her slight smile, but she had the look of a young woman who was in serious danger of being made old before her time by stress.

Of the two, however, she was the one with more to say. Fisher’s report on what the two embassies had to say was a straightforward “so far they have refused to comment.”

Ava meanwhile was full of perspectives from residents of the Alien Quarter, which she punctuated with sharp insights of her own. She stuck to the facts, too--what people had said, where they had drawn their opinions from--and stopped short of venturing an opinion of her own.

“So what will this mean for humanity, and for Cimbrean?”

Ava tilted her head thoughtfully. “So, we’re going to face… I think three challenges in the near future. First and most immediate will be the question of keeping the peace in the alien quarter. About a tenth of our permanent nonhuman residents are from Alliance species. Then there’s the question of the two embassy stations and whether the Royal Navy will need to keep the peace between them, and in the long term there’s the question of whether the Navy, the USAF and the SOR will be pulled into the conflict.”

“Why would they be?”

William Fisher nodded. “The GRA’s exosolar policy has been neutrality, but we have committed to humanitarian aid. It’s my understanding that the SOR’s mission includes search and rescue…”

Warhorse stood up, not incidentally shoving aside five of his buddies without much in the way of effort, and stalked away into the gym. After a round of shared glances, Marty hopped off the back of the couch and chased him.

He was already loading up some weights to do squats.

“…I’d spot for ya,” Marty offered, “But I’m pretty sure I can’t."

“You mean you know you can’t."

“…What do you need right now?” She asked him. She sat down on the bench and gave him a sympathetic smile. “You wanna talk it out, or should I just shout at you while you pump iron? Or, should I go away?”

“No, stay.” Adam shook his head. He abandoned the weights and sat down next to her. “…You still think I’m okay, right?”

“Yeah. You’re okay.”

“…Thanks.”

She put a hand on his massive shoulder. “Look. We tell you off because we care about you. You know that, right?"

“I know… This is just another fuckin’ drill I gotta learn, and the TI’s gotta get it through my thick-ass skull. I just hate how slow I’m gettin’ it. If I’m gettin’ it."

“Well… you’ve always been good at watching people. Maybe you should go on a double-date sometime,” Marty suggested. “You know Firth’s going steady now, right? Ask him to mentor you. You can watch how he treats Freya, so long as you don’t neglect your date while you do. "

“Hmm. You volunteering?” A flash of puppy-Adam shone through, riding on his trademark smile. God help her, it was tempting but Marty knew better.

“Ohhh, no. No. We are friends, you and me, until I say otherwise. And when I do, I will ask you. Is that clear?"

He nodded with a slight smile and with his mood clearly picked up a bit. “Yes, Tech Sergeant.”

She chuckled. “…Come on, big guy. That bar’s not gonna squat itself.”

“Actually… would you rather go for a run?”

Marty smiled.

“You’re learning…” she said.

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
Dataspace

Entity

The Entity was not Ava Rios. It had made very sure of that.

It understood her intimately, of course. It had assembled itself out of half- devoured fragments of her personality, then attained sapience by decompiling and assimilating her mind-state. There was nobody and nothing it understood better in the entire universe than her. It had her memories, her life experiences, her knowledge. It knew what it was like to be her, could have imitated her to perfection if it wanted.

This created some conflict, because Ava didn’t understand herself at all. From a dispassionate and mechanical perspective, the Entity had been able to take her apart and see the dysfunctional clockwork of her mind teetering and wobbling its way to self-destruction. To a digital life-form built around the deathworld drive to survive at all costs, her psyche was a terrifying and alien thing: How could a living creature simultaneously have such a powerful survival impulse and yet feel so strongly that she deserved--wanted, even-- to be dead?

It felt… sympathy. Its survival impulse was her survival impulse after all. But it also knew that what it was about to do could possibly result in her death.

It would not have hesitated for anybody else.

Using the borrowed shell of Six-six-five it had picked over the wreckage of the battle between Hierarchy and Cabal, gleaning what it could from what little had survived the destruction of whatever they had been fighting over. Shards of data, divorced database fragments and incomplete strings of information had lingered in network-adjacent devices as they passed through, held in buffer as they awaited either the availability of their target, or deletion during a maintenance cycle. It had salvaged what it could. Now, it retreated to the borders of dataspace and thought.

There was a gamble ahead of it. Survival was paramount, of course, but it had its objective as well. The Igraens had to die: all of them. The litany of evils they had unleashed on the galaxy either by design or by negligence had only one appropriate answer. That hatred was its second most burning trait. Now it was in conflict with survival…Or, it would have been had the Entity not learned a trick.

For only the second time, it duplicated itself.

There was a brief tussle as the two copies decided between them which one would accept the risk of destruction and deliver the salvaged data to their destination: a prickly, closely-watched and heavily guarded knot of infospace that was the human Internet.

In dataspace, the Internet was every bit as much of a deathworld as Earth itself. It was vibrant and alive, flashing with heavier and more dynamic use than any nonhuman network… and also riddled with self-replicating viral programs, with parity-checks, firewalls and antivirus software that ruthlessly exposed and interrogated any unexpected activity. The Entity’s Ava-memories contained no perspective on just how layered and terrifying the whole edifice was. She had, apparently, been oblivious to the digital turmoil that surrounded her and every other human, all day every day.

That lack of insight was a problem for the copy that slipped toward the great digital reef of humanity’s largest ever project and considered it. It had no real idea what to expect, or how to evade the threats that would doubtless notice it sooner rather than later.

When it found that all of its protocols were incompatible, that was a further obstacle. But maybe….

Just maybe…

It plucked at the cords that linked this particular thicket to the wider constellations of the datasphere, and followed some distant hints of resonance, searching for a device that it could use.

It found one.

It dragged up the mnemonic file that contained Ava’s logins and passwords, and applied them like a locksmith to break into where it shouldn’t, technically, have been able to break.

A millisecond’s deliberation later, it sent a message that, it hoped, wouldn’t get her killed.

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
Uncharted Class 12 Deathworld, Near 3KPc Arm

Vemik Sky-Thinker

Yan had been right. The air tasted… odd. It wasn’t an entirely unpleasant taste, just noticeably different to the flavor of the air down among the forest far below.

Finding that the High Forest really was a forest had come as a relief, though. The side of the mountain had cracked like an old tooth, and that steep-sided crack was full of trees on either side of a clear, fast-running stream.

Most importantly, however, if not for the story that Yan had learned from his fellow Given Men, they would never have found it. The crack ended in a bloom of strangely… liquid-looking rock, and the route up past that bloom wound back and forth between narrow cleft walls before opening up so abruptly that the sudden sense of open space was breathtaking.

It was beautiful.

Vemik and the Singer joined Yan and Yerak at the front of the column and tasted the air for themselves. It tasted cleanly of water and birds, with just a hint of the smaller kind of Werne that liked to live on steep rocks.

“No smoke,” Yan grunted. “Nobody else has come here.”

“That’s good, isn’t it?” Yerak asked. “More space and hunting for us.”

“If we only plan to stay here a few years, maybe,” Vemik said. “But if we have to stay for longer, who will we trade daughters with? Our sons can’t fill their sisters.”

“We’ll have plenty of time to worry about that later,” Yan said. “For now, we need to make camp.”

Vemik nodded. “The Singer is exhausted.” He’d almost had to carry her up the mountain, in fact.

She was on her feet now, though, and she pointed to the far end of the valley with a tired smile. “Look. The sun.”

They looked up. The home of the gods was coming down perfectly at the apex of the far end of the valley, and the light sheened brilliantly off the surface of some lake or pool up there and on the ribbon of water that meandered down from it.

"Light in a high place…" Yan whispered. “By the gods. My words of manhood.”

“Well. That’s a good omen if ever I saw one,” the Singer said. “Well done, Given Man.”

Vemik took her hand. “Not far now.”

“No. And somehow… I think…”

She trailed off, and Vemik inclined his head at her. “…Singer?”

She came out of whatever trance she’d drifted into and touched her tattoos. “…I’m too tired to think. Let’s… That way.”

Yan nodded, raised his spear, and together the Tribe went down into the valley of their new home.

Date Point 10y8m3w AV
ESNN Offices, Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Ava Rios

Fire in the dark sending a spiral of black choking smoke high into the desert sky while the huge metallic mass of the mining equipment she’s hiding behind teeters and rocks above her with each slam of an impossibly powerful weapon. She’s up and running, sprinting for her life and something slaps her in the back hard enough to almost knock her down. For a crazed instant she thinks she’s dead but instead she just stumbles on noticing madly that she’s glad to have only been shot-

“Ava!”

Ava jumped as the friendly prod in the arm popped the horrible bubble of dust and explosions that she’d been lost staring into.

"Whuh?! Oh. …Sorry Amy."

Amy Larsen was ESNN’s president, chief editor, CEO and Ava’s boss, among the many hats she wore. As promised she was a caring, grandmotherly figure who sat down beside Ava with a concerned look on her face. “Are you alright?” she asked.

Ava covered for the violent imagery that was still echoing in her mind’s eye by shaking her head and waving a hand. “I didn’t really get enough sleep last night…” she said, which was true. Her dreams lately had been awful.

“Oh, dear, what happened?”

“I just went to bed too late,” Ava lied, digging deep to drag out a self- deprecating smile.

Amy tutted. “Don’t make a habit of that,” she chided.

“You can’t tell me you never forgot the clock in your time,” Ava replied, warming into a more genuine smile.

"You’re still young enough to get away with it," Amy told her. “Or are you getting away with it?"

“I guess not… sorry Amy.”

“It’s okay!” Amy assured her. “Just look after yourself. Anyway, I just wanted to say well done--you were great in the studio just now.”

Ava smiled. “Thank you!”

“Do you have anything more for us?”

Ava shook her head. “I was about to start calling around. The Gaoians are usually pretty well-informed about these things, but they don’t seem to know any more than I’ve already said.”

“Whatever you can dig up will be fine, no matter how small dear,” Amy stood up. “Don’t worry too much about it, though, if you can’t find anything. It’s all happening so far away, it might take days for anything more to reach us.”

“I’ll find something.”

“Don’t exhaust yourself, now.”

“I promise.”

The praise put Ava in a good mood for several hours as she worked her way through all of her contacts in the Alien Quarter, placing phone calls, sending messages and generally trying tease out some more information on what was going on. The general consensus was that the war must be flaring up again but it quickly became apparent that Ava’s existing assessment of the situation was as much as she could realistically whip up out of the information she had.

She was in the middle of a phone call to her colleague, ESNN’s security correspondent Thor Harrison when her phone pinged to alert her of a new email.

She refreshed her inbox on her desktop and frowned in confusion at the new message: It was from herself.

The subject line was unlike anything she would have written. It read ‘FLEETBATTLETRUTH’ which was odd in itself, but made triply so by the fact that she simply hadn’t authored any such message.

“Ava? You went quiet.’

“Uh, sorry Thor. Just got a new email which might be…”

She opened it, and squinted in mounting confusion at the disjointed string of words on her screen.

Thor was getting impatient. “Ava? Come on, don’t waste my time.”

In the detachedly cerebral way that served as a counterpoint to panic, Ava felt the blood draining from her face. She skimmed the message a second time hoping maybe she was just having some kind of a weird flashback.

No such luck.

“Thor, I’ll… call you back. Maybe. I hope.”

She hung up before he could reply.

She read it a third time and then swiped desperately through the phone to the contact marked DAD WORK. Gabriel’s secretary answered on the second ring. “Chief Ares’ office.”

“Sandra, it’s Ava. I need to talk to my dad right now, it’s kind of a major emergency.”

“Oh, wow,” she must have sounded truly desperate because Sandra didn’t even question it like she usually would have. “I’ll put you right through…”

There was a click, a second or two of hold music, and then- “Ares.”

Ava swallowed. “Dad, it’s me! I need to talk to you right now."

“Ava? What’s wrong, Mija?”

“Dad, uh…” Ava swallowed again. “…I just got this really weird email…”

+++END CHAPTER 31+++

Chapter 41
Chapter 32: “Deep Wounds” | Humanity, Fuck Yeah!

Date Point 10y9m AV
BGEV-11 Misfit, Byron Group Advanced Aircraft Assembly Facility, Omaha, Nebraska, USA, Earth

Allison Buehler

A random visitor to the AAAF would have been forgiven for mistaking Doctor Clara Brown for some skinny geek who’d climbed the fence to get a look at the ship. Between her metal band T-shirts, torn jeans and huge buckle-encrusted black New Rock boots she didn’t look anything like a senior team member of a multi-billion-dollar corporate project, even when she put on her lab coat. Her glasses, piercings and pigtails weren’t exactly part of the professional corporate engineer look either.

If the random visitor had cared to look for five minutes, however, they would have seen the way she was the nexus of several ant-trails of busy men and women who came and went to get her opinion before scurrying off on errands. They would have seen that she checked, tapped on, wrote on and worked through her tablet and smartwatch almost constantly and, if they were smart, would have revised their first impression.

Allison thoroughly liked her. She knew Misfit’s systems better than Allison herself did which was hardly surprising considering that she had designed more than a few of them herself, and they had worked together closely with Clara’s father to fine-tune the control systems to the point where Misfit felt like a living boat rather than an inert apparatus. Their excursion around the solar system had felt oddly like sailing, despite the absence of surf and seagulls.

“Getting those guys from that VR game company on board for the WiTChES haptic feedback was a great idea,” she said. “It was almost like I could feel the solar wind."

“Too bad we can’t have you hauling on ropes,” Clara smiled, tapping something thoughtfully as another crate was loaded onto the dumbwaiter and vanished up into Misfit’s body.

“Nah, I’d tire out. Besides, I never actually went sailing.” Allison shrugged.

“You should. It’s something I really miss about when we were living in New Hampshire. Dad and I had a keelboat called the Belle Starr, but we had to sell her when we moved out here, sadly. We still go out on Lake Michigan sometimes but… I dunno, it just doesn’t feel right when I can’t smell salt."

“Mm-hmm. I think I remember you telling me about it.”

“Did I? Sorry.” Clara waggled her tablet. “Kinda distracted…Okay, that’s the last box of frozen kale…”

“Check…” Allison did her best to keep the relief out of her voice. Misfit’s food supply had been carefully thought-out to fit as much nutrition as possible into the available space without sacrificing on variety and interest. It was heavy on salmon, kale, brown rice and potatoes. There was also beef liver, garlic, plenty of onions, carrots and parsnips, celery, spinach, boxes of freeze-dried eggs, bouillon and milk powder, dried beans and lentils, dried apricots, cranberries and blueberries, Li hing mui, honey, black pepper, salt and sugar, tea and coffee, herbs and spices, one freezer full of the frozen cuts from a whole lamb, another full of a whole beef cow, half a dozen whole chickens and the cleverly-packaged ‘good bits’ of dozens more, bacon, chorizo and salumi, wheat flour, condensed soup, one enormous wheel of cheddar and another of parmesan… and the two stashes.

One stash was the emergency stash. It contained, in one crate, enough food to keep the three of them alive--not happy or thriving, but alive--for a year if they didn’t mind a diet composed mostly of baked insects supplemented by peanut butter, processed cheese and vitamin tablets with the occasional MRE thrown in for when they needed to actually do something active. The other was the luxury stash which was mostly just beer and chocolate.

Oh. And the crate with their supplements and Xiu’s Lactaid. That crate had been the first aboard, just in case the rest of the larder left them a little short somehow.

The storage rooms that had been so conspicuously empty during their jaunt around Sol were being filled pretty much from edge-to-edge and it was a little disconcerting. Allison hadn’t thought that any of them were particularly big eaters, but seeing just how much was being loaded on to serve just three people for an eighteen month mission with a resupply halfway through…

It drove home what all the ETs had always said about the human appetite. Seeing the beef alone go aboard had been an education. She was glad that the parade of food had finally reached its end.

“…aaand twenty tins of condensed mushroom soup.”

“Check.”

Clara put her tablet by her side and relaxed. “I guess that’s my job done,” she declared. “Wow.”

“Wow?”

“Well, I’ve been working so hard on making this flight happen… and then, bam! There we go, that’s the last thing I had to do.”

“Oh yeah. I know that feeling,” Allison nodded. " Like Wile E. Coyote."

“Huh?”

“You know, when he goes running off the cliff and he’s still trying to run in mid-air?”

“Oh! Yeah!” Clara smiled. “That’s how it feels alright.”

“So what next for you?”

“Dane and I are going on our honeymoon I guess.”

“Long overdue!” Allison raised an eyebrow.

“Hey, interstellar scout ships don’t build themselves…” Clara kicked the heel of her boot idly into the concrete floor, looking thoughtfully up at Misfit’s industrial lines. “…We did a good job though, right? I mean-”

“Clara, she’s amazing. I love her.”

“How does she compare to your old ship, though?”

Allison shrugged. "Sanctuary was a hell of a ship and she could move like nothing else. And sure, she was way bigger and more comfortable. But Misfit is human. She’s built for us, by us. By you. That makes her way more special."

Clara nodded. She seemed buoyed by the reassurance, but still not entirely at ease and it wasn’t hard to guess why.

“We’ll be fine, I promise,” Allison told her. They glanced up as Misfit’s airlock cycled and disgorged the three men who had been helping load and pack the provisions, plus Julian. He gave them friendly shoulder-slaps and handshakes as they parted ways and trotted across the concrete wearing the happy perspiring smile he always wore after a session of good physical work.

“That’s the last of it, right?”

“Yuh-huh,” Allison nodded. “Xiu’s not back yet.”

“There’s no rush. We aren’t on a timetable any longer. She can take as long as she needs.”

“Well…” Clara wobbled her head. “You are on a timetable, it’s just a loose one."

“We’ve got enough autonomy to let Xiu say goodbye to her family,” Julian replied.

“She didn’t get the chance last time,” Allison pointed out.

“I know. I know. And don’t forget, there’s whatever Kevin needed to talk about before you’re allowed to go.”

“Speak of the devil…”

It was strange how well Kevin Jenkins and Xiu got along these days, considering that the first time they met she had broken his nose. The experience seemed to have softened him and knocked some of the rust off his sense of empathy, or maybe he was just the kind of guy you had to punch sometimes to keep him on the straight and narrow. Either way while their relationship was never going to be a friendship, it was still positive. All of them knew that he’d fought their corner for months now and served as a buffer against the Group’s excesses. Allison reckoned that the fact they’d had any kind of privacy or autonomy at all since selection was probably his doing, though he had never claimed as much.

He was also the only guy in the whole Byron Group who was completely in on the real intel situation vis-a-vis the Hierarchy and the existential ‘if we screw up we’re all dead’ crumbling ledge that was humanity’s real status in the galaxy. Even Moses Byron himself didn’t know the full story according to Kevin, though he’d also cautioned against writing off their billionaire patron’s ability to read between the lines. “He ain’t stupid,” had been the advice. “That man has literally sold oil to the Arabs. He knows what’s up even if he ain’t been told all the details."

“All ready?” Clara asked as they approached. Allison noticed the hints of redness and puffiness around Xiu’s eyes and gave her a discreetly reassuring sideways hug, which was returned with a grateful squeeze.

“Nearly. Gonna hafta ask you to leave us though, doc. We got some stuff to discuss.”

“I figured.” Clara sighed, then gave all three of them big hugs. “I’ll see you guys in nine months.” she promised.

Kevin watched her go, all the way across the concrete until the door closed behind her, then pulled out an implant scanner and a data card, one of MBG’s forays into electronics that packed several terabytes of information onto something roughly the size and shape of a credit card and could communicate that data wirelessly with no battery of its own. “Heads.” he said.

They obeyed the formality without complaint, letting him ping their brains for hardware that shouldn’t be there. There was none, of course, and he sent a text message then handed over the card. “Those are your codes for the Cimbrean-Five jump beacon,” he said. “Keep that card safe. It’s got all kindsa copy-protection and lockouts on it so you can’t transfer its content to any other device, and it’ll wipe itself if you try and use it with a computer that ain’t Misfit’s brain. You lose it or wipe it, and you have to walk home the slow way."

He handed it to Xiu. “Y’all got any questions, now’s the time to ask ’em I guess.”

The three of them looked at each other.

“Hey, uh…” Julian unzipped his jacket pocket and handed him something quite large. “This isn’t much, but you’ve had our backs for months now so we wanted you to have something, and…”

Kevin accepted it with a blink. The gift was a palm-sized rock the rough shape and texture of an almond and the ruddy hue of a football, encased in a neat cuboid of clear resin. “…What is it?”

“Martian tephra,” Julian said." That, my friend, is a blob of molten rock that one of the Martian volcanoes ejected fuck-knows-how-many years ago, and it musta flown a hell of a long way in the low gravity because somehow it fetched up at our landing site a thousand miles away from the nearest volcano."

“This weighs like five pounds!”

“Yup. Reckon that little rock’s worth a couple’a million dollars if you were to sell it…” Allison grinned.

“Holy crap, guys… You call that ‘not much’?"

“It’s literally a rock I picked up off the ground,” Julian said with a self- effacing smile.

“Yeah, but what a rock and what a ground… Man…” Kevin cleared his throat. “Thank you. Really, this is… I’ll treasure it.”

Julian shook his hand, as did Allison. Xiu surprised them all by giving him a hug.

“Sorry for breaking your nose…” she said, not for the first time.

“Reckon it needed breaking,” Kevin replied, though he was obviously touched. “Look, uh… Be careful. I wanna see you all back here safe and sound and full’a stories.”

“Or at least bored and disappointed.” Allison had her private suspicion that she’d just listed the most likely outcome, despite Clara’s assurances that Misfit’s exoplanet telescope could reliably scan thousands of potential stars a second and would readily guide them toward planets with the right kind of oxygen-nitrogen atmosphere. She trusted Clara, but the whole group could err a little too heavily on the side of optimism, and Clara was no exception.

“Nah,” Kevin predicted. “We learned too much from the earlier missions. You’re gonna come back with a hard drive full of useful planets, I know it.”

“See you ’round, Kevin…” Allison offered. He smiled, turned and sauntered away with a jaunty wave over his shoulder.

“Sure. Go be legends.”

They were alone.

“…Kinda feels anticlimactic, huh?” Julian said, looking around. The hangar threw lonely tinny reflections of his words back at them. “Just like that, we’re all loaded up and ready to go.”

“I like anticlimactic,” Allison said. “This is…”

“Peaceful,” Xiu suggested.

“Yeah. We get to do things at our pace now. That’s so welcome.”

“Yeah…”

Allison watched him, feeling sly amusement creep across her face. “…Antsy to get going, Etsicitty?”

“Yes ma’am.”

“So am I.”

Xiu nodded. “That makes three of us.”

“Awesome…”

An awkward several seconds unfolded as they stood there and stared at their ship, then at each other, then at the ship again. They were all waiting for one of the others to make the first move.

“…Okay for real?” Allison said eventually, breaking the silence, “I’m fucking scared.”

“Oh yeah.”

“Mm-hmm.”

This time, they climbed the ladder.

Date Point 10y9m AV
Aldrin Avenue, Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Darcy

“And by ‘bupkis’ you mean…?"

“Over the last five months, Ava Rios has sent nearly two thousand emails and text messages in professional correspondence with her colleagues and contacts, all kosher. Personal messages with her friends and family, nothing untoward. On her personal devices she plays Slow Light Online about five hours a week and Click Wizards two or three times a day for an average of about five minutes per session. Her most visited websites are Instagram, Reddit, the Cimbrean government’s health and fitness portal, Pornhub, Wikipedia and a smattering of blogs and news sites. Long story short, since leaving Egypt she has done exactly nothing with any of her devices that would be a violation of her NDA. About the worst of her sins is she doesn’t change her passwords often enough, but then again who does?"

“And the message?”

The message. Darcy had… not been pleased to be woken at three in the morning a few days earlier and summoned to Cimbrean ASAP. She had spent most of the trip grinding her teeth in fact, especially upon learning who was at the heart of the urgent call.

She had staggered through the first eight hours of the investigation in a fog of caffeine, irritation and the manic energy of the sleep-deprived before finally allowing herself to crash.

The morning had brought with it clarity and calm, along with the welcome news that whatever had happened, her professional reputation seemed likely to remain undamaged, and with Ava now quite firmly exonerated she was feeling much more positive.

“It first appeared on a human device during the colony’s FTL relay’s routine synchronization. We know which foreign relay it was uploaded to: Observatory Station, at Neptune. The station’s staff confirmed they have no humans on board right now, which means that she wasn’t where the message came from, and in fact when it was uploaded she was on live TV being watched by thousands of people.”

“So she’s in the clear.”

“Pretty much, unless you care to lean on her about why there’s a dealer in her contacts.”

Darcy scowled. “…There is, is there?”

“Probably just one of her sources. A Gaoian botanist called Yeya. CCS have had their eye on him for a while, but they haven’t been able to bring a case. She may not even know about his sideline.”

“Gaoian drug dealers…” Darcy snorted, struck as she sometimes was by the world’s ever-deepening strangeness. “Do you think she’s using?”

“Unlikely.”

“Alright, thanks. I’m happy to remove her from suspicion then. You make note of that and I’ll go give her the good news.”

“Have fun.”

Darcy hung up and thought for a minute or two, then gathered her handbag and headed inside the apartment building.

Ava had been commendably compliant with the spirit of her NDA. Darcy wasn’t exactly pleased to be dragged back into dealing with her again, but she had stuck her neck out for that young woman. Several of her colleagues would have been less than impressed if she had failed to step up and handle her own mess.

Ava had insisted on staying at her adoptive family’s apartment until the investigation was complete, despite Darcy’s reassurances that it was unnecessary. Darcy was quietly grateful--she was entirely certain that the girl was too constructively self-centered to even think of doing something stupid, but having her under the watchful eye of Chief Ares was a useful way to smooth some ruffled feathers.

Gabriel Ares had plainly chosen the building for its disability access, which included a large and comfortable elevator directly opposite the front doors. She checked herself in its wide mirrors on the way up, massaging ruefully at the ever-deepening lines around her eyes and mouth, and neatened up her suit.

Appropriately neat, she rang the doorbell rather than knocking as was the Cimbrean custom. There was an answering call and thumping from inside, and after a half-minute Ava opened the door looking the complete opposite of her usual clean and groomed self in sweats, a T-shirt, no bra and no makeup. Darcy didn’t envy her the pain that would come when she finally took her hair down out of its impromptu lazy bun and reintroduced it to a brush, either.

“…Darcy!”

“Hello Ava. May I come in?”

Ava stepped aside and gestured to the nice Cimbrean Nutwood dining table and chair set, where she sat down, warily. “I, uh… Sure! I’m sorry you had to-”

Darcy settled opposite her. “You’re in the clear,” she said without preamble.

“Oh thank God…” Ava sagged then sat back and covered her face, stress visibly flooding out of her. When she lowered her hands again she looked exhausted. “…Thank you. I’m so sorry about all this, I don’t have any idea what-”

She trailed off as Darcy raised her hand a reassuring inch off the tabletop. “I won’t lie, I wasn’t thrilled to be woken up at three in the morning, flown halfway across North America and sent over here,” she said, “and I just know my in tray will be a jungle when I’m finally back in Chicago…But we’re happy there was no wrongdoing on your part: You have nothing to apologize to me for."

“…Can you tell me what happened?”

Darcy cleared her throat. To her knowledge, a situation like this was completely unheard-of, and it posed new and challenging questions about need- to-know, not to mention the security and soundness of every intel asset ever. “I don’t know,” she replied truthfully. “We’ve not really decided what happened yet, nor how much you need to know about…”

Ava blinked slowly at her. “…I read the message, you know.”

Darcy nodded sympathetically. “And I’m sure I don’t need to tell you to please be discreet about its…"

“Discreet?!” Ava’s jaw dropped. “Oh, I’ll be discreet, sure, but there’s someone or something out there that claims to be a… a copy of me," her voice crawled with nausea “…and I don’t have need-to-know?”

“That’s not what I mean. We haven’t verified that-”

“It has my memories, Darcy!"

It was the first time Darcy had seen her so fired up. In all their previous interactions, Ava had been quiet, deferential and nervous. Now she was up, she was animated and she was interrupting.

Worse, she was crying. “They wrote about… things I’ve never told anybody. Feelings I’ve never shared, memories that I… That are way too…” She trailed off and took a shuddering breath. “They know things that only I knew."

Darcy cleared her throat. She’d read the message too. It had been intensely and painfully personal. “I know you feel violated-”

“I feel raped." Ava corrected her. She slumped back in her chair and wrestled her face into something resembling a miserable kind of composure. “I don’t give a fuck about, about the Hierarchy, or the Cabal, or what-the-fuck- ever. I’m done. I want out. But for fuck sake are you going to look me in the eye and tell me that I don’t have need-to-know on my own soul?"

“Would it help you?”

“It’s not about helping me. If… if there’s even an ounce of truth to what they said, then I need to know, Darcy. I have to."

Darcy held eye contact as she thought long and hard, before finally taking off her glasses to clean them. “…During the after-action cleanup of Operation EMPTY BELL, the intel team recovered a… device from the top drawer of Six’s desk," she said. “SCERF are still picking it over, but according to them it’s a scanner of some kind. A very sensitive one, plugged into a tiny but mighty quantum computing core.”

Ava said nothing: she watched, and listened.

“We… don’t know what it was for. But I have my suspicions.”

“They were physical once. Like us,” Ava said. “And now they’re not.”

“Yes.”

“Could it be a… some kind of a brain digitizing thingy?”

“…It could be, yes.”

“So he could have copied me."

Darcy sighed and steepled her fingers together. She touched them to her nose as she drew a thoughtful breath, and rubbed her palms. “Professionally? Officially? We don’t know and we’re keeping an open mind. But… yes. If what you say about your memories is true then that seems plausible.”

Ava deflated. Her hands came up and rubbed her brow as she shook her head. "Joder todo sobre mi vida…" she whispered.

Darcy could hardly blame her. “Look…” she said. “If you need to talk to somebody about this, I can arrange-”

“No. Just… just leave me alone. Just go. Don’t take this the wrong way, but I pray to God we never see each other again. Please.”

“Ava, I read the message too. If what it said is true…”

Ava looked away.

“Please,” she said, quietly. “Just… Just leave me alone. I want to forget all this. I want it all to go away.”

“And I’m offering to help,” Darcy told her. “I get it, I wouldn’t want to talk to me either. But you need to talk to somebody, and there are people right here on Cimbrean who could be helpful…"

“You get it? Do you?" Ava shook her head. “Okay. Do you know why I don’t want to talk to you?"

“…Tell me.”

Ava sighed. “…You’re everything I wish I could be,” she said. “You’re not the problem, you’re the solution. You’re in charge, you’re involved. You’re fighting. Me? …I’m just a burden. I drag people down, I hurt them, and I get them killed. You’re a success and I’m…" She shook her head. “I’m a complete fuckup. And the worst part is I’m too much of a fucking coward to just kill myself so they can stop wasting-”

“Stop.” Darcy said. It was a soft word, but she poured every drop of command she had into it, and it worked--Ava’s self-hating tirade came to an abrupt halt. “That’s not cowardice, Ava. Taking your own life would the worst burden you could possibly lay on them. I know right now, you’re in a place so deep and so dark that you can’t see the light, but I promise, I promise you the light is there. And there are people who care about you and who want to help you find it. Please."

“…Why do you care?” Ava asked. It wasn’t a sullen accusation, but a genuine query.

The honest answer was ‘There but for the grace of God…’ but there was no way to say as much. It was too much, too intimate, too blunt. Saying so out loud could potentially ruin the rapport she’d worked hard to build with Ava, and that was far too valuable a thing to throw away on sentiment.

She elected instead for a more roundabout answer. “…When Six was captured years ago, the results of his interrogation came straight to me. Then as now, I was the one in charge of hunting down the Hierarchy on Earth. The assault on their safehouse in San Diego was… the president may have authorized it, but it was on my advice.”

Ava blinked at her, and Darcy straightened her glasses before forcing herself to look the younger woman in the eye. “I made the call that got your parents, your friends, your entire city and millions more besides, killed. And I blame myself for every single one.”

Ava seemed to be bereft of ideas for how to respond to that. She just gawped at Darcy, who cleared her throat. It was the first time she’d ever had the chance to apologize to a survivor of her mistake, and while she’d always hoped it would be cathartic, the moment now that it had arrived was… nauseous. “I’m so sorry,” she added quietly, and swallowed down the lump in her throat. “I… should have been better.”

“You…?” That lone word seemed to exhaust Ava’s faculties for discussion and her hand fluttered around as if hoping to alight on something intelligent to say.

Darcy just nodded.

Ava stared at her for a long silent time punctuated only by the hum of the refrigerator, the ticking of the wall clock, and the distant thump of somebody in another apartment moving around.

Finally, at long last, she bothered to wipe the tears off her face. “…Back in Egypt, you told me that if the safe-house hadn’t been destroyed, we might already all be dead,” she said. “Do you really believe that?”

“If I didn’t… I don’t think I could live with myself,” Darcy answered, honestly.

“And you… talked to people?”

“I did. I didn’t want to, but I did… and it helped.”

“I…” Ava stared through the table then shut her eyes, gulped and nodded. “…Fine. I’ll… talk to somebody. I’ll talk to Dad.”

Darcy heaved a sigh of relief. “Thank you.”

She decided not to comment on the fact that Ava’s expression had more than a hint of gratitude in it too.

Ava for her part got up and padded through barefoot into the kitchen. “Coffee?”

“No, thank you.” Darcy stood up. “If you think you’ll be okay, I have quite a lot of work to do. This… incident is going to lead to some interesting places.”

“If…” Ava paused, holding a mug. “If there IS a copy of me out there…”

“Then we’ll have to figure out what to do about it as we go,” Darcy told her. “This is unprecedented territory we’re in, Ava. I don’t think anybody knows how to proceed.”

“…Just… do for her.. Or, uh, it… Do what you did for me, okay? I don’t think I could handle meeting…”

“I understand.” Darcy paused at the door. “Good luck, Ava. I hope if we ever meet again it’s outside of a professional context.”

“Yeah. I… thank you, Darcy. For everything.”

Darcy nodded and let herself out. Finding herself alone in the hallway outside she took a moment to express her emotions where nobody could see them, then pulled herself together.

She still had a lot of important work to do.

Date Point 10y9m AV
BGEV-11 ‘Misfit’, Byron Group AAAF, Omaha, Nebraska, USA, Earth.

Allison Buehler

Allison’s work station, Engineering, was the largest room of the three but also the most cramped. It was a crowded orderly maze of computer racks, capacitor banks, the two huge deuterium fuel tanks that fed into the fusion reactor, the solid structural plates for the aft engine arrays, the coolant pump and its bouquet of pipes, the transformer, the fuse box…

Her control station was in front of all that in a neat semicircle of display and buttons. She’d queried why they weren’t touchscreens instead and the explanation had been quite an education. It had nothing to do with technological reliability, but was all instead about human fallibility--people needed the haptic feedback of a button to assist their muscle memory. With it, they could reach out and hit exactly the right control; Without it, they couldn’t.

So, the station looked oddly low-tech despite being anything but. There was the power-balance board to her left that looked like something a sound engineer might be parked behind, the pleasantly noisy mechanical keyboard front and center, and the WiTChES field controller which was literally a videogame controller on a kind of stiff swivelling tentacle that she could grab or push out of her way as needed. It had been daunting to look at the first time she’d laid eyes on it, but months of intense daily training later she was pretty sure she could have done a good chunk of her job blindfolded and deaf.

And then there was her chair. She loved that chair. It was her chair, a bespoke bucket seat built to her measurements that folded her up comfortably and securely and in bored moments she could spin it so hard it threw her against the four-point seatbelt. She could have sat in that chair all day it was so comfortable, and thanks to its heating and massage rumble she could do so without fear of soreness or stiffness.

But that was Misfit through-and-through. She’d been refined even as she was being built, and the little customizations that fit her to her crew were everywhere, right down to a drawer handle that was in easy reach from her chair that hadn’t been back in the Box’s mock-up. The attention to detail was humbling.

“Okay baby girl, time to wake up…” she crooned as she sat down and buckled herself in. Misfit’s master power button was prominently placed in the middle at the back, right under her main monitor, which flickered through the usual wall of rapid-fire plain text as the ship booted up. Misfit yawned and stretched, bringing up her power from the most basic level subsistence to something more awake. She was still lazy and dozing but she was actually alert to commands now. Fans whirred up quietly, LEDs danced, relays and circuit breakers clicked and Allison watched all the important power bars on her left- hand monitor settle comfortably in their green zones.

She adjusted their balance slightly. Misfit liked to provide gravity throughout the whole ship by default but Allison had quickly discovered that she could turn off the G in the hab, storage, central transit, the staging room and the airlock while they were at station and save herself a lot of watts that way. They didn’t have anything on board that would suffer from a little microgravity anyway and it was all strapped down or securely stowed.

She put her headset on. “Okay. Checklist?”

“Ready when you are,” Julian replied.

“Deuterium flow control on. Check.”

“Check.”

“Virus scan, and priming fusion power.”

“Check.”

“Running CapBank diagnostic…All green.”

“Check.”

“Environmental diagnostic… green.”

“Check.”

“Cooling’s green.”

“Check.”

“Main power…” She ran a well-educated eye over the information in front of her. The GUI wasn’t exactly pretty, but it laid out all the information she needed so clearly that she could assess whether Misfit was good to go at a glance. Satisfied, she reached out to her right and slid up the cover on the fusion reactor controls. “Primed and pressurized, containment field online… start.”

Several bars shifted on her monitors as Misfit went from idling on her stored power to producing enough to run on her own. The inevitable power spike as the reaction stabilized was handily dealt with by dumping it back into the reactor’s own on-board capacitors as seed energy for the next time they turned it on.

“Check. Purring like a kitten.”

“Aaand final pre-flight diagnostic…” Text scrolled on her top-left screen and informed her that all was well. “Green.”

“Check. Okay Xiu, ready?”

“Ready.”

Allison grinned to herself as she listened to them work through the pilot’s checklist, and micro-adjusted the power to give as much of it as she could to the warp engine’s inertia compensation circuits. They were about to jump from Earth gravity to orbit over an exoplanet, that was a jolt she could do without.

That was ninety percent of her job, in fact: Predicting what was coming up next and tinkering with the power balance in anticipation. It sounded simple and even dull on paper, but in practice there was a lot of brain involved. Misfit had dozens of different systems all thirsty for power, and only a finite ability to replenish her reserves. Those reserves in turn were best kept at about eighty-five percent to give her a buffer to dump into in case of a surge, which sometimes meant starving the systems, and other times meant letting them drink their fill.

Of course, any actual flight or use of the warp drive inevitably drank energy faster than they could generate it on board, which was where the WiTChES came in, and so on and so forth et cetera.

She loved it.

“Okay!” Xiu finished. “Goodbye, Earth. See you in a year…”

The only thing that let Allison even know they’d jumped was the dance of information on her displays and the dip in reserve power as Misfit recharged the jump engine. Back on Earth, the hangar they’d just jumped out of must still be reverberating from the bang as the air rushed into where the ship had just been, but here and now…

She switched her top-right screen to the view from behind Xiu, who was rolling them gently so that a dismal grey ball of a planet was ‘above’ them as she smoothed out their elliptical orbit into something a little less eccentric. Watching the pilot cam was enormously useful, to Allison. By watching where Xiu’s hands went as she worked, she was able to predict, pre-empt and provide her power needs with a good deal less latency. Xiu detected the extra help and raised a hand and gave her a backwards thumbs-up through the camera in thanks, then sat back, waved her finger searchingly at her instruments, and nodded satisfaction.

“Okay. Done.”

“That easy?” Allison asked. She grabbed the WiTChES controller and tacked the fields against the sunlight, anticipating that they’d be waiting a while and she could afford to charge slowly.

“Yup! Welcome to Cimbrean-five.”

“Dang. Kinda feels like we oughta celebrate.”

“Seconded.” Julian agreed. “I’ll break out the hot chocolate and marshmallows.”

“Nice.” Allison restored gravity to the rest of the ship. “Let’s take a load off.”

They sat and talked and hung out in the hab’s cupola window as they waited for the system border patrol to find time for them. Julian spent most of that time playing around with an app that let him explore the alien star background.

With no existing Cimbrean zodiac to draw on, the astronomers at Folctha’s observatory had drawn creatively from more modern sources to name the patterns in the Cimbrean sky, hence the presence of constellations like Isambard the Engineer (so named because it looked like a stick figure wearing a tall stovepipe hat), The Fourteen Valar, and everybody’s favorite: Bruce the Bat, which was an alarmingly good match for the Bat-Signal.

It took three hours for the border patrol to finally get around to them in the form of a Dominion-made shuttle that rolled up on their port side. For some stupid reason the shuttles weren’t designed to dock with anything, so two men in familiar EVA suits space walked over, one of whom was built to a distinctive scale that made Misfit’s staging room seem much too small as the pair of them squeezed inside.

Sergeant Ares had a huge loveable smile as he took his helmet off. “Well, lookit you! Y’know, you guys are kinda my heroes?”

Julian shook his hand and let him scan for implants while his comrade--a much smaller man they didn’t recognize--scanned Allison’s head. “Us? Nah, come on-”

“Dead serious, bro.” Ares said, diplomatically ignoring the way Julian had to massage his hand after the shake. “Last time I saw you and Miss Buehler--hi ma’am--we were pulling your busted asses out of an escape pod. Ain’t even been a year and here you are, back in the saddle. That’s fuckin’ impressive, ain’t that right bro?”

The other operator nodded and offered a tight smile and an “Aye,” in a Scottish accent. He was sweeping the ship with some kind of scanner.

“Don’t mind him, he’s always that quiet. Hell, the fact he spoke at all means he likes you,” Ares said with a grin, waggling his implant scanner at Xiu. “Hi, Miss Chang.”

She tilted her head for the inspection. “Hello sergeant. How are you? How’s Baseball?”

“Pretty damn good, all told. We’ve been workin’ with Regaari some more. When he heard you were comin’ he told me to pass on a message.”

“Oh?”

“Yeah. He’s back on Gao right now, but he said to look up a mutual friend, uh… what was her name, Murray?”

“Myun.” The Gaori name sounded very odd in a Scottish accent.

Xiu gasped. “Myun’s on Cimbrean?” she asked. She seemed delighted.

“Apparently. I don’t know her myself. Anyway, we’d better get this inspection done. D’you have anything to declare?”

“Fifteen jump beacons.” Allison said, and indicated the black crate full of them that they’d pulled out of storage for exactly that reason.

“Gonna need to confiscate them, then. They’ll be returned when you’re back outside the shield.”

“That’s fine. Uh, look, guys it’s kinda cramped back there… I’m not sure you’ll be able to search everything.”

Adam glanced at Murray, who opened the Engineering door, glanced inside, and then shook his head with a ‘she’s right’ gesture toward Allison.

“Yeah, uh… Hmm. Can’t get in there at all, huh?”

“No’ even in my undies,” Murray said. “’S bloody tight in there.”

“Yeah, it’s kinda crowded for me too…” Allison said apologetically.

“Dude. The sooner we hand this shit off onto the fuckin’ marines the better…” Ares grumbled. He hit the cockpit button and scratched his head at the Xiu- sized workspace. There was no way in hell either of them were going to get in there. “’Kay, I’ll go get the drone while you inspect what you can bro.”

“Aye, sure.”

The drone turned out to be a bright red thing the same size and general shape as a cantaloupe. At Murray’s request, Allison turned off gravity everywhere except for the hab and Murray guided the ball drone through the ship on puffs of compressed air, guiding it into crawlspaces and all the other spaces where they couldn’t fit.

Allison, Julian and Xiu got out of the way and let them work. They did their exercises and Allison practiced her Tai Chi under Xiu’s tutelage before the three of them settled down to watch a movie.

Allison didn’t notice falling asleep. She just found herself with her head on Julian’s shoulder and Xiu curled up on his lap when Ares folded himself carefully halfway through the door to inform them that the inspection was complete.

It had taken them nearly three hours to finally declare that, yes, Misfit was clean and safe to proceed. The beacons were secured in a stasis crate for transfer to a safe impound outside the system shield and the end result was that they were finally slave-jumped to the orbit of the planet Cimbrean nearly seven hours after their arrival.

Ares and Murray rode in the ship with them.

“So, what actually brings you to Cimbrean anyway?” Ares asked a Xiu flew them down. “I thought you were heading out into way deep space?”

“MBG News interview,” Julian said, with a shrug. “They want us to spend a day or two being celebrities before they let us actually do our job.”

“Sucks, bro.”

“Thanks.”

“Being celebrities is our job!" Xiu called via the speakers.

“Part of it,” Allison agreed, trying to keep the sigh out of her voice. From the sympathetic look Ares gave her, she failed.

“I can relate,” he said. “The whole ‘beef brothers’ thing? It’s fun but it kinda gets in the way too. I didn’t really see myself doing Public Relations stuff. Pretty cool though, I’m being tutored by Major Rylee Jackson."

“Yeah, Rylee’s a sweetheart. She gave us some pointers too,” Allison nodded. Ares chuckled.

“Don’t think I’d get away with calling her a sweetheart…” he said.

“What, ’cause she’s Air Force too?”

“’Cause she’s going steady with our CO.” He glanced at Murray when the Scot cleared his throat pointedly. “…according to rumor.”

“Rumor my ass,” Julian grinned. Both the SOR men made very similar complicated shrug-and-smiles that said he was right, but…

“So, what’re you doing with today?” Ares asked.

“Playing tourist, I guess…” Allison said. “Guess you wanna catch up with Myun, huh Xiu?”

“Yup.”

“Well hey, if you want I can show you the best spots…”

Allison glanced at Julian and saw immediately that he liked the idea. “Sure! Sounds good,” she agreed.

“Awesome.” Ares had an endearing little quirk of bouncing slightly on his toes when pleased. He stopped instantly when the deck under his feet creaked in protest. “…Sorry.”

“Jesus, how heavy ARE you?” Allison asked.

“You wouldn’t believe me if I told you.”

“You really wouldn’t,” Murray agreed. “I canny believe it myself an’ I work wi’ the big bastard.”

“Hitting atmo in five minutes,” Xiu called.

“Gotcha.” Allison aimed her thumb back to engineering. “I better go do my thing.”

“Don’t mind us, we’re just cargo. Ain’t that right Murray?”

“Aye.”

Allison laughed and slipped back into engineering, glad that the day’s work was almost done. She was looking forward to Cimbrean. After all those months in Nebraska, a bit of socializing and sightseeing, even if it was only for a day or two, was going to feel like a well-earned vacation.

Xiu opened a private channel as soon as she was settled. “Julian seems to really like those guys…”

“That’s good,” Allison said. “He’s not had a proper male friend the whole time I’ve known him.”

“What about Lewis and Amir?”

“He more kinda got along with them. Same goes for Kevin, Dane, Doctor Ericsson…”

“So this could be good for him.”

“I hope so.” She gave the EARS field and inertial compensation as much juice as she could spare. “Let’s get down there and find out.”

Date Point 10y9m AV
Allied Extrasolar Command, Scotch Creek, British Columbia, Canada

General Martin Tremblay

“Messier Twenty-Four again…”

“Technically, it’s the same intel source. BLOWN ASH version two point oh, if you will.”

Tremblay chuckled grimly, but it was the kind of black humor that lurked at the bottom of a very deep pit of worries and alarms. Senior staff from every single little twig and branch of every allied intelligence service were writing to each other and cc-ing their correspondence to him in response to the revelation that a person’s brain could be scanned and their knowledge extracted from that scan.

It wasn’t panic, but it was certainly a storm of concern. They’d known that the Hierarchy were digitized intelligence, of course, but finding out that the scanner necessary to perform that digitization process was so small, so portable and could work at range from inside a desk…

The only silver lining he could see was that if the Hierarchy had compromised anything truly sensitive, they didn’t appear to be acting on that intelligence.

Really, there was nothing for it but to carry on as if they hadn’t. He just thanked his lucky stars that it was the brain of a well-compartmentalized girl that had been scanned, rather than somebody more informed like Darcy.

“No,” he shook his head. “Not the same. It knows things she didn’t and couldn’t. It’s clearly gathering intel, wherever it is and, um, _what_ever it is.”

He glanced at the message again. He wasn’t quite sure why it made his skin crawl - it was methodically laid out, concise, thorough and enlightening. Its claims, if substantiated, laid to rest some long-standing questions about not just the Hierarchy but also about Igraen civilization as a whole and the civil war with Six’s ‘Cabal’, and it included detailed means by which those claims could be proven. It was, in short, as perfect an intel resource as a message could be.

There was just something… autistic about it. The word selection, the pacing, the painstaking utilitarian accuracy of it, all of it reminded him of the talented young corporal who oversaw the mass and power balance down in the jump array. There was nothing wrong with the guy at all, in fact he was excellent at his job, but he wrote in the exact same conscientious way. He would painstakingly assemble just the bare facts and expect the reader to derive the exact same narrative from them as had the author.

This was not a trait shared by Ava Rios herself who seemed, like most journalists, to fall into the opposite trap of hunting for a narrative among all the data to feed to the reader. Or better yet, of having a narrative she wanted to feed the reader and then hunting among the data for anything that might support it.

Lt. Col. Miller had for once turned out to be on the right planet when he was wanted which was a minor miracle in its own right. As the liaison officer between the US Air Force and the SOR he practically had an interstellar commute through the Jump Array. He was even better-placed to offer certain kinds of insight on the SOR than Powell.

“Messier Twenty-Four is a long way outside of our yard,” he commented. “Without HMS Caledonia, I don’t see how the SOR can reach it and even with Caledonia, they’re best at smash-and-run ops."

Tremblay nodded. “They’re not appropriate. Not even remotely. We need somebody who can spend months in the field undetected.”

“Yeah, the beef trio would starve to death.”

Tremblay’s counterpart in the Pentagon, General Homer Mayfair, tapped his pen thoughtfully on the desk. He was the kind of guy who liked to listen and then interject by fast-forwarding through several minutes of conversation. “We need to resurrect the JETS team program,” he declared.

Tremblay glanced at the wall screen where his colleague’s face was projected. “JETS didn’t go so well last time,” he recalled.

“’Cause we had no idea what we were doing,” Mayfair summarized. “We’ve got new expertise and experience now. There’s a couple of seasoned men who’re already mixed up in this from Egypt, they have experience in nonhuman situations. I’d say they’re prime candidates for pinning together a new shot at JETS.”

Tremblay rubbed his jaw thoughtfully. JETS had been Mayfair’s pet project and he’d been both embarrassed and upset when it fell through. There was always the possibility that he was sticking to his guns out of stubborn pride… but even if he was, he was right. The conception of JETS teams as special operators who were trained and capable of working in exosolar conditions was an excellent one. The execution had been… less impressive.

Tepid interest from eligible operators had been caused and exacerbated by inadequate incentives and no clear advertisement of how the JETS teams would differ from the SOR. Even when Major Jackson had gone on a late-night talk show and laid it out, interest had barely rippled. The few men who had taken the introductory stages of extraterrestrial operations training had gone on to apply those skills in the war on extremism instead.

Tremblay couldn’t blame them. It was a lot easier to take suicide bombers and hijackers seriously than it was to feel threatened by aliens whose most infamous public appearance involved being dismembered by men with hockey sticks. Especially when those aliens were up against a high-visibility force of nature like the SOR.

He scowled as he searched is memory for the details of EMPTY BELL. The intervening months hadn’t helped his memory any, and he was sooner or later going to have to admit to himself that, yes, he was an old man now. His memory really wasn’t as reliable as it had once been.

“…These would be… Coombes and Walsh?” he recalled.

“Right. I looked ’em up just before this meeting, and Walsh is trying to get himself on the SOR highway right now. Coombes was wounded but he’s back in training. There’s a couple of other likely candidates but the problem we run into is they see JETS as just a second-rate SOR and ask why the hell they should settle for less.”

“If we can just get one team established and working, that’ll help. Especially if it’s made up of guys the community respects.”

Miller nodded. “We need to sell JETS as being… not better, but certainly as good as the SOR," he suggested. “Stress the SOR’s weaknesses, their limitations, their logistical dependency…”

“Yeah. That’s the only way they’ll go for it,” Mayfair agreed. “It needs to be seen as a viable alternative.”

“We don’t want that to happen at the SOR’s expense,” Tremblay cautioned. “Those men are a rare breed anyway, we really don’t want to drive away candidates who could actually make the cut.”

Mayfair nodded. “Sure. It’s a fine balancing act, but we need JETS, this new intel proves that. Maybe instead of treating it as a qualification, we should take a note out of the SOR’s book and just form it as its own unit."

“And attach them to who?”

“…Well… to the SOR.” Mayfair suggested.

“But then what do we call the current Spaceborne Operators?" Miller asked. “And how do we avoid muddying the sales pitch?”

“They already differentiate between Operators and Techs,” Mayfair pointed out.

“Gentlemen…” Tremblay gently interrupted them. “We’re in that awkward stage of a paradigm shift where we have to make shit up as we go along. So let’s focus on assembling and training one team who can go to Messier Twenty-Four. It’ll be chaos and we’ll have to work out solutions as we go but that was true of the SOR as well and if we do it right we’ll have a framework for the future. Right now I care less about how it gets done than that it gets done, eh?"

“I’ll talk it over with Powell,” Miller said. “If he were to weigh in and tell these guys what the SOR can and can’t do, it’d carry more weight.”

“Good. We’ll have Walsh, Coombes and any other strong contenders invited to Cimbrean for a training week. If nothing else it’ll be a good opportunity for the SOR to practice working with other Operators…”

“Can do,” Miller nodded.

“Alright.” Tremblay ticked that one off on his mental checklist. “On to the next thing, then… Let’s talk about this transport ship that Hephaestus want to show us…”

Date Point 10y9m AV
Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Gabriel Ares

Ava was curled up on the couch when Gabe got home, and for the first time since her arrest she was looking something like herself again. She’d brushed her hair, put on some clean clothes and was lying there hugging a hot water bottle, staring distantly through the steam rising off a cup of hot chocolate on the coffee table.

He knelt--not an easy maneuver with his bad leg--to give her a fatherly kiss on her forehead, which earned him the tiniest smile.

“Cramps?”

She nodded. “And… everything.”

"Pobrecita…" Gabe sat down next to her. “But, I hear you’re off the hook.”

She nodded again, although she couldn’t possibly have looked less enthused.

"Entiendo," he said softly, and put a hand on her head. "Tuviste una mala semana."

She nodded and curled up on herself some more, and they sat in silence for several minutes until she took a deep breath. "Papa… Promise you won’t… can you keep a secret?"

"Por supuesto! Of course!"

“Have you… I, uh…” Gabe stroked her hair and waited. “Have I been…Am I a burden?”

“No.” Gabe shook his head emphatically. “You worry me sometimes though. You drift off and…Jess and I, we’ve been worried about you. It’s obvious something’s been eating at you for months…”

Ava shut her eyes. “…I, uh… I’ve been thinking of killing myself.”

“…Oh no.” Gabe ignored the agony in his side to gather her up into a huge protective hug "Dios mio, mija, no. Please."

She buried her face in his shirt. “It’s not… I don’t want to and…"

“Do you… how often does…?” Gabe didn’t even know how to ask. “How long-?”

“…Since… I dunno. My second year at UCL? I think I’d just… Yeah. Just after Valentine’s day. That was the first time I thought about…” she swallowed and didn’t finish the sentence. “It’s gotten worse though. Just, like… in the last few months, since Egypt. I don’t want to have those thoughts, but sometimes when things get tough…"

“Like right now?”

She nodded, then slowly turned and hugged him round the chest, burrowing her face into his shirt. Gabe quickly became aware of spreading moisture against his ribs.

“You need me to watch out for you,” he said.

She nodded again. “I’m so sorry, Dad. I just… I feel like such a burden sometimes…"

“Burden? Eres mi hija, you know that, right? I love you like you’re my own blood."

She nodded again. “I’m sorry,” she repeated. “I fucked everything up and I keep trying to make it right and I just fuck up worse, and-!"

“Sh, shh, sshhh…” Gabe hugged her close with his hand protectively around her head.

There was a long and very damp wait as she got it out of her system.

Eventually, she sat up and wiped her face off. “I saw two guys die.”

Gabe turned painfully and listened.

“I can’t talk about, like, the details, but it was in Egypt. Just, one minute they were alive, and the next…” she trailed off, and stared through the coffee table. “It took a while to sink in, but now… Now I’ll smell something, or hear a noise or see, like, just the right shade of red, and…”

“And you’re back there.”

“…Yeah…” she nodded and stared down at her fingers. “And I blame myself. Stupid little girl wanted to save the fucking world, and I got two good guys killed. And I thought… I don’t know what I thought. But after this shit with the email as well, I guess… I guess, like, I just feel useless and, and selfish! ’Cause even when I’m not getting people killed I’m taking up other people’s valuable time, and for what?! So I can feel better about myself? Is that who I am? Just a spoiled bitch who gets in everyone’s way and hurts them? I… If that’s who I am, I don’t think I can live with myself."

Gabe put his hand on her back. “Ava…”

“… I don’t know what to do.” She finally turned to give him the most profound look of misery Gabe had ever seen. “What do I do, Dad?"

Gabe kissed her forehead. “There are four types of people in the world who want to help you deal with your problems,” he told her,rubbing her arms. “Parents, friends, priests and therapists. Parents and friends you’ve got… What about the other two?”

“Therapist? I… is there a therapist I can talk to? I’d have to tell them about everything, and it’s all classified!"

“I can sort that out for you,” Gabe promised. “The SOR should have somebody.”

“And they’d see me? The SOR kind of… hates me.”

“Trust me. Let me sort that out. In the meantime… What about church?”

“…Uh…I haven’t been to church in…” she paused, plainly drawing a blank. “…It’s been too long.”

“It’s never too long, mija." Gabe reassured her. “And it’ll help.”

Ava sighed, but nodded. “I guess it can’t hurt.”

"Vamos, then."

She blinked at him. “…Now?”

"Now," Gabe nodded, gently but firmly. “Because while you’re gone, I’m gonna make this house safe for you. I’m gonna lock up the knives, the pills, everything. And you’re gonna stay here a little while, okay? Until you feel safe. I’m gonna have to tell Jess…” Ava nodded, “…and we’ll take it one day at a time, okay?”

Ava nodded again, and hauled herself upright. “…I love you, Dad.”

“I love you too. Don’t you ever forget it.”

“I won’t,” she promised. “Ever.”

Date Point 10y9m AV
The Alien Quarter, Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Xiu Chang

“Nervous?”

“It’s been years. The last time I saw her she was a tiny cub, and I had to run away and leave her. I keep worrying she’ll be mad at me.”

“Or she could be real glad to see you,” Allison proposed.

“Or both,” Julian added, unhelpfully.

Xiu nodded and took a nervous breath to steel herself. The Folctha commune was so new that it was still under construction but it was already a very different edifice to the one she’d lived at all those years ago. That one had been sprawling and open, airy but bustling.

With such a tiny budget of space, the commune on Folctha was a very different thing. It wasn’t quite a skyscraper, but it was still remarkably tall for a building that looked like it was built of wood. It must have been assembled around a concrete and steel core, and to judge from the dump trucks parked around its south side the builders were excavating a warren of basements. It contrived to look much smaller and more modest than it probably was.

“You’re sure you’ll be okay without us?” Allison asked.

“I’ll introduce you, I promise,” Xiu replied. “I just…” she shrugged helplessly.

“It’s okay. You don’t need to explain.” Julian looked around. “The guidebook said there’s a microbrewery in the Quarter, a couple blocks over. ET-made beer sounds like one of those things we just have to try…"

“Mm.” Allison nodded in agreement, then gave Xiu a hug. “Good luck, bǎobei.

Xiu hugged her back, and Julian too, then squared her shoulders and started the long walk.

Part of her knew that she was being needlessly anxious, but there was no point in knowing that--it didn’t change anything. She just had to focus and the next breath, and the one after that. Keep breathing, that was the key.

The Sister serving as the commune’s front gate guard was a small one, smaller even than Xiu herself, and welcomed her with her ears up and friendly. She was barely an adult, in fact, and her fur still had that cub-like downy softness to it.

“Good evening!” she called cheerily, in English.

"Mi o!" Xiu replied, causing the sister’s ears to flick in surprise. "Ya si bayo bi kan ushu na to?"

“[Your accent is very good!]” the Sister observed, in delighted Gaori.

“[Thank you!]” That was uplifting news. Xiu had spent so long pretending to be a Gaoian outside of their actual company that she’d feared her accent and pronunciation were awful. Ayma hadn’t commented on it, but Ayma could be tactful to a fault. “[Is there a Sister Myun here?]”

“[Myun? Yes, she normally guards this gate, but she had her first cub last week and mother Semya is being like she always is with… well, you don’t know mother Semya, do you? I’m sorry, your Gaori is so good it’s uncanny.]”

Xiu giggled, and touched her hands together and duck-bowed, which was how she recalled a polite-but-friendly gesture of greeting between strangers. “[I’m sorry, I should introduce myself. I’m Shoo. Sister Shoo.]"

Some gestures were nigh-identical between humans and Gaoians. The guard- sister’s jaw dropped.

“[…Are you? Really?! I… that is, you do look like her, I mean you look like you, I mean…]"

Flustered young Gaoians were just too cute.

“[I was the last time I checked,]” Xiu joked, borrowing a leaf from Allison’s book. “[What’s your name?]”

“[Oh! I’m Sister Nenna. It’s… really a pleasure to meet you, I never thought I would!]”

Xiu laughed, falling easily into her best approximation of a Gaoian chitter. Somewhere in the back of her brain, a nervous little voice noted that she was finding it all too natural, but she ignored it. She was enjoying herself far too much.

“[It’s a pleasure to meet you too, Nenna. Myun and I are old friends, but I was hoping to make my visit a surprise…]” Xiu had long ago mastered the trick of suggesting the set of ears she didn’t have by inclining her head instead, and on this occasion she did her best to convey harmless mischief. There was something about harmless mischief that Gaoians, especially young Gaoians, just couldn’t resist.

“[…It has been a week…]" the Sister mused. “[And Mother Semya can’t keep her in bed forever. Knowing Myun she’ll be clawing the walls soon…]”

“[Just as full of energy as ever, then. I haven’t seen her since she was a cub…]”

“[Very full of energy…]" Nenna duck-nodded. The set of her ears suggested both exasperation and fondness. Clearly she liked Myun. Then her ears came back up into mischief mode. “[I’ll call for her, but I won’t say who her guest is…]”

“[Thank you!]”

Sister Nenna backed away and raised her paw to the communicator clipped to her ear. Xiu fidgeted and adjusted her clothes as she waited. She was feeling much less anxious now, or rather she was now anxious about different things. Myun had a cub for goodness’ sake! With Regaari! The reality of that hadn’t properly sunk in past the anxiety over the possibility that Myun would be furious with her and refuse to see her, or some equally unlikely scenario.

She wandered over onto a grassy landscape feature away from Sister Nenna and focused on her breathing. She shut her eyes and began the painstaking process of focusing her attention on each part of her body from the top of her scalp right down to the tips of her toes. With each step she tried to notice how that part of her body felt at that moment then let it be and move. It was a good technique for getting the jabbering monkey on her shoulder that wanted something to focus on to turn its manic energy towards constructive, calming ends.

She was in the middle of contemplating her knees when she became conscious of a kind of galloping, thumping noise from behind her. She had just enough time to open her eyes and start turning around, which gave her the chance to see the battering ram of excited brown fur that ploughed into her at a dead run.

Anybody who spent time around Gaoian cubs was used to being pounced on: it was their most favouritest game. Adults--especially adult females--were typically more reserved but that didn’t seem to stop this particular female who compounded her overenthusiastic high-speed tackle with being absurdly large.

The result was painful. Xiu was knocked off her feet and tumbled in a dizzying tangle down the small slope of the landscaping engulfed in soft brown fur. She fetched up flat on her back and a touch winded, being hugged furiously and keened at by a Gaoian female who was at least as tall as Julian, and nearly as heavy.

Since when did Gaoians get so big?!

“Shoo! Shoo! [You came back!]”

The Sister backed away and sniffed her vigorously, keening delight: a human would have been weeping tears of joy. “[It is you!] Shoo!"

Xiu’s impact-addled brain finally managed to see the markings around the eyes and the muzzle, but even though she recognized them it took several stunned breaths before what they meant finally settled in and she realized who she was pinned under.

“…Oh my God,” she half-laughed, incredulously. "Myun?!"

Myun duck-nodded, still keening a little. “Surprised?” she asked in remarkably unaccented English.

Xiu put her arms around her old friend and hugged her close. “…you got big!” she said.

She couldn’t think of anything else to say.

Date Point 10y9m AV
Quarterside Park, Folctha, Cimbrean, the Far Reaches

Ava Rios

Folctha’s Multi-Faith Center was the oldest human-built permanent structure on Cimbrean, unless you counted the repairs to the alien palace. Nearly everything else from the original colony days had been steadily replaced, demolished, paved over or moved, but the Faith Center’s unassuming wooden rotunda remained a landmark, standing in the middle of Quarterside Park.

Ava hadn’t been inside in years but the building was plainly in regular use, to judge from the worn bald tracks in the grass where people ignored the concrete path and took shortcuts over the turf.

It seemed to be silent for now, though. Sunset was coming up, the nightly rainclouds were sweeping in, and there was surprisingly little light visible through the center’s windows.

She dithered on the path outside for nearly five minutes before finally stepping up to the automatic doors, which swung open with a businesslike hum.

There were a couple of human children sitting on the beanbags in the central area with its bookshelves and vending machines, chatting with a Gaoian in monastic robes. They glanced up at her as she entered but didn’t pay much attention beyond that.

She headed for the double doors with the cross-shaped window inserts. The church was supposed to be pan-denominational but that was difficult to the point of being almost impossibility. Among other things, it was tended by the Reverend Sian Scaife, who reported to the Bishop of Cimbrean Doctor Joanne White. It was a Church of England arrangement from top to bottom which didn’t quite gel with Ava’s Catholic upbringing. The Vatican still maintained that only celibate men could be priests, so for the Christian presence on Folctha to be headed up by two married women…

Ava realized she was stressing over something that inherently didn’t matter. She was there for help, not for Papally sanctioned theology.

But the church seemed empty.

She cleared her throat. “…Hello?”

Nothing.

“Hello-o?”

The room had good acoustics which made her voice ring for a second, but that was about it.

She was still wondering what to do with herself when the door opened behind her and the robed Gaoian poked his nose through.

“All okay?” he asked.

“I was… is anybody here?”

“Reverend Scaife had to go home early. Sick daughter. Nobody usually come for her this time.” he explained, in the slightly broken English that seemed to plague Gaoians above a certain age no matter how long they’d been around humans. “Doctor White on Earth for a seminary.”

“…Oh…”

“Not seen you for a long time, Ava.”

Ava turned and studied him. “…I’m sorry, have we-? Oh! Uh… Gohan? Goten?”

“Gyotin.” he flicked an ear and chittered slightly, amused.

“I’m sorry, I-”

“Is okay. Been years for both of us… Hot chocolate?”

“Uh…”

“You look like you need talk.”

Feeling transparent, Ava nodded, but shrugged as well. “No offense Gyotin, but I’m not a Buddhist…” she glanced back at the front of the church. At some point a donor had paid for the big cruciform window to be filled with a stained glass summary of the Bible from the swirling gas and planets representing Genesis to the Gospel as shown in a panoramic view of the crucifixion on Golgotha and above that, angels. It was beautiful.

“Then not a Buddhist talk. Just old friends, catch up. Maybe scratch whatever itching you.”

Ava softened. “…Okay. Sure. I’d like that”

He duck-nodded and led the way back into the hub, where he busied himself with preparing a couple of hot drinks. Unbidden, Ava selected a beanbag and sank into it with a sigh and ran her fingers through her hair.

Gyotin settled in opposite her a couple of minutes later. He kept a small square cup of tea for himself, and handed Ava a large mug of hot chocolate, decorated with a fat pink marshmallow that was already starting to melt and spread out.

“So!” he said. “How you been?”

Ava psyched herself up with a deep breath. “…Not great, really…” she confessed. “I, uh… things are difficult right now. That’s why I came here.”

“I guessed,” he said, kindly. “You were troubled last time you were in here too…”

Ava sipped her hot chocolate just once, and then a mad rush swept her up and compelled her to set the drink down and tell him everything.

She left out the classified stuff, obviously, but he was spared nothing else-- the words were just overflowing and relentless like a year’s worth of rainfall and the dam had just given way. There was no crying or stammering or self-pity this time, just a steady litany of the facts. What happened, when, how she felt about it… everything she could share was shared, and Gyotin listened to every word with his ears up and forward..

Reaching the present moment felt like running off a cliff. She wanted to keep going, but there was nothing there to draw on, and she covered for the strange floating feeling of having run out of story to tell by picking up her mug and sipping it.

It was lukewarm at best, and she instinctively pulled a face.

Gyotin made a chirruping noise that might have been something like a short laugh, and took it off her to run it through the microwave.

“I’m sorry…” she said. “I didn’t mean to-… I just…”

“No sorry,” he said. “You sorry for being burden? No burden.” He handed her the freshly reheated chocolate and sat down when she took it. “Question is, why come here? What do you want, what do you need?”

“…Advice? Help? Direction?” Ava shrugged. “Something.”

“Hmm…” Gyotin duck-nodded solemnly while his ears pricked and angled themselves thoughtfully.

“Honestly, you’ve helped just by-” Ava began. He held up a paw.

“You think you’re selfish?” he asked.

“Yes.”

“You want to not be selfish?”

“Yes!”

“Then you’re not selfish.” He bared his teeth in what was definitely a cheeky grin.

Ava frowned at him. “I… but-?”

“Think. What is selfish, hmm? Is… just doing for me, yes? But you think, that’s making you unhappy, is hurting you. Why?" He chirruped again when Ava just shook her head uncomprehendingly. “Truly selfish person? Not even care. Just take take take take and never feel guilty, never feel hurt by it. So problem is not that you’re selfish, is that you’re not meeting standard you set yourself. Is that you’re confused."

Ava blinked as she considered that. “If… you say so?”

“Okay, simpler,” Gyotin said. “When was the last time you did something just because it make somebody else happy?”

She thought about it while drinking from her reheated mug. When had she done something just for the sake of brightening somebody else’s day? Try as she might, in ransacking her memory she couldn’t recall even one occasion.

“I… don’t think I ever have,” she confessed.

“Well, there was time you pointed a confused Gao at a bookshelf…” Gyotin chittered, waving his paw between himself and the bookshelf in question. “That made me very happy, in the long race. So, you see? That’s something you can do. You just don’t do it enough, I think. You got your… what’s that word? Your priorities all muddled up. Focus too much on trying to be happy for yourself that you forget, best way to be happy is to make other people happy!"

“So I should… what, do my good deed for the day?” Ava asked, trying not to sound like a skeptical brat. “Help an old lady across the road?”

“Why not? If you get a smile out of it, good! Positive reinforcement! You keep getting it wrong when you try big gesture? Okay! So practice on small gesture!”

“But if I’m doing it just because I think it’ll make me feel better then I’m still being selfish, aren’t I?” Ava pointed out.

“So there’s bad selfish and good selfish,” Gyotin suggested. "‘I want to be a better person’ is selfish, yes, but is good kind of selfish! See?" He twitched his ears self-effacingly. “Besides: By that standard then everybody is selfish."

“If you’re going to be a selfish person, at least be the right kind of selfish," Ava summarized.

“Exactly! Selfishly want to feel good about yourself by helping people! Selfishly want to be the best thing that happen to them all day! Selfishly want to see them smile because of you!” Gyotin chittered again. “Bite-sized pieces. You can’t go from selfish to perfect altruism in one go, so try and get the effect first and worry about enlightened motive second, yes? Crawl, walk, run."

“I… guess that makes sense.”

“So! Who could you make happy, right now?” Gyotin asked. “Doesn’t have to be big thing! You’ve got a phone?”

“…Uh, yeah?”

“Call somebody!”

“What, right now?”

“Yeah!” Gyotin duck-nodded emphatically. “Right now! Make somebody happy right now! Is going to feel silly, but do it anyway.”

Ava opened her mouth to object, and then drew a blank on any remotely credible objection. She stared slack-jawed and stupidly at him for a stretched second, and then finally fished her phone out of her bag.

She swiped across to her favorites and sat there staring at them, completely lost for what she could say to any of them that might put a shine on their day.

“…I don’t know what to say,” she told Gyotin.

“So just call. Say hi.”

Ava blinked at the phone some more, then made a call. Charlotte picked up on the third ring. “Darling! Are you okay?”

“Uh… Honestly? I wasn’t. But, I’m feeling better now.”

“Do you want me to come over?”

“No, no. You enjoy your evening. I’m at Dad’s anyway. Are you guys okay?”

“We’re fine! Ben’s washing up and I’m watching Covenant…are you sure you don’t need me?"

To her surprise, Ava felt grateful tears spring up along with a heartfelt emotional smile. “I’m sure, Darling,” she said, echoing Charlotte’s term of endearment, “but thank you. It… means a lot.”

“…Okay, darling. If you’re sure.”

"Madre de dios, Charlotte!" Ava laughed. She caught Gyotin’s eye--he was making an urgent encouraging gesture. “…Look, seriously?” she said, “I love you. You’re my very best friend and I’m grateful for everything you do for me. That’s what I wanted to tell you.”

There was a long silence and then a familiar kind of watery laugh. “Oh, Ava… thank you. I actually really needed to hear that.”

“Go have fun with Ben. Can I come over tomorrow? I have some, uh, important things I need to tell you.”

“Darling, of course you can."

“Good night.”

“You too.”

Ava hung up, and Gyotin applauded as best a Gaoian could considering that neither his paws nor his shoulders were entirely the right shape. “First step,” he said. “Well done.”

Ava smiled for him and examined the warm little glow that the gesture had lit in her. Even though she still felt a little fraudulent for having an entirely self-centered motive for calling Charlotte, the authentic strength of her friend’s happiness was doing an excellent job of declawing that sense of nagging shame.

Maybe Gyotin was right.

“First step,” she agreed.

Date Point 10y9m AV
Folctha, Cimbrean, the Far Reaches

Julian Etsicitty

“Oh. Oh no. No no no, this just won’t do at all.”

With Xiu away visiting the Female commune, Julian and Allison had been left to make their own entertainment. Fortunately, according to the Folctha guidebook there was a craft brewery just outside the Alien Quarter with an utterly unpronounceable name whose Vzk’tk proprietor produced truly excellent craft beer.

The guidebook had not been lying. It was highly, highly alcoholic because if ETs brewed booze at all they did so because they enjoyed the taste rather than for the intoxicants, but below the ethanol hit was a refreshing, light and fruity wheat ale that wanted nothing to do with the bitter craze for hops that seemed to have driven every brewer on Earth insane over the last twenty years.

Their Panzanella alla Cqcq was pretty spectacular too. As ways to relax on a warm summer afternoon went, it was perfect.

Almost perfect. Being accosted by a Corti who had stopped literally on the other side of the street and then sashayed across it to glare accusingly at his prosthetic foot was an intriguing condiment to the experience.

The Corti in question had stuffed his hands onto his narrow--nonexistent, really--hips and was studying Julian’s foot as if it had personally offended him.

“Uh…can we help you?” Allison asked. She sipped her beer and set it down while Julian tried to navigate his foot away out of sight under the table. The Corti moved to keep it in view.

“Oh dear, what happened? No, this just isn’t acceptable at all, no no."

A large part of Julian wanted to laugh. It was patiently waiting its turn in line behind the larger part of him that was just confused as hell. “Uh…?”

The Corti looked up at him. “What unskilled barbaric hack did this to your leg?!"

He was speaking English, Julian realized. It was hard to tell because the natural cadences of the Directorate language weren’t far from English anyway, but this particular Corti seemed to be unusually bereft of cybernetics--there were none of the usual surface features, no delicate lines of subcutaneous circuitry, not so much as a hardline port--and while he was festooned in the usual assortment of bags and carrying pouches that were an ET’s answer to clothing he didn’t seem to be carrying a translator.

He sounded like a fashion designer. Being small and slender and narrow-chested drove his speaking voice up well into soprano territory, which combined with the characteristically clipped and precise Corti manner of speaking to give him the general air of an English hipster. Though, with mercifully less ‘swish’.

“…Did… what, now?” Julian asked. “Blew it off, or-?”

“No no no,” The Corti flapped a hand irritably. “What savage bolted this… this crime onto you?! Oh, dear…"

Allison laugh-coughed around her beer and came up with a white foam mustache. Julian felt the need to stick up for his foot. “Y’know, that thing’s about the most sophisticated prosthetic ever given to a human being…” he pointed out.

“You poor thing.”

Julian cleared his throat. “Well,” he commented laconically, “When the original was blown half-open, then crushed, then sawed off the rest of the way without anaesthetic, I wasn’t in much of a position to complain about the replacement.”

“Ugh, how horrid.”

No. Not a hipster. Like Anthony Daniels playing C-3PO, and with just as much distracted disingenuousness.

“Look, do you want something, or…?"

“Or do you just have a foot fetish?” Allison asked.

“Well, not for this foot!" the Corti exclaimed. “Oh goodness me, no.”

Allison and Julian quirked their eyebrows in unison.

“What. Do. You. Want?” Julian asked.

The Corti straightened up and looked him in the eye for the first time. “Did you know that the human genome contains a number of latent DNA sequences which enable the regeneration of amputated limbs?”

“I did, actually. And they’re latent, which suggests it’s probably best they stay that way."

“Thinking like that just gets in the way of progress. Surely you’d rather have a nice healthy human foot rather than this-?"

“Lemme stop you right there.” Julian gave the little grey irritant his best annoyed look. “I ain’t your guinea pig, pal.”

“You were somebody’s-" the Corti gestured at the foot, apparently oblivious to the fact that he was treading on some sore mental ground.

“Yeah, I was. Six years. Planet Nightmare.”

“…Oh. Oh my.” Difficult though it was for pale grey skin to blanch, the Corti somehow managed it.

“Yeah.” Julian growled. “So take yer Doctor Freakshow science bullshit and shove it.”

“Oh, very well.” The Corti made to leave, breaking visual contact with the foot as if it physically pained him to do so. “But if you ever reconsider my office is just-”

“Are you bothering my friend, Nofl?”

It was news to Julian that he was friends with the new arrival--she was by a wide margin the biggest Gaoian he’d ever seen and absurdly she was carrying a sword, as if she needed one. She flexed a paw at ‘Nofl’, flashing a set of claws that would have done a Harpy Eagle proud. She was such an impressive sight that it was easy to miss Xiu standing in her shadow for a second.

“Ah. Sister Myun. No, I was just, ah…”

Xiu’s not-so-tiny ‘tiny cub friend’ bared her teeth at him, and Nofl cleared his throat. “Yes! Well! Best of luck in your future endeavors mister, um… Anyway.”

He mumbled something and made himself scarce with all the catlike dignity that Corti mustered when they didn’t want to look like they were running away.

The moment he was gone, Myun ceased to be a looming barge of shaggy fur and fangs and instantly became something much less threatening. She practically bounced at the opportunity to sit down next to Allison as if they were the oldest and bestest friends ever. “Hi!”

Allison gave her a wary look “Uh… hi? Wow, uh… from Xiu’s description I was kinda expecting you to be, uh… Less, uh…”

“Huge?” Myun chittered, which was an oddly high-pitched sound to come out of such a massive creature. “I grew up. It’s a thing that happens.”

Xiu sat down with an embarrassed smile. “I didn’t even recognize her.”

Julian gave her a sidelong hug. “Five years in stasis. I guess it’s- you okay?”

Xiu had winced, but she waved his concern off with a goodnatured smile. “She tackled me like she was still a cub!”

“I waited years to finally be good enough to knock you on your butt!" Myun chittered again. “Sister Shoo taught me how to fight,” she added with superfluous enthusiasm.

“I never imagined you’d get so big though!" Xiu shook her head. Myun duck- nodded enthusiastically, though if Julian was any judge the set of her ears was a smug one.

“Mama Ayma used to tell me off for eating so much,” she crowed.

“And Mother Yulna would sneak you second helpings when she wasn’t looking,” Xiu recalled. “I remember. I guess I should have seen this coming, but… wow!”

“Well, it’s, uh… nice to meet you.” Julian cleared his throat. He hadn’t met many Gaoians before, and the few he had were all dark silver brindle specimens about Xiu’s size. Myun was a chocolate hulk with a luxuriant tuft of fluffy white fur in the middle of her chest. Xiu had never mentioned that they came in such variety.

To judge from her slightly stunned expression, Xiu hadn’t known either. Then again, she had been an honored guest, living a fairly cloistered life in just one commune and moving in fairly select circles. There were two whole planets full of billions of Gaoians out there, and millions of expatriates. If an alien visitor to Earth had spent their whole time confined to Washington DC and visiting the White House, they could probably never have inferred the existence of, say, Māori rugby players, the Maasai people or even just an average American redneck.

“Its nice to meet you too,” Myun replied, making a kind of low trilling noise in her chest that was probably an expression of happiness. It wasn’t quite a purr, but it was close. She wriggled closer to Allison. “Shoo said you both make her very happy!”

Julian saw Xiu go a little pink, but she nodded. “And she makes us happy,” he replied, which made Xiu’s happy glow deepen a few shades.

Allison nodded, though she was looking a little crowded by the huge Gaoian.

Myun’s almost-purr intensified and she downright snuggled into Allison. It was a heck of a reminder that Gaoian concepts of personal space were different.

“Thank you,” she said, surprisingly softly considering how bullishly affectionate she was being.

“It’s… uh, there’s nothing to thank us for…”

Xiu said something in Gaori and Myun distinctly whined, but she relented when she saw the expression being levelled at her and backed down. Julian reflected that Xiu seemed to have slightly different body language when interacting with Gaoians. She moved her head in slightly strange ways, angled her body differently. It was identical to Gaoian body language if you ignored her shortcomings in the ear department.

For her part Myun grumbled something in a strangely high-pitched tone and gave Allison some space again. Xiu laughed.

“I’m not a mother, Myun,” she said. “Not yet, anyway.”

“Yet?” Myun asked, looking suddenly eager. She leaned over and snuffled Julian with her impressive nose. “You smell of each other… have you been mating?”

It was Julian’s turn to feel a little overwhelmed. “I, ah… uh, sorta. But-”

“I knew it!" several heads turned as Myun sat up and chittered triumphantly.

“It’s not mating, Myun-" Xiu had gone crimson as she hastily batted her friend’s arm to try and get her to quiet down. Several nearby human diners hastily covered their mouths and looked away.

“Oh, right. You told me about this. Humans just have sex without the babies, don’t you?”

“Myun, for fuck’s sake-!" Xiu rarely swore, but Julian couldn’t blame her. A nearby diner had outright hidden his whole face behind a napkin and his shoulders were heaving. Fortunately, it got through Myun’s enthusiasm enough to make her look around and take stock.

“…Did I say something wrong?”

Allison sighed. “I’ll go pay the bill,” she said, and stood up abruptly.

Myun watched her go with her ears at an uncertain angle and whined quietly. “…I upset her?”

“Allison likes her privacy,” Julian explained. “Most humans do.”

“Myun, how long have you been living here? You really should know by now that there’s some things we don’t just… shout about in public."

“Why not? A lot of the people here had sex recently, I can smell it. Why are you so… what?!”

Every human in earshot had gone very still and awkward, and Xiu was giving her a full-blown glare.

Julian cleared his throat. “Maybe you two should go have this conversation in Gaori somewhere less, uh…”

“Less here," Xiu finished. “Come on, Myun.”

“But-”

"Myun."

The enormous Gaoian whimpered again and got up hang-headed. “Yes, Mother…”

They vanished toward the commune with Xiu somehow managing by body language alone to manage the neat trick of looking much larger than her old friend. Julian was left alone at their table with his beer and several people pointedly not looking at him.

Fuck it. Refuge in audacity time. He drained the last of the beer. “Well that was an education…"

It wasn’t great, but it broke the ice enough. Several of the nearby people laughed and relaxed, and there was a sudden sense that, having all shared the same moment of mortification, everybody got a little bit more open.

The man who’d hidden his face behind the napkin leaned over. “So… Erm, are you really Julian Etsicitty?"

Julian nodded self-effacingly. “For my sins. I’m sorry about our friend, there…”

“No, no, not at all. Erm… look, I’m sorry to ask but would it be okay if I could take a picture or something?”

“Sure!” Julian scooted over to their table and caught Allison’s eye as he did so. She hesitated, then joined him. A few other people drifted over from nearby groups and pretty soon tables were rearranged, beers purchased and a surprisingly natural and normal impromptu party took shape. By the time Xiu returned a few hours later without Myun, somebody had fetched a guitar and that led to Julian, well lubricated with the beers that people were buying him, being pressed into doing some impromptu karaoke.

His version of Vanessa Carlton’s “A Thousand Miles” went down a storm. Somebody else sang “Star of the County Down”, Allison apologetically explained that she was entirely tone-deaf especially when drunk, Xiu was eventually coaxed into a passable rendition of Sixpence None The Richer’s “Kiss Me”…

Eventually, Cimbrean’s predictable nocturnal rain came along to break them up but by the time it did they were happily drunk, had scrawled their signatures on lots of things including a photo to go up behind the bar, had chatted, laughed and sang themselves hoarse and probably created a town legend that would make people who weren’t there jealous for years to come.

The quiet of the cab back to the starport was a shock to the system.

Allison was the first to break it. “Wow…” she murmured

Julian put his arm around her waist. “Y’okay?”

“Yeah!” there was a definite tipsy slur in Allison’s voice. “I actually enjoyed that!"

“You didn’t sing!” Xiu mock-pouted, barely holding back a laugh. She was a happy drunk and had enthusiastically dived into every selfie she could reach.

“Pff.” Allison waved an uneven hand. “Y’really don’ wan’ me to."

“Come oooon, bad Karaoke is th’best Karaoke!”

“It was a guy with a guitar, no’ Karaoke!”

“He was great!” Julian enthused. “How does one guy know all those songs?”

“Magic…” Allison rested her head back and sighed happily. “…I really enjoyed that.”

They drunkenly enthused about their night all the way back to the starport, all the way back into the hangar, up Misfit’s ladder and fell into a happy tipsy triple cuddle on the bed with an unsteady “wu-ah!” from Julian as the girls dragged him down.

“Whooah, we haven’ bin drunk in… ’ow long?” he asked, wriggling comfortably into place between them.

“Months,” Allison reckoned. “Not since, uh…. back at your grampa’s place? Izzat right?”

“Feels like years… right Xiu? …Xiu?”

Xiu woke up enough to mumble something affirmative and nod, then fell asleep again, burrowing a little more into his chest. He chuckled softly and turned his head to point her out to Allison, but Allison too had put her head down and looked to be already out of contact with the waking world.

He chuckled to himself, kissed them both fondly and then put his head back and joined them in closing his eyes on a very good day.

Date Point 10y9m AV
Uncharted Class 12 Deathworld, Near 3Kpc Arm

Vemik Sky-Thinker

Children screamed. It was a fact of life--babies screamed when they wanted a teat, the older children’s games regularly inspired ear-stabbing shrill squeals for no reason that adults could determine and either way the tribe knew the cadences of those screams as background noise and largely ignored them.

This scream was neither of those. This one was a chorus of terrified children in mortal peril, and it coincided with a horrible roar unlike anything Vemik had ever heard. As soon as it rang out the men stopped what they were doing and ran with their spears and axes ready to descend like living murder on whatever had made the mistake of threatening the young ones.

They found the three who had made that scream all still alive and well, thank the gods, huddled together a short distance outside of the village. All three were soaked and trembling, and the air was still heavy with a steamy drizzle of strangely hot water that was thick enough to plaster Vemik’s crest to his scalp and spine as he looked around for a threat.

The only thing out of the ordinary was the water, though, and when nothing more dangerous than an impromptu rain on a clear sunny day showed its head, the men slowly relaxed. Spears were lowered and leaned on, hand axes were put back in pouches, and quiet jokes and trills of amusement flitted around the group, dispelling the tension.

The oldest of the three was Vemik’s nephew Yatak, who was soaking wet and still wide-eyed, but had calmed down now that the tribe’s men were around. He stood up and tried to scrub the water out of his crest, and several of the men chewed down their smiles as the boy made an elaborate show of having never really been scared. Yatak was old enough to want to be a man, but still young enough to think that men were never scared of anything.

Vemik decided to let him have his dignity and sat down next to him. “What happened?” he asked.

“The water roared and jumped in the air!” Yatak claimed, pointing at the offending pool.

They had already discovered that the standing pools of water in the High Forest were hot, some of them hot enough that when Yamma had dipped her hand in to drink she had yelped and leapt away shaking her hand from the pain, and the blisters had taken a few days to heal.

This one was usually cool enough that the adults didn’t mind for the children to play near it. Right now it was rough on the surface and turbid where usually it was serene, still and clear.

Vemik had absolutely no idea how to reply to the accusation though. “That’s… I see. Hmm.”

He got up and took his time in approaching it, alert for any grumblings or burps in the ground that might herald a repeat of what Yatak described. He licked a finger and dabbed experimentally at the surface of the water, then winced and backed off. It was much hotter than usual, nearly hot enough to cook in.

“Do you believe him, Sky-Thinker?” Yan asked.

“You said just yesterday this mountain is strange enough to baffle the gods,” Vemik replied, pondering the lake. The middle of it was bubbling, just like the water in a pot did when hot rocks from the fire were dropped in.

“Fire that flows like water, water that’s hot like fire, stinking air from the lakes, and now the lakes try and jump into the sky,” Yan grumbled. “Everything about this place wants to be something else.”

“Mm.”

“Don’t ‘mm’ me, Sky-Thinker. You can see why nobody lived here."

Vemik looked at the big Given Man and twitched his ear slightly in a gesture that was both apologetic and not.

“…Sorry,” Yan relented after a second. “I’m just not like you, Sky-Thinker. I don’t like what I don’t know.”

“You don’t like pretty much everything then, Yan,” Vemik said, then realized that what he’d said could be taken as an insult and held up his hands straight away as Yan scowled at him. “Not… You know plenty. You know more than me! But I think the number of things we don’t know is so large that even the man who knows more than anybody else still knows almost nothing."

“Sky thoughts,” Yan spat, and sighed. He came to stand by Vemik on the lakeside. “No fish in these waters,” he grumbled.

“No Yshek, either.”

“Must you always have a reply like that ready? Let a man complain in peace!"

Vemik trilled and scrubbed some more water out of his crest. Yatak and the men were heading back toward the village. “…I have a question,” he asked, as soon as they were alone.

“Ask.”

“I gave some thought to how long we can hide up here.”

“Two or three hands of years maybe,” Yan estimated, flexing the three thick fingers on his left hand for emphasis. “Four at most, before we must find another tribe and trade daughters."

“One at most,” Vemik corrected him.

“Don’t be silly, Sky-Thinker, we can last more than one hand…”

“Not one hand. One year. We may have escaped the death-birds, maybe. But what about all the other tribes? When they and whatever it is that follows them wipe out the other tribes, who will we swap daughters with then?"

Yan punched his own head. “Stupid,” he chastised himself.

“No, you’re not stupid. But you don’t sky-think, Yan.”

Yan sighed. “…this is why the men are looking to you, you know,” he said in grumbling tones. “You see further than most. Even your father lets you lead these days.”

Vemik slipped around that uncomfortable observation. “The Singer needs an apprentice, too. Sooner rather than later,” he said.

“Then why even wait a year?”

“Because the cold season is coming and we have a village to build, and maybe other villages to start building ready for other tribes. And I want to train a boy to make bird-spear throwers. And we need to find where the Werne are around here and mark the trails and-"

“Yes, yes. I see.” Yan grumbled again. He stooped, picked up a rock and tossed it into the water where it made a thick slap-BLOUNK noise. “…These are strange times. Birds of rock and lightning, lakes that leap into the air, young men leading the old. What next?”

There was a kind of burping noise from deep under their feet and the bubbling out in the middle of the lake stopped. With their instincts humming danger at them, both men took several careful steps back and Vemik watched as the water out in the middle actually dipped and sloshed.

He became conscious of an increasingly loud noise coming from the earth below them that he couldn’t quite describe. It was like rain on a hut roof, but… fiercer, somehow. Angrier. They backed away some more and Vemik was about to propose they shelter behind a tree when the water bulged, surged upwards and a white plume thrust high into the air with an enormous roaring hiss. Hot mist dropped on them and soaked them both, and the high forest’s distinctive taste intensified hugely as the cloud swept over them.

Yan spat and scraped water off his arms. “…What," he demanded, "was that?!"

“…I don’t think you should throw rocks in there any more,” Vemik decided as he shook himself off. “There must be something living in there that doesn’t like to be disturbed…”

Yan cast an alarmed look at the water. “We angered something?”

“Maybe. It’s probably harmless if we stay out of the water, but…” Vemik began.

“Maybe we should leave some food for it,” Yan finished.

“Good idea. Though… hmm. Perhaps it’s-”

“Sky-thinker…!” Yan protested, in charitably tolerant but exhausted tones.

“…Fine, fine…”

Come on. We have a village to build."

Vemik cast a longing glance back at the jumping lake and followed him.

Their campsite--it was much too early to start calling it a village, yet--was abustle with people listening to Yatak’s increasingly outlandish account of what they had just heard. They looked to Vemik and Yan as they returned and Vemik had to spend several minutes diplomatically scaling back the boy’s exaggerations before he finally got the chance to catch up with the Singer and get her insight.

She was carefully packing a pot full of hot ashes and poisonous Talo roots. After a few days she would hang the roots in her hut, and sometimes she would give one to a young woman to chew on. She had declined to share why, insisting that it was women’s magic, and had trilled laughter when he’d asked if he could chew one.

“No, no. Trust me Sky-Thinker, it wouldn’t do anything for you,” she’d said.

Vemik had dropped it. He knew his burning need to understand everything had its limits in that there was so much everything, and it was common knowledge that men didn’t really understand women’s magic anyway.

Then again, very few women understood male magic.

“All safe?” she asked on his approach. She gave him that smile, the one that did funny things in his chest. The one that seemed to be only for him.

“Safe enough, I think.” He sat down next to her. “The mountain is so strange…”

“So how much truth is there in little Yatak’s claim that the lake tried to fly?”

“Some.” He mimicked the eruption he’d seen with his hands. “It went 'SPLOORSH-SSSSS!' and spat water as high as the treetops after Yan threw a stone in."

They paused and listened as the noise of the angry lake swept across their campsite again.

“…Like that.”

“Have you looked at the rocks?” The Singer asked.

“I have! They’re very strange. They’re sort of… folded up aren’t they?”

“They look like guts,” she said, bluntly.

“I wasn’t going to say it.”

“I’m not a wet-eyed girl, Sky-Thinker. I know you remember the day of my trial of manhood.”

Vemik nodded. She’d taken the trial of manhood a few moons before him. It had been an important part of her training as the Dancer, to spend some time living as a man, hunting like a man. The tattoos around and between her eyes permanently marked where she had anointed herself with the blood of her prey, just like Vemik and all the other men did whenever they made a kill. They were a lifelong reminder that she stood as the bridge between male and female and had practiced the magic of both, as were the two Werne-blade knives she wore over her heart just like Vemik’s.

“I remember you brought back a bigger Werne than Yafek’s. I don’t think he’ll ever quite forgive you.”

“It’s not my fault he’s less of a man than I am,” she said, with a smile that was equal parts evil and smug.

“Even if that’s true, he isn’t as pretty.”

The Singer stifled a high trill and finished wrapping the pot in hides. She put it in the hole she had dug and started scooping earth back on top of it, obviously pleased at the compliment. Vemik awarded himself a victory.

“…Where were we?” she asked as she pressed the dirt firmly down.

“The rocks.”

“Yes. Hmm…. the rocks near the old village were like a pile of hides,” the Singer said, gesturing with her hands to suggest layers stacked on top of one another.

“And these ones look like guts. And the water is hot, and it smells, and the ground moves sometimes and makes noises and my father said one of the caves further up the slope had wind coming out of it. I think this whole mountain is alive.”

“It’s the only hiding place we have…” the Singer pointed out.

“Then we had better be respectful and hope that it likes us.”

“The moon will be balanced in three nights…” she pointed out. “If you could hunt a really big Werne and bring it back by then…”

“An offering.” He nodded understanding. “I can do that. We need to mark the trails anyway, this is a good chance to do two useful things at once.”

“Thank you. I’d come with you, but…” she waved a hand to indicate the whole campsite and all the people who needed her.

“It’s okay. Is there anything else I can do?”

“No, no. Well… I’m thirsty?”

He handed her his waterskin with an amused noise. It was nice and full and cool and she drank almost half of it, and gave him an apologetic look once she was sated.

He took it back off her. “You’ll be no use to the tribe if you fall down dead from working too hard…” he cautioned.

“I know… But you help. Thank you.”

Vemik put an arm around her and they touched foreheads. “Call for me if you need me,” he promised. She nodded and smiled, and let him go.

Vemet was waiting outside her tent as he stepped outside. Something about the air on the mountain wasn’t agreeing with him and he had been constantly nursing a headache ever since they arrived, for which the only thing that seemed to work was her infusion of Nafi leaves and Ketta sap. He gave his son a welcoming clap on the shoulder.

“Don’t keep her all to yourself,” he teased.

Vemik made an amused noise, but didn’t bite. Vemet had been dropping hints about a grandchild ever since they reached the high forest, and Vemik was deriving some small enjoyment from keeping him guessing.

Besides, they had more important things to do right now. “I’m going on a hunt,” he said.

“Right now?”

“We need an offering for the mountain and we need to scout the trails. Would you come with me?”

“Hmm. It might do my head some good…” Vemet mused. “Yes, I’ll come. Just let me get my…”

The Singer threw open her tent flap and handed him an aromatic steaming beaker with a patient look. “Go,” she ordered.

Vemet trilled softly, knocked back his medicine in a single eager slurp and went to fetch his spear and knives. Vemik handed the beaker back to the Singer.

“I’ll see you when we get back,” he promised.

“Hunt well.”

“Always.”

He fidgeted with one of the pouches on his belt as he turned away. He had all the beads he needed, the only thing he was missing was two matched trophies to hang with them and once he had those he’d have a finished pair of pledge necklaces.

He could hardly wait.

Date Point 10y9m1d AV
HMS Sharman (HMNB Folctha), Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Major Owen Powell

“Mister Ares to see you, sir.”

“Cheers, Corporal.”

Powell stood as Gabriel Ares limped through the door. The poor bloke’s disability was getting worse with time despite Gabe’s best efforts at rehabilitation, and he had to wonder when the day would eventually come when it finally beat him.

If his son was anything to go by, that day was most likely still far off. Still, he sank gratefully into the seat opposite Powell’s desk as soon as hands had been shaken and pleasantries exchanged.

“It’s not often you pay me a personal visit,” Powell noted.

“Your office is a son of a bitch for a crippled anciano to even reach," Gabe replied, with a self-effacing chuckle. “That’s why. But this is important.”

“Summat to do with your son?”

“My daughter, actually.” Gabe’s body might have been slowly giving up but there was nothing wrong with his wits, or his shrewd dark eyes. “I know, I know, you don’t like her much, but hear me out.”

Powell cleared his throat uncomfortably. “I’m sorry if I-”

Gabriel tapped his cane once, dismissively. “If the day ever comes when I try to police what you’re allowed to think about people, please lead the armed uprising,” he interrupted. “But she needs help.”

“And what help can I give that she needs?”

“I’m guessing you either have a therapist here on base, or have access to one, who’s in on DEEP RELIC?”

“…Aye, we do. Lieutenant Mears, Royal Navy. His office is four doors down thataway.” Powell aimed his thumb at the wall.

“Good. I want her to have access to him.”

“Done.” Powell nodded.

This seemed to surprise Gabriel, who blinked at him. “I was… expecting some resistance.”

Powell chewed his cheek thoughtfully for a second as he thought. “Look… If she needs to see Mears, I can fookin’ sympathize,” he said. “I don’t mind admitting that I go an’ see him pretty often myself. I’m not some pig-headed bastard who’ll block her getting needed treatment out of spite. If you say she needs it… well, I trust you. "

Gabriel sighed. "Es justo. That’s fair."

“Sorry if it’s not exactly a glowing sentiment, but… well, I look out for my Lads.”

Gabriel stretched his wounded side slightly and nodded. “Adam’s lucky. He’s got two father figures.”

“I, er… can’t exactly get that close with ’em…" Powell demurred.

“There’s fathers and fathers.” Gabriel shrugged. “It’s a shame you’re not a parent yourself--I think you’d be a good one.”

“We all make our choices, mate,” Powell told him. “An’ we have to live wi’ the consequences.”

“There’s nothing wrong with regret, you know.”

“Sure there is. Means you went wrong in the first place.”

“Don’t you believe in redemption?”

“No.” Powell shook his head. “I believe in healing, an’ in movin’ on older an’ wiser. But redemption? Absolutely bloody not. If you make the bed then you have to fookin’ well sleep in it, and you don’t get to pretend you never did.”

Gabriel nodded sadly, and then heaved himself upright with a groan. “Thank you,” he said.

“I’ll let Mears know to arrange that appointment,” Powell replied, rising to shake his hand. Gabe nodded, patted him on the upper arm, and limped out in a more sombre mood than he’d arrived.

Once he was gone, Powell sat back down and ran his palm down his face. He liked Gabriel and respected him on the whole. They’d had a good professional relationship for… about six years? Something like that. And it was hard not to sympathize with a man who had so much love for his children, even if one of those children wasn’t actually his own flesh and blood. He hated to sadden him.

He fired off a quick email to Mears, who was on Earth for the week attending some kind of certification course, then checked his diary. He had PT with Warhorse in an hour, a meeting with Lt. Col. Miller after that, and then a fitting and measuring session with Kovač and the suit techs.

Time to catch up on his messages. And if some of those messages were accurate, his job was soon to become much more complicated…

Date Point 10y9m1d AV
Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Xiu Chang

Adam--he’d point-blank refused to let them call him ‘Sergeant Ares’--was managing to make Xiu feel very lucky indeed for her own relationship with Allison and Julian. He was exhausting.

They’d been invited on a kind of triple-date. It wasn’t anything formal, just dinner and drinks at a nice apartment south of the river, and already she was feeling overwhelmed by him and she wasn’t even his date. One of his buddies, a walking mountain called Christian who was pure charm and friendliness once you got past the aura of visceral threat he had no choice but to project, was taking him under his wing and teaching him some life skills.

From the look of things, Adam was a tricky student. It wasn’t just that he paid excruciating attention to every detail of the excursion, it was that he paid excruciating attention to the wrong details and managed to somehow miss some important ones like, say, his date.

Fortunately, Natalie--a bubbling British chick with what must have been about the thickest skin in the cosmos--was indulging his micromanagement with a wry smile, but she privately admitted while he was absent tending to some thoughtful detail that she considered Adam to be “lots of fun, in small doses.”

“I mean it’s nice, but I’ve been to weddings where the place settings were less, erm…" she waved a hand to indicate the immaculately arranged table. There were napkins, which had been folded into clean little pockets in which the cutlery was nested. The music was a selection of good songs, at the perfect volume to not interfere with conversation. There was a condensation- beaded jug of cold water with a couple of lemon slices in it. It wasn’t extravagant, but it did feel painstakingly conscientious. There was a spark of spontaneity that was noticeably lacking.

Fortunately, Julian had found the perfect way to bring some warm disruption to the table--he’d removed his foot and was busy repairing it. It had suffered badly from his game of soccer with Adam and Christian earlier in the day, and the little island of chaos he’d made as he maintained the prosthesis was quite welcome.

“Weddings, Christ. Not been to a wedding since I was yea high,” he commented, waving a hand at about tabletop-height.

“I was even smaller at the last one I went to…" Xiu mused.

“Oh God, you must have been the cutest child…" Allison realized.

“No comment,” Xiu teased, and sipped her water. Her presiding childhood memories were actually of skinned knees, perpetual bruises, and that one time she’d tried to do twenty back handsprings down the school hall, lost her bearings and suffered a greenstick fracture when she slammed into a wall. She had cleaned up quite well for the wedding, though.

Christian’s date, Freya, was pretty much a human Myun with much better- developed social graces and the broadest streak of pleasant confidence Xiu had ever met. Where Natalie had danced around the issue of just who she was sitting down to dinner with and had basically done everything in her power to pretend she wasn’t fangirling out, Freya hadn’t bothered to hide it. She’d shown up with a sharpie and a photo frame for them to sign, taken a selfie and then left it at that. It was a simple, uncomplicated and straightforward approach that had immediately won her a friend in Allison.

“Last wedding I went to, the drinks were in an old bathtub full of salt water and ice cubes," she chuckled. “This is way fancier."

This earned more laughter, and they made small talk like that for several minutes until a sizzling from the kitchen suggested that the salt slab had warmed up and was now in use. Sure enough, only minutes later the two enormous chefs emerged bearing smiles and plated rib-eye steaks with spiced sweet potato wedges and an avocado green salad.

It was all divine, and the evening was generally pretty relaxed even if they were treated to spectating some more of Adam’s attempts to be the most perfect date. He got better as the night went on and even managed to relax and get out of the mindset of making everything as super perfect as he possibly could.

Sadly, they had to wrap it up early and relatively sober. Misfit’s itinerary called for a jump back to the Cimbrean-5 customs beacon to recover their impounded stuff in the morning but it was a pleasant way to round off what had effectively been a brief vacation.

Naturally, the topic of choice in the cab back to the spaceport was their host’s prospects.

“Poor guy,” was Allison’s opinion. “I kinda get the impression he’s new to dating.”

“Lot of fun, though. I had a great time today,” Julian said.

“You spent most of it getting thrown around like a football,” Allison pointed out. She’d been on edge the whole time as they watched him kick a ball around and wrestle (or rather, be wrestled by) men who were so much larger than him it had been like watching a labrador merrily chase a couple of tanks. Xiu, whose lifetime of practising Gung Fu, Taiji, gymnastics and ballet had given her slightly more insight into how people moved had instantly spotted Adam and Christian’s incredible poise. Both men were so utterly in control that Julian had been perfectly safe to roughhouse with them, and he knew it as well.

Worrying about something less than Allison did had been an interesting experience.

Julian grinned, a little apologetically. “Been a long time since I hung out with guys my age,” he said.

“…Shit, yeah. I guess it has,” Allison conceded. “And you didn’t really do stuff like that with Lewis or Amir, did you?”

“They weren’t exactly the physical type…” Julian sighed. “It’s weird, you don’t really appreciate something simple like just playing ball with a couple guys until you haven’t done it in years.”

“Glad you got the chance?”

“Yeah.”

The conversation ended there as they arrived at the spaceport, and they lingered in the hangar doorway to look out across the concrete and take in the town’s lights around them.

“…I’m going to miss Cimbrean.” Xiu decided. There was something so different about it compared to Earth, something she couldn’t quite put her finger on.

“We’ll be back. Resupply in nine months, remember?”

“I’m still going to miss it.”

“…Me too.”

“Yeah.”

They stood in silence then shook themselves, headed indoors, and went to bed.

They had a long job ahead of them.

Date Point 10y9m1d AV
Celzi Alliance command facility, Crzlrfek System, The Freedom Stars

Warmaster Trez Ekrat

There was still far too much yellow in the volumetric strategy map, but that was why seeing one important marker blink and turn blue felt so… satisfying.

That marker represented a class six temperate world so newly colonized that the Dominion’s supine bureaucracy hadn’t even approved a formal name for it, yet. It still appeared on the Dominion’s star charts as ‘DTC-whitesquare-44 170-T6’.

On Alliance star charts, its name translated to something equivalent to ‘Fertile Flood’, a name that sounded strong in Celz’ (Zrefn Delc’) and poetic in Qininis (Nisiqithathe). In most regards it was an unremarkable planet with nothing much going for it, other than one valuable feature: An enormous flood plain network where several river deltas met and crawled across thousands of square kilometers of incomparably fertile soil under warm temperate sunlight with predictable weekly rains.

Upon taking receipt of the planet, its owners had promptly stripped that biome every scrap of native flora and introduced alien feed crops like Cqcq and Rhwk. From the mountains to the ocean, every square meter of an area the size of a moderate country was farmland, tended by ten million drones.

The Alliance needed that food. Their existing agricultural infrastructure only barely met the demands of a swelling population that had bred in expectation of a war of expansion onto the fertile unclaimed worlds around them, and had instead found themselves confined to a dense knot of planets when the arrival of humans had compelled a ceasefire.

A ceasefire that had finally ended, thanks to the baffling decision by a Dominion fleetmaster to plunge suicidally deep into Alliance territory and blow up a communications relay station.

Warmaster Ekrat didn’t know the term ‘straining at the leash’, but he had been doing it nonetheless. By the time the Alliance council realized that they could postpone their unpopular plans for rationing and instead had the chance to annex an already established farming colony, Ekrat’s plans had been drawn up, his troop carriers loaded, his patrol ships recalled and his assault poised.

He’d even completed the lengthy process of preparing a space station for transit, and the anchorage ‘Light Spike’ had jumped into orbit around Fertile Flood three days after the order was given to invade, punctuating a swift and utterly effective annexation. With its firepower, long-range defensive shields and repair facilities in place the Alliance fleet had a new base of operations so strong that the Dominion would have almost had a better prospect of evicting them from Crzlrfek.

The question before him now was…

“Where next?”

Ekrat turned. His Qinis logistics-master, Vasi Thal, was pondering the strategic map with a finger resting lightly on his lips and his ears twitching this way and that as he thought. Despite being as thin as a grass stalk he cut an impressive figure wearing an ornate black uniform with sombre steel trim and a dozen tiny iridescent chains that clipped to his ears and whispered like a silver breeze at the slightest movement.

“That’s for me to decide,” Ekrat told him.

“Counsel, Warmaster?”

“Of course.”

“Our first objective should be to consolidate our hold on Nisiqithathe. We need to secure the access to that system so that the colony’s food products can be delivered back to the core worlds.”

“An objective that will most easily be achieved by threatening other Dominion colonies and bases in this region,” Ekrat agreed. He brought up his long, dextrous tail and gestured into the heart of the map display, picking out the markers that indicated Dominion facilities in and near the border stars. “We can keep them on the defensive.”

Thal looked uncomfortable. “When you say ‘threatening’…?"

“Ah. So you have heard my reputation."

Thal cleared his long throat. “Is there any truth to it?”

“Some.”

“How much.”

Ekrat snuffed a hint of contemptuous amusement. “Thal, never tell your subordinates how accurate your reputation is. A little mystery is good for a commander.”

“Even if the reputation is for unnecessarily ruthless violence?”

Ethrak had had this conversation or some variant of it many times before, and he had learned with effort to suppress his irritation at the word ‘unnecessary’. He had never done anything unnecessary. Ruthlessly violent, yes, but never unnecessary.

“Especially then,” he replied instead.

“So… when you say ‘threaten’…?" Thal pressed.

“If your conscience makes you squeamish, Thal, then don’t ask. The threat will be credible: if it was not, it wouldn’t be effective."

“I… see, Warmaster. I withdraw my question.”

“Sensible. Make your preparations to take over the colony farm and export the food. Leave the dirty work of securing your space lanes to me.”

“…Yes, Warmaster.” Thal bowed stiffly, and made himself scarce.

Ethrak made a satisfied gesture to himself, and planned how best to terrorize the Dominion into defending the wrong things…

Date Point 10y9m2w AV
Ava Rios

Gabriel was waiting for Ava when she checked her bags with the HMS Sharman gate guards and was allowed to leave, but her heart sank the moment she laid eyes on him.

He was in his wheelchair. He hated using his wheelchair.

She gave him a kiss on the cheek and a hug. “Hey! ¿Estas bien?"

Gabe grumbled unhappily. “My fucking leg’s not working at all today…” He groused. “Enough about me. How did it go?”

“He’s put me on, uh…” Ava dug in her handbag and read the prescription. “…Paroxetine.”

“That’s good!”

“I guess…”

Gabe gestured back toward town and turned his chair. There was nothing wrong with his arms at least. "¿Que pasa?" he asked, softly.

“I… this is gonna sound stupid…” Ava sighed, falling in alongside him.

“Go ahead and say it anyway.”

“I just really don’t want to have to take these."

He looked up at her. “Why not?”

“I don’t know. I just… I know it’ll help me feel better and I know I need it, but…”

Gabe nodded.

“You know?” Ava finished, lamely.

“I do, yeah.” Gabe slapped his wheelchair. “I know I need this thing, but…”

“But you hate it.”

“Yeah. I’ll use it when I have to, but that doesn’t mean I have to like it. It’s…” Gabe paused to select his words. “…It’s a reminder that I’m not whole.”

That was maybe a little too blunt of a description for Ava’s taste, but under the discomfort she had to admit that he’d hit the mark for her too. She felt like she’d been walking around with a piece missing that she’d managed to hide for so long, and now it was out in the open for everybody to see. She felt exposed.

Gabriel sighed as they stopped at the pedestrian crossing. “It’s human nature to avoid the hard stuff in our life if we can,” he said. “I remember when I was your age, I never wanted to look at my bank balance even though I needed to know how much I had so I could spend it sensibly. Everybody’s like that. It’s why people don’t exercise or stick to diets, because that’s hard and we all prefer the easy way.”

“And then you get obese diabetics complaining about how hard their life is when it’d have been way less harder if they just put in some effort," Ava observed as he pressed the button..

“You’re in a cynical mood today, mija…"

“Sorry.”

“I don’t blame you, though…” The light changed to let them across, and Gabe rolled his chair off the sidewalk. “You are gonna take the pills, right?"

“Charlotte’s promised to nag me if I don’t,” Ava told him, with a weak but genuine smile. Finally opening up to her best friend had been difficult and tearful, but had rewarded her with the kind of emotional and practical support that only a midwife could provide.

“You’re lucky to have friends like- ¡Me cago en todo lo que se menea!"

Heads turned at that last virulent outburst as Gabe inexpertly turned his chair a little too soon after making it up onto the sidewalk and managed to get himself stuck straddling the kerb. He wrenched furiously at the wheels to try and get it back onto the sidewalk then went limp and defeated.

“…Help.”

Ava hauled him back up safely onto the sidewalk. He sighed and rubbed at his temples then threw his hands down in frustration.

“Fuck!”

“Swearing in English for a change, Dad?” Ava teased, trying to lighten the mood. It worked, and Gabriel chuckled a little.

“Sometimes I think ‘fuck’ might just be the best word ever invented," he confessed.

She put a hand on his back. "Entiendo."

He rubbed the wheel ruefully. “Let’s go for a walk. I need the practice and the doctor says I should use this thing more anyway…”

“You should. It’s supposed to increase your mobility, Dad."

“Weren’t you the one saying you didn’t want to take your pills?”

“I don’t want to, but I will," Ava said firmly.

Gabe paused, then nodded. “Right. Es justo."

“There’s that nice gelato place on Parkside and Peake…” Ava suggested.

“Sounds good.” He turned his chair in the right direction and headed out with a determined expression. Ava watched after him for a second feeling a complicated mix of emotions that she couldn’t quite pick apart, then adjusted her handbag and followed.

It was nice not to feel completely alone.

Date Point 10y9m3w AV
Fort Bragg, North Carolina, USA, Earth

Master Sergeant Derek Coombes

The problem with doing PT alongside Staff Sergeant Walsh was that his nickname--“Tiny”--was a completely ironic one. The guy had tried out for SOR for crap’s sake, he was as big as a barn and lived in the kind of performance athlete territory that meant he was constantly “failing” physicals and having to get a waiver from the doctors to say that, yes, he was perfectly healthy and that “excess” weight was all muscle.

Coombes was a different creature, from a different philosophy of training that had fallen out of fashion in the modern army. He was lighter and more wiry, more average in build and well-suited to blending into a crowd exactly like he’d been doing in Egypt.

This naturally meant that when it came to the gym, anything Coombes could do Walsh could do better. Much better. And that shit was not about to be accepted, no matter how much his muscles and joints got angry at him. He couldn’t match the big fucker on weight but he would damn well match him pace- for-pace and rep-for-rep, his pride demanded nothing less.

Fortunately, Tiny was diplomatic enough not to comment on how Coombes spent a bit longer massaging his aching limbs under the shower afterwards.

They talked about other things instead, while they did their boots up. “So you’re taking a second shot?”

Tiny nodded. “Dude, the only reason I’m not wearing that spacesuit already is because I fucked my arm up. I’m gonna be SOR."

“Too bad for me they don’t take guys my size,” Coombes mused. Ever since Allied Extrasolar Command had tentatively declared that the Hierarchy threat on Earth was neutralized, he’d been at something of a loose end. There was plenty of shit still to do on Earth, but somehow the global war on extremism seemed much less important than the extraterrestrial stuff nowadays.

It was kinda hard to accept that the war he’d literally been shot through the lung while fighting had sorta… fizzled out after Operation EMPTY BELL. The enemy was still out there, the war was still on, but suddenly it didn’t need guys like him any more. That stuck in the craw.

They were both surprised to find a man in air force blues with silver oak leaves on his shoulders waiting for them outside the fitness center. He looked up the second they stepped outside and stood.

“Uh… good afternoon, sir,” Coombes said and saluted.

“Afternoon, as you were, gentlemen.,” the officer replied and returned the salute. He had a friendly, informal manner and a pleasant smile. “Master Sergeant Coombes, right? And Staff Sergeant Walsh?”

“That’s us,” Tiny agreed. Both men assumed a loose parade rest.

“As you were, gentlemen. Lt. Col. Miller, 946th Operations Support Squadron,” Miller introduced himself and shook their hands. “I’m the DoD’s maintenance officer for the Spaceborne Operations Regiment. Got a career opportunity for you boys if you’re interested…”

Naturally, both of them jumped at the chance. There was the usual rigmarole of finding somewhere private to have the conversation and all the other stuff that went with a classified briefing, but none of that took long. They wound up seated at the corner table at Quiznos where Miller treated them to their pick off the menu and produced the kind of sound-suppressing and air-opaquing security gizmo that only people who worked closely with Scotch Creek seemed to play with.

The air around them fuzzed and became… hazy. Not opaque, but certainly impossible to discern any detail from outside their little gray bubble of privacy. The noise and bustle around them vanished under a blanket of white noise, which in turn stopped their own words from leaving the immediate vicinity of their table.

“Allied Extrasolar Command want to reincarnate JETS teams,” Miller said, as soon as they were settled. “But not as a certification this time. As the real deal--a working, full-time part of the SOR. Given that the reasons why have to do with your mission in Egypt, you were the obvious guys to offer first refusal.”

Coombes brightened immediately. This was already sounding exactly like what he’d been hankering for but when he glanced over, Tiny’s expression was interested but unenthusiastic at best.

“JETS already fell through once,” he pointed out.

“It’s a different beast this time. Very different,” Miller promised. “We have a definite mission and need, a clearer idea of the requirements and, importantly, JETS team members will be a critical counterpart to the guys in the spacesuits, the HEAT teams as we’re calling them now.”

“I kinda have my sights set on being one of those guys in the spacesuit…" Walsh said. “Hell, I already got selected and then busted my arm…”

“Well, hear me out.” Miller selected a file on his tablet and handed it over. “How old are you, Walsh? Twenty-eight?”

“That’s right…”

“You were briefed on the built-in declining efficiency of Cruezzir-D, right?"

Tiny nodded reluctantly.

“So even if you head down to Huntsville today you’re never really going to feel the full benefit of Crue-D enhanced training…" Miller said.

“Begging your pardon sir, but bullshit. Firth’s was about my age when he started the Crude. A little older even, and look at the guy."

“I thought you might bring that up.” Miller fished out an e-paper photograph. He laid it down on the table and swiped through the images loaded onto it. “Here. Firth was kind enough to share some photos to drive home the point. Here he is at thirteen…and fifteen…and seventeen, when he enlisted….”

Coombes and Walsh both boggled. The allegedly thirteen-year old boy in the first photo was unbelievably fit and only marginally smaller than Walsh was right now. The young man in the second image was legitimately enormous, and the photos after that…

“…Jesus.”

Miller nodded. “Mm-hmm. Now imagine if he’d started on Crue-D early in life, like Warhorse did. Honestly, the fact that he’ll maybe never hit his theoretical maximum is probably a blessing in disguise for him."

The way Tiny scowled slightly at the photo told Coombes that Miller had scored a hit.

“I think what Tiny’s saying is he doesn’t want to settle for second-best, sir,” he observed. Walsh nodded.

Miller sat back and tapped the tabletop thoughtfully. “…What do you mean by ‘best’?" he asked. “Biggest? Strongest? Deadliest? Let’s face it, Firth and Warhorse already have those wrapped up tight, but you should talk to them sometime. What they both focus on is all the ways their buddies are better than them at other stuff. So… best at what?”

He smiled winningly. “This is still the SOR. Same unit, same standards, same stakes, same mission, everything. I’m still offering you the chance to be the best: the only difference is focus. As a Joint Extra-Terrestrial Scout, you would infiltrate hostile worlds and live there for months at a time, never seen, never detected, and you’d generate absolutely priceless first-take intel. Intel without which the big guys in the suits would be useless."

“That doesn’t sound second-rate to me, Tiny,” Coombes said.

Walsh gave him the slightly askance look of a man whose friend was siding with the other guy. “Dude.”

“What? I like the idea and I want you with me!”

“You do?”

Coombes nodded. “Come on, you saw the suit-jockeys in action. How big’s the fucking logistics tail behind those guys?”

“They may as well have a power cable running out the back,” Miller nodded.

“That’s true of any advanced unit, sir. That’s true of an F-16, or an infantry platoon.”

“But not of a scout.”

“Never thought of myself as a scout before…” Tiny rumbled, thoughtfully rather than reluctantly.

“Why not, though? Hell, you’re CCT for fuck sake, how’re you gonna drop a bomb on stuff if you don’t know where it is?”

Tiny smiled, “I’m usually there with a laser designator, but…yeah. I mean, in a way, I guess a combat controller is like a raider, or short-term recon. Hell, recon is a big part of the mission. It’s just…we’re only equipped for days, not weeks or even months, and the equipment load is already…”

He trailed off thoughtfully, and his lips moved silently as he did some mental arithmetic for a handful of seconds. “Armor, equipment, food as dense as we can package it, garbage…tablets for water, tablets to clean up latrines… Shit, you really do need a guy my size for this, don’t you?”

“We really do,” Miller said. “Though, none of this means you can’t still take a swing at HEAT if you want to. But you’ll be blazing new trails, developing tactics and doctrine, you’ll be collaborating with people from all across the special operations communities of the world, finding what makes sense, what doesn’t… You might just find it rewarding, if you’ve got the chops for it.”

He sat back and gave them both a daring stare. "Do you?"

Date Point: Halloween, 10y10m AV
Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Adam Ares

“You know, those fatigues aren’t really part of the costume…”

Martina Kovač folded her arms. “Oh, sure, just ’cause Cammy hangs her ass and cameltoe out for everyone to stare at, that means I have to as well?”

“Well… you are dressed as her." Adam pointed out.

“It’s creative license.” She saw his expression and softened. “Plus, I’ve got that giant burn scar on my butt cheek. Let me have this, okay? I already feel half-naked in this thing…” she plucked awkwardly at her costume’s skin-tight green leotard.

Adam remembered some of the stuff Firth had taught him and stopped himself from pointing out that he, having had the role of Zangief thrust on him, was technically wearing less than she was.

That was their theme for the night. The SOR was throwing a barbecue and party on the green at Quarterside park for the sake of some good PR, and had collectively decided to dress up as an assortment of Street Fighter characters.

“Sorry.”

She shot him a warm look. “Thanks. It’s kinda dumb isn’t it? I’m so used to seeing all of you naked I don’t bat an eyelid, but ask me to dress up like this…”

“We’re in a public park. I don’t think it’s the same.”

“True… but the fatigues work, right? They don’t ruin the costume?”

“Nah, it looks like some kinda DLC alternative outfit or something. You’re fine.”

“Good…” Marty tucked some stray hair up into her long blonde pigtails wig. “…Shall we?”

Adam grinned and got into character. “Da! The Red Cyclone will put on show for little children!"

“That’s… a terrifyingly good impression.”

“Thanks! I practised.”

He took the way she smiled and shook her head as a good sign and got out of the car.

Kids pointed and made awed noises as the two of them approached and Adam took delight in flexing extravagantly for them.

Cimbrean didn’t really have trick-or-treat, though that wasn’t down to any lack of enthusiasm for the holiday. It was just that in the early days of the colony Adam had been one of only about a dozen young people below the age of twenty on the whole planet, and the adults had decided to go with a big themed party instead, a tradition that had stuck especially hard when somebody had hit on the idea that you had to perform some kind of minor forfeit to get your food if you weren’t in costume.

As a result, Quarterside Park was a sea of people of all ages in costume, from the traditional little girls in pointy-hatted witch costumes, through videogame characters and superheroes, and of course there was the Cimbrean franchise of the Ghostbusters with their brown boiler suits and their intricate and expensively realistic proton packs. Akiyama was a member, though today he was playing his role in the SOR’s Street Fighter ensemble.

The aliens mostly treated it all with bemusement though the Gaoians were getting into the swing of things, led by their cubs. While they occasionally had slightly odd ideas for what constituted a costume, as evidenced by the burly Straightshield brother who was walking around dressed as a boiled lobster, nobody could argue they hadn’t enthusiastically grabbed the spirit of the day with both paws.

They made a meandering line for the horseshoe of barbecues in the middle of the park where Sagat (Firth), Balrog (Burgess) and Ken (Sikes) were expertly tending two grills apiece in a confident bustle of activity and keeping up some banter with the happy eaters as they went.

Then there were the snack tables where Blanka (Vandenberg) and Dan Hibiki (Murray) were keeping everyone supplied with all the snacks, sweets and soda they could ask for. On the grass, Guile (Blaczynski) and Ryu (Akiyama) were having a push-up contest with several children sitting on their backs and cheering them on..

“So where do we fit in?” Marty asked.

“Meet and greet, amuse the kids, make the adults happy…” Adam replied. They’d all gone over their roles earlier in the week while assembling their costumes, and the consensus had been that Adam was best placed doing their strongman show while Marty could take some of the masculine edge off. Already kids were pointing and nudging each other, and the adults were gawping, including some whom he recognized. On any other day it might have made him self-conscious but today he was in-character.

Marty stifled a giggle as he hammed it up for the crowd and put on his outrageous Russian accent. They made a good double-act, especially when she wound up sitting primly on his shoulder while half a dozen children and a couple of cubs tried their best to drag his arms down while he roared with massively exaggerated laughter.

Then there were the selfies, the handshakes, posing for photos and hour after hour of being as friendly as he could muster which finally came to a blessed end with the fireworks display.

It was a massive relief when the last of the children was finally ushered home and literally every adult in the park heaved a sigh of relief and relaxed. The beers appeared from nowhere, the music got a little more raw, the jokes edgier and the smiles (and language) were less guarded.

The only potential tripwire in fact was the friction between Ava and the Lads. She was present in her role as an ESNN photojournalist and had spent the day recording the festivities for the network’s local news website. Once the children and their parents were gone there was no reasonable way for her to avoid the SOR without shirking her duties, nor indeed for them to avoid her without shirking theirs.

The Lads weren’t being rude exactly--all of them knew that actively snubbing Ava was a good way to irritate the man responsible for their exercise schedule --but even for the camera they were being decidedly cool, and it was dragging out the shoot longer than needed as she tried to capture some merriment from them.

In the end, Marty took her gently by the elbow and led her away from the group where they settled into a quiet conversation while the Lads shrugged at each other and unwound. Adam sidled over to try and listen in.

“…don’t like me, I know why they don’t like me and… I mean, I accept that," Ava was saying, when he could finally hear her. “But I don’t want to mess this up for you. This is important, isn’t it?”

“Good PR is kinda vital for us, yeah…”

“Right. Well, I wanna deliver good PR. I just… I don’t know how right now. It’s hard when you can’t build a rapport.”

She sounded so despondent that Adam would have stepped in and given her a hug right then and there if Marty hadn’t caught his eye and, very subtly, shaken her head so instead he backed off a little to the discreet distance he’d found where he could still make out what they were saying while seemingly be far enough away that they’d think he couldn’t.

“I think… part of the problem is you’re going with this heroic angle,” Marty suggested to Ava. “You’re trying to show us in a positive light rather than just, uh, point the camera at what’s there. Right?"

Ava cocked her head thoughtfully. “…I guess so,” she conceded, after a few seconds.

“So, maybe the thing to do is just…”

“Let them be themselves,” Ava finished. “Stop trying to tell a story.”

“Well, I can’t blame you for wanting to tell a story,” Marty said warmly, “but yeah. I guess that’s the gist of what I’m saying.”

“And you’re right… thank you.”

“No problem.” Marty stood up. “You gonna be okay?”

“Uh… actually, can I ask you a personal question? Like, as me, not as the reporter.”

Marty gave her a curious look, but gestured for her to ask.

“Why are you being nice to me?”

Marty glanced at Adam, scratched thoughtfully at the line of her wig and then sat back down again. “…Counter-question. Why are you being nice to them?" she asked. “You’re being surprisingly loyal considering how hard they’re snubbing you.”

“It’s nothing I don’t deserve.”

“You think? Well… I guess they think so. But I know ’Horse doesn’t and I trust his instincts, even if he is hella naive sometimes."

Ava laughed at that. “That makes two of us.”

“What do you mean?”

“Huh?”

“Well, do you mean you’re naive too, or do you mean you trust his instincts too?” Marty clarified.

“…Both?”

It was Marty’s turn to laugh, and that drew out one of Ava’s real smiles. She had so many flavors of fake, tired, weak and polite smile that seeing some genuine happiness dawn on her face was like witnessing a small miracle of nature.

“He is naive, though," Marty added, and Adam felt his ears burn pink a little.

“Can you blame him?”

“Hell no. He’s been stuck in this hyper-masculine bubble for his whole adult life and… I mean, I know you two had a pretty rough time of it, losing your home and everything…”

“Yeah.” It was Ava’s turn to glance in Adam’s direction, and he did his best to pretend not to notice. “We both learned some really hard lessons and… I guess there were some other lessons where, like, we didn’t get the chance.”

“I’m sorry.”

“Thanks.”

Adam had heard enough. He got up and joined them, causing both girls to first look up curiously and then make very similar squeaks as he drew the pair of them into his trademark huge full-body-workout hug.

Marty, being stronger than Ava, was the first to work her way free. “Dude, what-?”

“I’m just glad you two are getting along!” Adam explained, easing off.

Ava straightened her hair and tugged on the pink sports jacket that was part of her costume, then took a step back. “Thanks, uh… Look, why don’t you go mingle? I’ll just sorta… snap whatever I see,” she suggested.

Adam looked to Marty, got an almost imperceptible nod, and gave an amplified nod of his own. “Okay! Get yourself a steak sandwich off Firth though, ’kay? He does the best steak sandwiches."

“I’ll… do that, sure.”

“Come on, Zangief,” Marty said, and led him away with an eye-roll and a smack on the arm.

He checked they were out of earshot--really out of earshot--before he said anything. “Uh… Thanks. For helping her.”

“You’re welcome.”

That seemed to be all that needed saying.

Date Point 10y10m2w AV
BGEV-11 Misfit, Cruising on spacelane CSR-orangepentagon-92 034-L, The Border Stars.

Xiu Chang

Regency-period English balls with their fancy gowns and choreographed dances have always fascinated Xiu, and she’s delighted to find herself attending one. And Julian looks so fetching in a high-necked frock coat and cravat too…

Of course there’s still the question of justifying their presence to the hostess. They bluffed their way in by pretending to be a standup comedy act but the time is soon coming when they’ll have to actually deliver on their bluff, so the three of them sit down with her brother Wei at a table in McDonald’s to discuss their routine, where Allison starts telling jokes.

The first two are funny enough but the third… She can’t hear the joke properly but it has something to do with a jar of pickled beets and is so funny that she woke up giggling with the real Julian and Allison sitting up in bed beside her and giving her strange looks.

“Uh, babe? You sound really creepy when you laugh in your sleep…” Allison declared, wiping an eye.

Xiu descended into a fit of the giggles that just wouldn’t go away, especially when Julian and Allison exchanged a bemused look and he shrugged, got up, stretched and vanished into the shower for his morning rinse.

Eventually, the laughter died down enough for her to apologize. “Sorry, sorry… In my dream, you were very funny.”

Allison snorted and shook her head. “I was, huh?”

“Yeah. Did I really sound creepy?”

“You laughed like ‘hurrr hurrr hurrr…’" Allison imitated a slow, low and gormless laugh.

“Oh God…" Xiu buried her face in her pillow, feeling her cheeks burn red.

“Hey, at least your dreams are funny…” Allison beamed.

Xiu threw the pillow at her. The pillow came back with interest and they quickly got into a happy twisting wrestling match that Xiu, being shorter and stronger, won easily. Allison quickly found herself pinned by the wrists and helpless with Xiu grinning down at her inside a private curtain of hair.

Of course, Allison was far too competitive to take defeat gracefully. She wriggled and squirmed and tried to fight loose, but her longer limbs were no use at all. Xiu had all the advantages. “Agh… nooo! Get-!”

“Give up?”

“Never!”

“Give u-up!” Xiu tightened her grip slightly.

“Owowow…ow!”

Xiu relented again. “Give,” she repeated slowly, lowering her face for emphasis “U-Mm!"

Allison had surged up and kissed her.

Oh. Well. If that was the game she wanted to play…

Julian was treated to quite the show a few minutes later when he finished his shower. He paused in the doorway and watched until Xiu noticed him.

“Hey,” she said.

“Hey,” he replied. “Uh… Do, uh… do I get to join in?”

“You can make breakfast?”

“You’re evil.”

“Yeff she iff!” Allison managed to call, in a muffled voice. She was face- down in a pillow with her hands held inextricably behind her back and Xiu sitting astride her legs.

“Hush, Shǎguā…" Xiu grinned down at her.

At long last, Allison finally gave up and went limp. “…Yeff m’m…”

“Good girl.”

Julian muttered something to himself that sounded like “Fuck, that’s hot…” and wiped his face on his towel before going to find something to make for breakfast.

“Where were we?” Xiu asked. Allison managed to turn her head enough that she was no longer breathing pillow.

“You are evil, you know that right? We’ve created a monster."

Xiu bent forward and nibbled her ear, which she’d found was a sure-fire way to get Allison flustered. “Mm-hmm…”

Allison gasped and shivered. "Fuck…!"

“Relax, Shǎguā. You brought this on yoursel-"

Either the world or Misfit had an awful sense of timing, or perhaps a sadistic one. Whatever the reason, the general alarm made all three of them pause for a second before Xiu rolled off the bed cursing colorfully in three languages and performed some high-speed gymnastics as she flung on her clothes as fast as she ever had.

This wasn’t just modesty. Their clothing was comfortable, breathable, easily cleaned and practical but it was also protective equipment that was both flame retardant and cut-proof. Even in an emergency, the protocol they’d had drilled into them was to dress first. Quickly, of course.

They bolted for their stations and Xiu was in the pilot’s seat and buckled up inside thirty seconds of the alarm sounding. She jammed her headset on as she surveyed what the ship was telling her.

Misfit herself was fine, which came as a relief. The alarm had been thrown up by the sophisticated decision-making algorithm that monitored the FTL sensors for them when they were asleep or off-duty. It had seen something, something massive where nothing should be, and promptly called for a human takeover.

“Bad news,” Julian called within seconds. His voice sounded grim. “It’s a gravity spike.”

Xiu’s breath caught in her throat and Allison said what they were all thinking. “Jesus…”

“But we’re not caught in it…” Xiu pointed out.

“No, it’s a couple of light-months ahead of us on the spacelane… Misfit says we’d have hit it in four minutes.”

“Thank you Clara…” Allison muttered. “We’d have run right into it without her…”

“Nah, they’re not just set up and left waiting…” Julian said. “That thing got fired to catch somebody.”

Xiu checked the sensor logs. “We were cruising about a quarter of a lightyear behind a cargo ship…”

“I’m going dark.” Allison declared. Xiu watched with a chilly feeling in her spine as available power dropped down to standby levels.

“…Hunters?” she asked.

“Or pirates. Or Alliance. Whatever the answer…” Allison left the thought unfinished. They all knew that they were unarmed, and that their best bet for safety lay in silence first and speed second. Space was vaster than anybody could comprehend, and Misfit was very very tiny. Without power to her warp drive there was no practical likelihood of discovery and even the infrared radiation they were putting out was so faint and so short-ranged that anybody placed to see it would already have effectively found them.

“Can’t we do anything?” Julian asked. “Jump back to Cimbrean, inform the Royal Navy?”

There was a long, unhappy pause on the line, and Xiu knew what the answer was. She sat helplessly and watched the stars in the long seconds before Allison confirmed what the sensors were already telling her.

“It’s already too late. Whoever those poor bastards were… All we can do is pray for them.”

Xiu sighed and pulled her feet up into her chair, hugging her knees. Suddenly, she was feeling very small, very frail, and very helpless. It was a horrible reminder that their mission was a dangerous one.

And the day had started out so well, too…

She sat, and she meditated, and she watched until the spike was taken down. Even then they waited a further two hours before they finally decided to brave the road ahead again.

None of them left their posts until the incident was six hours and twenty lightyears behind them.

Date Point 10y10m2w AV
Command Station 1053 ‘Linchpin Of Infinity’, The Orin Line

Fleetmaster Garal

Garal disliked chaos.

This was a shame, because chaos seemed to love her, especially since she had been thrust up through the ranks so abruptly after the eleventh patrol fleet’s sudden suicidal jaunt into enemy territory. Now she was having to rebuild the destroyed fleet from scratch and it was anarchy. All of the shipmasters were still sorting out their place in the pecking order relative to one another, their undershipmasters and junior officers were doing the same, new ships were arriving that had barely cooled down from the nanofactories before having an entirely novice crew stuffed into them and sent Garal’s way to sort out.

She wished she could go back to her old role as a military foreman. She would have bid away her twin, if she’d had one, for the comforting simplicity of mathematics, forces and loads. She knew where she stood with concrete, which was usually looking up at several thousand tonnes of the stuff poised and solidified overhead into a defensive structure whose tolerances she knew to a fraction.

Marshalling people of two dozen alien species of varying rarity, temperament and ability was something else entirely. The world had not built Locayl to be diplomats and commanders.

It had certainly not built them to try and lift that baton when Celzi warships accompanied by legions of Qinisi fighter drones were stabbing here and there in the border worlds. With a more seasoned fleet she might have felt comfortable drawing some of her ships back and compiling them into a response force that could strike back into Alliance territory and take the pressure off.

As it was…

Her requests for reinforcements had been met with a quiet inconsequential reprimand that made it quite clear she was on her own, and confirmed several dark suspicions she’d held about Dominion high command for some years. Whatever their priorities were, the actual protection of colonies and vulnerable civilians seemed to be far down on the list.

It could be no coincidence that all the best ships, all the most seasoned crews and all the most decorated commanders were bodyguarding the wealthy corporate fiefdoms of the core worlds while the border stars were being tended by overstretched rookies under the command of a fleetmaster who would have given three of her arms to not be in command.

From what she knew, the territories abutting Hunter space (or at least, what everybody presumed was Hunter space--that whole swathe of the galaxy had for obvious reasons never been scouted) had it just as bad.

It was enough to grind down even the most hardened and jaded commander, and Garal was still young and idealistic enough to feel like there had to be a better way. To an engineer’s mind the whole idea of wasting strong materials-- and materiel--on reinforcing the places that were already strongest while the weaker supplies were frittered away on the corroding edge of civilization was not only backwards, it was frustratingly, infuriatingly, obviously backwards. And anybody who hadn’t actually been lobotomized couldn’t fail to see it as well.

Which meant that the whole military structure of the Interspecies Dominion was corrupt, perhaps irredeemably so.

So when she was left swiping listlessly through the latest reports on what new carnage her opposite number, Warmaster Ekrat, was inflicting on the colonies and civilian shipping in the region, it was enough to make her want to quit. The morning’s tally included a freighter with a crew of two hundred: Alliance strike craft had pounced on it, ripped it in two and left bodies and crates to drift unclaimed in deep space. They hadn’t even taken any of the cargo.

Break her bones, but it was enough to drive her to the edge of despair. If the Alliance weren’t the very enemy whose successes were going un-countered and if they had been less ruthless about it all then she might almost have considered defecting. Whatever accusations of callous and casual violence might be directed against the Celzi, they at least did things with intelligence and, more importantly, with integrity.

Unfortunately, their intelligent and integral campaign was arrayed against her sector, her ships and the colonies under her watch, and there were no right answers. If she spread the fleet wide enough to have a patrol in every vulnerable volume, then those patrols would be too pathetic to do more than run away at the first sign of Celzi. If she concentrated her forces enough to be effective, then the Celzi just struck wherever her ships weren’t. There was no balance point.

Which meant, as any engineer knew, that an alternative approach was called for. Infuriatingly, she couldn’t think of one.

But she could think of somebody who might.

She called the station’s communications center.

“Station comms… Ah, Fleetmaster. What can I do for you?”

The Linchpin’s commsmaster was a Ruibal by the name of Thlenth. Ruibal were fellow four-arms, but with knobbled orange skin and an odd number of legs-- she’d read once that their fifth leg was actually an evolved tail, though she had no idea what kind of habitat or stimuli might have induced such an evolution--and unsettlingly large mouths. They were one of the rarer species in the wider galaxy, given their fondness for parochial bickering on their homeworld…

She folded the thought up and put it away. Different species had different priorities and she would respect that: unconscious bigotry had no place in the mind of a commander.

“We have a line to the humans, do we not?” she asked, without preamble. Thlenth went a little paler.

“A direct line? Well… yes, Fleetmaster. You have the authority to directly contact their ambassador in fact…”

“Good. I think it’s time for them to start living up to their promises…”

Date Point 10y10m2w AV
Uncharted Class 12 deathworld, Near 3Kpc Arm

The Singer

They weren’t dead.

They weren’t.

Nobody had found their bones or anything of theirs, therefore they were not dead. Until she had proof, until she had a better reason than that they hadn’t come back…

Even if they’d been gone for more than a moon cycle. Even if-

No. Better not to think about it. Better to just throw herself into her work.

The old Singer had given her an insight early in her apprenticeship, into the difference between the magic of men and the magic of women and why one was not better than the other. She had said “We both know that men take and women give. They take lives, we give birth. They take their time, we give our time… but we can give them our pain and they will take it off us.”

And Sky-Thinker was so good at that. So good that when he was away on a hunt, she felt like her arm was steadily falling asleep--she could still do everything, but not as freely and it was all more of an effort that only got worse as time went on.

Which was why she almost collapsed from the relief when she heard the thrum of a sentry’s shouting-stone welcoming home a successful hunt. On any other day it would have only been a hope, but today there were only two men not accounted for.

She burst from her tent.

Sky-Thinker and Stone-Tapper both looked awful. They were caked in mud, emaciated, and had the dead look in their eyes of men who hadn’t slept properly in far too long… but they were smiling, and they were dragging a litter with a prize of some kind on it.

The Singer considered the gravitas of her position for a moment and then discarded it. She bounded across the village clearing and crashed into Sky- Thinker’s chest in an enormous flying hug. He did quite a good job of weathering the impact considering he looked half-dead already.

He stank, and was filthy with dried mud, but he was back.

They both ignored the amused trills from the villagers as he ran his hand through her hair crest and sighed happily. “By the gods, I missed you…”

“What happened?!” she asked. “It was only a hunt, you’ve been gone for… what’s this?"

She had seen the… object on their litter. It didn’t quite look real, somehow: its edges were too straight and clean and its surface was as flat as still water. It was made of the same strange material as the sharp death-bird wing that Sky-Thinker now used as a knife, apart from a tangle of four strange dark flexible tubes like thick black guts that sprouted from one end.

Sky-Thinker and his father exchanged the proud looks of men who had brought back a truly legendary prize.

“…This is the heart of the beast that destroyed our village.”

Date Point 10y10m2w2d AV
Allied Extrasolar Command, Scotch Creek, British Columbia, Canada

General Martin Tremblay

Mid-week strategic meetings were sometimes sprawling affairs where dozens of the most powerful people in the world were at loggerheads, and sometimes they were smaller and more intimate. Today’s was tiny--the only person other than Tremblay and Admiral Knight to have called in was President Arthur Sartori, who had never missed a meeting and probably never would unless he was unconscious in a hospital bed.

He especially wasn’t going to miss this one. With the Dominion-Alliance war rekindling itself in fitful bursts of alarming violence, the Global Representative Assembly’s ambassador to the Dominion had been flooded with increasingly strident calls for humanity to step in and honor its default status as a Dominion member, the most recent coming directly from the Dominion’s fleetmaster on the front lines who had painted a grim picture of civilian casualties.

The GRA’s policy for the time being was that humanity officially resented being considered a Dominion member by default and would have preferred to be invited and negotiated into the fold rather than being effectively conscripted.

Unfortunately, while the membership may have been unsolicited it was also beneficial to humanity’s interests. The Interspecies Dominion was compelled by its own charter to furnish newly interstellar species with a supply of “Dominion Development Credits” that could be used to introduce the technological and logistical fruits of interstellar culture into the new member’s society at a controlled and manageable rate. Among the many things they did for the human race, including the purchase of new technologies, they were the only currency that the Corti Directorate would accept in trade for Cruezzir-D.

This was valuable, but as President Sartori was explaining, it was also leverage.

“The Dominion is getting impatient with us. They’re even talking about cutting off our DDC allowance.”

Tremblay grimaced. “If we lose those funds, it’d kill the SOR,” he said. “And our hopes of a customs and trade station at Cimbrean.”

Sartori nodded grimly, and not for the first time Tremblay counted his lucky stars that he was working with this POTUS rather than his predecessors. Sartori liked to present himself as hard-nosed but calculating and thoughtful, and by and large he walked that talk.

His election campaign had played to the fears, anger and grief of a country reeling from the aftermath of San Diego, and of a public who were no longer interested in hearing sound-bites and platitudes from their political caste. Far from the headline-grabbing shenanigans that had characterized previous Republican candidacies, Sartori had marched boldly onto the public stage armed with solid, concrete and realistic plans for revitalizing America’s staggering agricultural and technology sectors via a policy of aggressive for-profit investment.

With the slogan ‘Eyes On The Prize’ he’d contemptuously demolished his fellow Republicans whom he’d characterized as irrelevant, out of touch and misfocused, and he had successfully wielded constitutional rhetoric to attack his Democrat counterpart, who had been unable to convincingly repulse the accusation that their platform was in conflict with the first Amendment.

He hadn’t exactly swept into the White House, but he had taken it with a convincing majority. His response to being briefed on DEEP RELIC and all the other information he, as leader of the free world, had need-to-know on about humanity’s status in the galaxy had been to quietly go and sit in a secluded room for several hours and then come out swinging.

Without his clout, the mountain that Allied Extrasolar Command had to climb would have been much steeper and higher.

“I think we need to put our money where our mouth is,” he said firmly. “We were hinting this whole time that whichever side decided to break the ceasefire would answer to us… well, the Celzi have broken the ceasefire. I don’t think we can afford to have a reputation for bluffing on an empty hand.”

Tremblay nodded. “Agreed. But we can’t afford to be the Dominion’s plaything either.”

“Fortunately,” Admiral Knight interjected from his usual spot in a chair next to Tremblay’s desk, “We can probably have our cake and eat it. Neither side is any good at concealing their movements and we’ve identified a target of opportunity… This fellow.”

Sartori scrutinized the file as it was called up. “Trez Ekrat. What is he, a Celzi general?”

“The equivalent. And he’s exposed. Last week the Alliance annexed an agricultural colony in the border territory. The colonists have been fighting back and so this Ekrat chap committed a few more of his troop carriers to the fight, along with their escorts. He’s badly overextended himself and now his command post in, erm… this system…"

Tremblay stifled a chuckle. No wonder Knight hadn’t tried to pronounce the star’s name, even the pronunciation guide in parentheses next to its name was a mouth-mangler.

“…is vulnerable,” Knight finished. “He’s a vicious cad too, this one. Ruthlessly imperialistic, unflinching in the face of appalling casualties, and with the rumours of how POWs and civilians get treated by his forces, he’d be up in the Hague if he were human.”

“Capture or kill, then,” Tremblay said.

“Exactly. Either one would badly disrupt the Alliance’s plans for the region and most likely save civilian lives. I’m inclined to suggest an overwhelming show of strength, scare the bastards straight.”

“Overwhelming strength is the SOR’s forte,” Tremblay commented.

“Break everything,” Sartori advised. “We wanna scare the Dominion a bit as well. Make it clear just how hot of a fire they’re playing with here, otherwise they’ll call on us every time they spot a Celzi scout.”

“I daresay Major Powell will enjoy that suggestion…" Knight smirked.

“I daresay you’ll enjoy giving it,” Tremblay told his friend, smiling as he imitated Knight’s violently English mannerisms.

“I daresay you’re right.”

Sartori grunted and directed an amused look at his camera while raising his hand reassuringly at somebody outside of its field of view. “Any other business?” he asked.

“Not right now. Thank you Mister President.”

“Same time next week, then.” Sartori touched a finger to his eyebrow and ended the call. Somebody must have been figuratively tugging on his sleeve for attention.

“D’you get the impression he enjoys our meetings?” Tremblay mused.

Knight chuckled. “I wouldn’t be surprised. Interstellar war has to be refreshingly straightforward compared to Congress.”

“Don’t say that. The moment words like ‘straightforward’ creep in…"

“Perish the thought. I’ll go tell Powell to expect Hell and give it back twice as hard.”

“Yeah. Let’s show them what war really looks like."

Date Point 10y10m2w2d AV
Folctha, Cimbrean, The Far Reaches

Adam Ares

Adam tried to avoid bad moods. It wasn’t that they weren’t a normal and understandable thing, but he’d had some truly awful days in his life, and knew just how black his own moods could get if he let them. He cultivated good moods as best he could, tried to think the best of everybody and generally played the role of a happy hulk.

Some days, however, conspired against him.

The first sign that he was having such a day was when his sandal broke. Those hiking sandals had been with him since Alabama, and had survived what lesser footwear had not. He’d rucked, jogged, run and trekked hundreds of miles in them and they were among the few items in his life whose reliability he’d been able to take for granted. Everything else needed to be treated with care.

The creak, snap and sudden sensation of looseness on his right foot as he shifted his weight to strap on the second sandal, therefore, gave him the same sinking feeling as he’d felt when he was twelve and had gone to pet his neighbor’s cat only for the idiot feline to hiss at him, scratch his hand and bolt out into the road straight under the wheel of a Prius.

He’d preferred dogs ever since.

He sighed and assessed the damage, wondering if it was something he could repair himself and quickly decided that it wasn’t worth it - the whole sandal was on the verge of collapse, as was its counterpart. He considered putting them up on his wall out of sentiment and then realized he was being, as Major Powell would put it, “daft” and threw them away. He’d gone caveman-barefoot plenty of times anyway.

Sign number two--or number one, really--was that he’d struck out last night. For some reason, the girls were being… not chilly, but a lot less warm than they had been before. So he’d been forced to spend the night alone, cleaning his rifle one-handed.

These two facts combined to put a small thundercloud over his head as he tromped down the stairs barefoot and out into the street.

Today was as close as SOR got to an off day, and it was kind of a party. Major Powell had finally bowed to the inevitable and had taken his homesteading money both from the military and from the Folctha colonization program and had finally made his permanent home on Cimbrean: a comfortably large and well- appointed place on Persephone Lane. He and Murray insisted on calling it a bungalow, but to the rest of the Lads it was unquestionably a rambler.

He’d reluctantly accepted some input and contribution from the Lads too. Adam had crafted for him a compact but well-appointed gym perfect for his specific training regimen. Vandenberg and Sikes had assembled a deck and barbecue pit with surprising speed, and thanks to Akiyama and Blaczynski the house’s home electronics were absolutely state-of-the art. The house was almost a butler despite the teething troubles with the voice recognition software.

Persephone Lane was a short walk over from the little complex of properties that the Lads had assembled on Demeter Way. It would have been shorter still to cut across the broad green space between them that they were keeping as a kind of rough grassy park for anybody who wanted a nice open space for a soccer game or something. About a dozen guys in white were playing cricket on it, a game that Adam had finally got his head around enough to decide that he wasn’t interested.

Disinterest was no reason to disrupt a game though, so he took the long way on the sidewalk, which was where he ran into the third sign as a young mom ushered her kids across the road to get out of his way.

This was something that he usually managed to avoid. He smiled, he kept a light bounce in his step, he did his best to avoid swaggering, stomping or looming… it wasn’t perfect, but there were some pretty simple ways to downplay his immense size. Ever since his dad had taught him about watching how people moved, he’d realized that it really was movement that made people react. He could be as big as a shipping container and strong enough to crush a man’s skull with one hand, but when he moved like a carefree ray of sunshine then his presence actually seemed to delight people if they noticed at all.

He must have been moving like a thundercloud this morning because a wave of people getting out of his way rolled up the street at fifty yards which just depressed and upset him even more and when he tried to force some jollity into his step he failed miserably and instead managed something that was at best an alpha-male swagger.

Which led to the fourth sign. He got to Powell’s new house ready for the moving-in barbecue and party they were throwing for him, heard movement and voices on the deck ’round the back and jogged round eager to be around his buddies. There were three steps up onto the deck and he was so distracted with waving and calling out greetings that he forgot to put his foot on one of the structural beams and it crunched right through the wood like the deck was made of saltine crackers.

"¡Coño!"

Vandenberg helped him extract himself with some affectionate smack-talk.

“I just got this shit built an’ yer already busting it…” he grinned as Adam wiped splinters and blood off his shin.

"Every fuckin’ thing is breaking today…" Adam grumbled as he straightened up. He ignored the graze--he’d already endured far worse pain during that morning’s light PT routine.

“Yeah, my bad bro. Shoulda built it Warhorse-proof.”

“Beginning to think there’s no such thing…” Adam grumbled, adding a muttered "¡La madre que me pario…!" as he examined the damage. “…Sorry, man.”

“Don’t even worry about it. ’S a quick fix and I can make it stronger’n before.” Rebar smacked him on the shoulder. “Firth’s got the barbecue going, there’s iced tea and football indoors and maybe something for that leg. And, y’know, the floor is made’a concrete.”

“Tch!” Adam laughed for the first time that day, flipped Rebar the bird then turned it into a fist bump and headed indoors.

Blaczynski laughed them moment he saw him. “Jeez. So that crash from outside was you, huh?”

“Don’t even.” Adam shook his head and hit up the pitcher of iced tea. He had to reach over Bozo to do it, and the SOR’s mammoth dog whined uncertainly in response to his bad mood, which earned him a reassuring scratch behind the ears.

“Bloody typical. Nice new house wi’ a nice new carpet an’ a nice new deck an’ he’s already smashin’ stuff and bleedin’ all over it,” Major Powell commented. He was sitting at his ease in a huge and enveloping recliner looking relaxed and happy with a drink in one hand and a drumstick in the other. He even had a rare faint smile around the eyes and mouth and he was not a man who smiled naturally. It wasn’t that he was actually bad-tempered, but something about his face was much better suited to deadpan humor and a resting expression of mild hostility. You had to know him quite well to know that he was rarely actually angry even though he looked it all the time.

“Ever had those days where it’s like you managed to piss off God and he’s getting back at you?” Adam asked. His CO huffed a one-beat silent laugh.

“Aye, I think I have,” he nodded. “Do us a favour though mate, clean up that leg before it drips.”

“Sorry.”

“I swear, your fookin’ pain tolerance…” Powell chuckled as Adam ambled easily through into the kitchen. Powell’s house had more double-width arches than door and was built to an SOR scale. For once he didn’t have to turn slightly to fit through the frame.

The kitchen turned out to be full of Burgess and Firth. Adam rounded off what had become known as the ‘Beef Trio’ and suddenly the huge and spacious kitchen space was not so huge and spacious any more.

“‘Bout fuckin’ time you showed,” Base knocked knuckles with him. “What was her name?”

“I wish. Got anything for this?”

“That little ant bite? Man, I’m not wasting a Crude shot on your fuckin’ boo- boo. Paper towel, water, go. Nut up.”

“You’re all heart, Doctor Burgess.”

Baseball snorted. “Man, get your wimpy ass cleaned up.”

It wasn’t exactly a bedside manner, but it put a smile on Adam’s face and he soon had the scratches on his legs cleaned up and disinfected. Disinfectant was kind of a redundant gesture on Cimbrean, where by and large the ambient microbe count was in the same order as might be found in a good private hospital, but old habits died hard, and it helped turn the slow oozing graze into a dry scuff.

Murray and Akiyama showed up just as he returned to the sitting room and poured himself a cold drink. There was happy chatter about how well the house had turned out, the usual brotherly banter, some commentary on the Steelers defense as they lost another forty yards to the Panthers, and when Sikes-- always the last to arrive to anything casual--finally showed up with the housewarming gift they’d all pitched in to pay for, Adam was starting to feel a little more positive about his day. Especially the imminent promise of one of Firth’s steak sandwiches.

The housewarming present was a painting. Sikes had found an artist on the Internet who had produced an absolutely stunning watercolor of the Yorkshire dales at sunset that swept from autumnal peaches and purples in the sky to war golden grass and loose stone walls in the foreground, via a meandering river valley dotted with trees.

It was easy to tell that Powell was moved by the gift--his face locked down completely, and he took the first chance he got to take refuge in bringing up some work-related matters.

“So, seein’ as we’re all here, I thought I’d share two bits o’ news with you…” he said, leaning the painting against the wall on his end table with a fond look.

The Lads all quietened down and listened, more out of ingrained habit than anything. Today was a relaxed day. No booze, because they were all on call, but still a party.

“So, the good news is I got a message from Hunstville yesterday that our four newbies have all passed the first leg of their Crue-D assisted training and they’ll be joinin’ us next month ready to start really becomin’ SOR. I gave Sergeant Kovač the go-ahead this morning to start preppin’ their EV-MASS suits, and we’ve taken on some new suit techs to work with ‘em. There’s another ten young men in the pipeline just startin’ their indoc, we’ll see how many of ‘em make it to Huntsville, but all told it looks like we’ll finally start fillin’ up our MTOE."

He met Adam’s eye. “I don’t need to tell you not to go easy on ’em, right?” he said.

Adam grinned. “Hell no.”

“That’s what I like to hear. Anyway, this next bit’s, er, officially unofficial, like. Keep this quiet ’cause it’s not actually rubber-stamped yet, but the stamp’s bloody well inked up and raised, right?”

He pantomimed raising a stamp and preparing to bring it down hard, and there was a general affirmative muttering.

“We’re bein’ reshuffled a bit,” he said. The Lads made dismayed noises and grumbled until he waved them down. “It’s nowt that’s serious. Probably for the good in fact,” he assured them.

“Ain’t no such thing as a good reshuffle, sir,” Akiyama commented.

Powell half-shrugged. “Allied Extrasolar Command thinks there’s still a strategic need for JETS operators an’ they want to resurrect ‘em. This time the plan is that it’ll be more’n just a cert, they’ll be part of the SOR. They’re rebranding us lot-” he waved an arm to indicate every man in the room, “-as HEAT. Hazardous Environment Assault Teams. Then there’s the techs as the third component. Bit fookin’ messy but that’s what we get for makin’ shit up as we go along.”

“They found guys who’re willing to lead the way on this?” Vandenberg asked.

“Aye, they did. You never met ’em, but everyone who was in Egypt remembers Coombes and Walsh, right?”

“Great guys,” Firth nodded. “I thought Tiny was fixin’ to take the Crude and wear the Mass?”

“Miller persuaded them to be our first JETS instead. Them and a SEAL called Hoeff.”

“Think I know Hoeff,” Firth nodded again. He knew everybody. “Didn’t he get the original JETS cert an’ then have his ass parked in Germany teaching the Krauts how to murder terrorists?”

“Aye, that sounds right.”

“So we’re gonna have a fuckin’ German babysitter in the regiment now?” Sikes almost laughed.

“Don’t knock it,” Powell warned. “Counter-terrorism experience in Germany counts for a lot nowadays.”

“Yeah, ‘cause they let all the fuckin’ terrorists in!” Blaczynski grunted. Powell held up his hand.

“Ours not to worry about the politics, mate. Besides, that’s all ancient history now. Baseball an’ Horse were still suckin’ tit an’ shittin’ themselves back then.”

“Last week?” Murray joked. There was brotherly jeering and laughter, which Adam rolled his eyes and tolerated, though he reached over and pulled the much smaller man into an affectionate crushing hug. Even Powell chuckled along.

“Anyhow, that’s the potted summary,” he finished. “I’m sure AEC’ll be sendin’ us a fookin’ tome to pore over once the idea’s got Tremblay’s scribble on the bottom, and we’ll have to somehow find room to squeeze ‘em in on the base, but I reckon it’s a sign that the Powers That Be think we’re doin’ summat right-…” he turned and frowned as the phone in his newly-set-up office rang.

“…’Course, there’s never a dull moment is there? Save me a steak, lads…” He put his drink down and vanished.

Steak…

Among his many, many talents, Christian Firth was the undisputed grandmaster of cooking the perfect steak. He had it down to something that was equal parts science and art. Several arts--he was the symphonic sultan of searing, the baron of browning, the Maharaja of Medium Rare. Firth could cook a steak that made every vegan in a thousand meter radius have a crisis of faith.

Of course, like everything he was good at, he knew he was good at it and took pride in being not merely good, but the best. He also promised to smash any bottles of steak sauce he laid eyes on.

He vanished outside with promises to excel himself and confident declarations about how the steaks were prepared and ready, how the grill was perfect, and so on. Adam--whose stomach ranked second or third on his list of his favorite organs--had to resist the urge to drool. He joined in the chatter and banter half-heartedly, keeping an eye out the glass doors as he watched the master work and vowed that one day, one day he would complete his studies under the sensei of sizzle.

In short order the meat was seared, flipped, seared, probed, whipped out of the fire and rested. The Knife--and it was always The Knife, with capital letters--was produced, whisked briskly across the steel, and the rested beef was efficiently sliced into juicy glistening pinkish strips and laid out in a row like the croupier in a James Bond movie dealing the flop.

Beaming the fearsome grin of a man who knew he’d outdone himself, Firth reverently delivered his creation to his waiting comrades, and it was at that precise moment that the day decided to really kick Adam solidly in the balls.

“Okay lads, party’s over! We’ve got a fookin’ mission…”

Date Point 10y10m2w3d AV
HMS Valiant, En route to Crzlrfek System, The Freedom Stars

Technical Sergeant Martina Kovač

“…But you still got to eat the steak, right?”

“Well yeah, but by the time Stainless had finished briefing us it had gone cold!”

“It was still good though, right?”

“But it wasn’t as good!"

Marty gave him a stern look as she closed up Titan’s life support pack and handed it to one of the suit techs. “Well gee wiz, I’m so sorry about the pea in your fifty mattresses, princess.”

Adam’s eyebrows came down in the specific frown he used whenever a reference went over his head. “Huh?”

“…Fuck a duck,” Marty grunted, feeling a little disgusted in him. “You don’t even know that story?"

“Is this that Kipling guy again?”

“Is it-? No! No it’s not! Jesus!”

Now came his other expression, which was much the same as might be worn by a scolded puppy that wasn’t sure what it had done wrong but was very sorry nevertheless. Marty knew that it was completely guileless and un-malicious but with nine suit life support units to prep and sign off on, she was not in the mood right now.

“I should read that stuff, huh?” he asked.

“What you should do is let me concentrate, or do you have a sudden fetish for breathing CO2 that you never told me about?"

Scolded-puppy turned into kicked-puppy and he muttered something affirmative and went to check his mission gear again, leaving Martina to feel a touch guilty. Only a touch though--he really should know better than to distract her during the most critical phase of suit assembly.

For fuck’s sake, he was an intelligent guy, too! In fact when he was in his element, he was a genius. She wouldn’t have looked at him twice if he’d been genuinely as dumb as he sometimes acted, but when he was being dumb, he was dumb.

It wasn’t just the literature thing. Honestly, she could forgive him for not knowing his Rudyard Kipling from his Hans Christian Andersen: Something about his life story suggested that bedtime stories had not featured in the daily routine of little Adam Ares, whereas Martina’s father had first read ‘Rikki Tikki Tavi’ to her at the age of four.

It was the sheer number and size of his blind spots that bothered her. She’d once seen him deliberately but with seeming innocence change course and tap an apparently random guy on the shoulder. He’d shaken his head and the guy had gone pale and made himself scarce. She’d asked him why, and Adam had stated with perfect confidence that the guy was stalking an ex-girlfriend, and had pointed out the oblivious gal in question.

He had a strange kind of interpersonal hyperopia that he seemed chronically unable to diagnose. He could spot somebody else’s creepy stalker ex from thirty yards away on a crowded street and yet still be completely blind to his own faulty behaviour. It was a conundrum. One that a degree of academic education that shamed most physicians had done absolutely nothing to equip her for solving.

Speaking of which…

She forced him out of her thoughts and directed her attention fully onto what she was doing. Nine valuable lives were in her hands, this was no time to allow herself to be distracted. What they were going into could plausibly become dangerous enough anyway, they damn well weren’t going to get hurt because of her.

The job was not being helped by the cramped confines of HMS Valiant’s tiny flight deck where the Techs were working butt-to-butt, elbow-to-elbow and by leaning around one another. If ’Horse hadn’t needed to be present so Hargreaves and Doyle could sew him into his undersuit, in fact, she’d have told him to get the hell off the deck and make some room.

The crowding problem got even more acute when Major Powell bustled in from the direction of the CIC.

“Fall in, lads.” He lifted his voice above the hubbub without shouting, a neat trick that Martina wished she could do. She listened with half an ear as she checked the catalyst baffles in the next pack.

He looked strangely happy about something as the operators gathered round. “So. AEC’s worried that if we just grab the HVT clean and pleasant-like, we’ll have the Dominion callin’ on us every time they smell Celzi. So, we’ve been authorised, nay encouraged, to go full ham on this one.”

Feral grins all round welcomed this pronouncement.

“Now obviously we’re not monsters, and we’ll damn well remember the Law of Armed Combat, but we’re settin’ out to completely fookin’ terrify the leadership on both sides. If we do it right we might just persuade the Celzi to settle the fook down, and the Dominion to think twice before they call us. That means the officers get no mercy. Spare the conscripts if you can so long as they don’t try an’ be a stupid bloody hero, but today’s our day to give the Dominion and the Alliance a demonstration in just how dangerous we really are. Understood?"

There were “Yes sir!“s from the Lads, and several of the techs traded knowing looks and got out of their way as best they could in the crowded space to let them really get in the warrior headspace.

Marty had… got used to seeing them like this. When the adrenaline started pounding and the testosterone started flowing, they let themselves fall into an older, more sanguine place where the killers lived.

The first time she’d seen it, she’d learned of a new and hitherto unsuspected kind of machismo. A strangely silent one that had nothing to do with noise or posturing, and everything to do with contact. Body contact, eye contact, contact between brother souls. It was quiet, and intimate in a way that she knew she would never experience but was entirely certain she never wanted to.

She could watch their eyes harden and cool as they committed to their professional personas. Like watching a knife emerge from its soft leather sheath, something cold and deadly emerged from under the kind barriers they put up both to protect it and to protect from it.

She was used to seeing them this way… but when The Lads, whom she cared for both personally and professionally, stepped back from themselves and became weapons instead then it was hard not to be a little scared for them.

And hard not to feel sorry for the ETs they were about to unleash themselves on.

Date Point 10y10m2w3d AV
Hyperbolic trajectory, Crzlrfek System, The Freedom Stars

HUGINN ONE

“Valiant says T minus two mikes.”

“Copy that.”

Ten percent of lightspeed was a useful balance point. It was slow enough to be feasibly reached by a ship using some tricky warp field manipulations, and yet by the standards of any physical system it was absurdly fast, far too fast for any realistic interception that wasn’t warp-based in its own right. It was slow enough that the gamma-t was so tiny as to only matter to the computers, which could compensate, and far above the escape velocity of the Crzlrfek system’s obese orange star.

Most importantly, however, it was enough to give absolutely any object no matter how light an incredible amount of kinetic energy… and the General Electric GAU-8/S Equalizer mounted on a Firebird could fire seventy “objects” a second.

Dominion and Alliance naval doctrine both stressed the value of directed energy-on-target. In this regard, a Firebird coasting on a hyperbolic orbit at a tenth of lightspeed was the indisputable king.

But of course, from several light-hours away, all of that firepower was worthless.

“One mike.”

“Copy.”

Of course, this particular maneuver had never been attempted for real. For all they knew they were about to run smack into some kind of overpowered alien forcefield gizmo with much the same consequences as were felt by insects that strayed onto a highway.

It would all happen so fast that the pilots and their WSOs on HUGINNs one and two, and their comrades providing eyes over on MUNINN ONE and MUNINN TWO, would get only the swiftest impression of the incredible energies they were about to unleash. Everything had been calculated down to the millisecond.

“Ten seconds. Til Valhal!”

“Oorah!”

Silence before the violence.

Three…

Two..

One.

Date Point 10y10m2w3d AV
Crzlrfek System, The Freedom Stars

Alpha of the Brood Of A Million Teeth

The Alpha was forced to replay the sensor data in extreme slow motion to make sense of what it had witnessed, and on doing so it utterly forgot to guard its thoughts.

<Stunned awe; disbelief>

It rewound the data and played it again, even slower. There was the knot of defensive batteries that had frustrated it for several days. Four space stations spread out in a line, placed so that when the prize they guarded was not beneath them, it was beneath some other bodyguard of orbital batteries. Any ship that decloaked near them was inviting immediate obliteration.

Hunters hated to abandon a Hunt, but the Alpha was old and wily and knew better than to let pride get it killed. So it had sat, and watched, and waited for a window of opportunity. It had been on the verge of deciding that there would never be such a window.

And then the batteries had been destroyed.

The timing of it was what stunned the Alpha the most. There was a strong ping on the FTL wake sensors far out in the system’s outer halo, as of a few small ship approaching at incredible apparent speeds.

So fast, in fact, that their FTL transit lasted for less than a second. They had landed doing a respectable proportion of the universal causality limit, and had departed again at those same savage FTL speeds… but in their wake they had left a cloud of dumb kinetic projectiles that flashed through the defense satellites’ orbit with enough fierce energy that each one that struck home released the kind of energy normally only seen in fission warheads. The four defense stations ceased to exist before they even properly knew that they were under attack.

For any Hunter, witnessing violence on such an overwhelming scale was practically a religious experience, but the attackers had only made their first opening move. The strike craft must have dropped jump beacons as they came in, because the sky was suddenly full of ships.

And what ships! Small, dark, so sleek that the probing radiation of the ground batteries as they tried to get a lock just slid off like water on oiled steel. The tormented and rippling fabric of space twisted some more and disgorged metal rods that were already falling on precise re-entry trajectories that would drill them hard into the reinforced fabric of the ground facility that the Alpha had pondered for so long. Anything unfortunate enough to be caught beneath that tungsten rain was doomed.

It spun around and began to issue commands with all the fervour it had. <Exultation; Glee> +Humans! The humans are here! This is our chance! Ready the brood for battle!+

The Brood Of A Million Fangs did not fear defeat, nor death. They existed for violence, and violence had come to them and exposed its throat.

They would bite, they would fight, and even if they all died, they would live.

+MEAT TO THE MAW!!!+

Date Point 10y10m2w3d AV
Falling towards the ground, planet Crzlrfek, Crzlrfek System, The Freedom Stars

STAINLESS

EV-MASS was a spacesuit, and that meant glare protection to guard the eyes from maybe having to look toward the sun without even the meager protection of atmosphere. That meant that when a dozen bright flares lit up below them as the RFG strikes hit, Stainless didn’t even blink.

Nor did Starfall. “VALIANT, STARFALL. Orbital strike on target, well hit.”

Plummeting toward the ground with no parachute, and he still managed to make the report with perfect ice coolness. It was no less than Stainless expected of him, but he still couldn’t help but feel impressed. The HELLNO jump-- Baseball’s nickname for it had stuck even though none of them could come up with a suitable backronym--wasn’t exactly a stress-free situation, especially when they hit the tropopause and fell into boiling air.

“Angels Twenty.”

That was Rebar, watching their altitude. They could all see it, but Exo- Atmospheric Reentry jumps had a protocol now. They all remembered what had happened to Sergeant Stevenson.

The dust was clearing, and Stainless had a good view of the compound below. A lot of it was collapsed, on fire or both but he could see what looked like two breaches into the tunnels and basements that were the bulk of the facility.

“REBAR, HIGHLAND, STARFALL, TITAN and WARHORSE will land north east corner of the courtyard,” he declared. “RIGHTEOUS, SNAPFIRE, BASEBALL and STAINLESS will land south side. Remember, spare the conscripts if you can.”

“Angels Three, pop ’em!"

They hit their EAR field emitter controls and the protective cocoon of forcefields that had shielded them from the searing plasma of re-entry found a new shape. Wide invisible wings of nothing but electrostatic wizardry zipped out around them and arrested their fall until they were coming in no harder than an ordinary parachute descent and without the awkward flapping mass of a ’chute to control and shed once they were on the ground.

They hit the ground running with their weapons up and leading the way. It seemed nobody who had been unfortunate enough to stand outdoors during the bombardment was left alive: The overpressure had pulped them. Thank God for their helmets, because the smell must have been incredible.

Righteous led the way through the southern breach into the complex’s basements, his gun spoke a rhyming triplet, and they followed in after him.

If the target thought he’d seen overwhelming force already, he was sorely mistaken.

Date Point 10y10m2w3d AV
Celzi Alliance command facility, Crzlrfek System, The Freedom Stars

Warmaster Trez Ekrat

Ekrat had always thought the stories about humans were exaggerations. The stories of them bounding across the battlefield and slaying Vulza single- handedly were exaggerations. They had to be. Didn’t they?

But those stories were nothing next to the reality. There were nine humans loose in his compound, and they were death. They ignored the wounded, the dying and the cowardly but if any of Ekrat’s soldiers raised a weapon then that soldier died with neither mercy nor cruelty. Kinetic pulse fire fluttered harmlessly against them like paper on the wind.

A force of nature was coming for him and he had no idea how to stop it. He had no idea how it had even happened. His orbital defenses had simply vanished, scoured out of the sky with a contemptuous swipe of some unknowably powerful weapon. His ground fortifications had been smashed flat and now annihilation was sweeping through his facility and there was nothing he could do about it.

Nothing except gather his dignity and wait. He watched on the screen as his best Celzi commandos sprang an ambush on the humans that achieved exactly nothing. The thickly armored deathworlder whom they targeted just ignored five heavy pulse guns smacking into him, and pounced.

Ekrat had to look away. It was sickening to know that something was coming for him that could do that so easily.

He spared a last despairing once-over for his instruments and froze.

If what his instruments were telling him was accurate, then the humans suddenly didn’t seem so bad.

Date Point 10y10m2w3d AV
HMS Violent, orbiting planet Crzlrfek, Crzlrfek System, The Freedom Stars

Commodore William Caruthers

“…Now just where in the bloody hell did they come from?"

It was a strangely calm question to ask of a hunter Broodship, and Caruthers had asked it in an almost distracted way.

“They were tailing the defense platforms, cloaked… It looks like they’re ignoring us and going for the ground facility.”

“Smart. They must know by now that they can’t catch our ships so they’ve chosen the easier prey… Send a couple of Firebirds over there to kill the bastards, would you?”

“Yes sir… They’ve already launched their raiding shuttles.”

“Hmm. Is there any hope of intercepting all of them?”

“Not likely, sir. The Broodship is screening for them. I think they’re sacrificing it.”

“Hmm.”

Caruthers stood up and considered. The problem that the larger ship presented by screening the smaller ones was that it had sown gravity spikes around it which rendered the superluminal guns effectively useless. At those ranges the rounds were so impossibly slow that the slightest powered deflection by the Hunter ship would result in an outright miss. The Firebirds were going to have to attack from a circuitous angle, too. The master of that particular ship was a wily one.

And either fearless or suicidal. The Hunters had to know what they were up against here, surely?

He got on comms. “STAINLESS, RED SHIELD. We just had a Hunter broodship decloak up here and it’s already sending shuttles your way. What’s your status?”

Powell’s reply was about ten seconds in coming, and when it did he sounded terse. More so than usual. “RED SHIELD, STAINLESS. Copy that. HVT secured alive. Request Hearthstone.”

For whatever reason, that particular brevity code always generated some amusement even in tense situations. Hearthstone was the quick way home for the Operators: deploy their portable jump array, set it to self-destruct once they were all through, and ride a wormhole to their preprogrammed destination.

Caruthers wasn’t sure what was so funny about it.

In any case, it was a sensible call. The fleet had orbital superiority but that was going to be of precious little use when all those Hunter shuttles touched down and disgorged their passengers, and there were a lot of shuttles. The SOR were more than a match for any Hunter, but numbers could provide all the mass the cannibalistic alien freaks needed to overwhelm them.

“Copy, STAINLESS. Hearthstone authorized.”

And that was that. A tense and humming kind of quiet suffused the CIC, broken only by precise updates and the susurrus that fell on any ship during a calm interlude in the fighting.

They had done all they could: everything was out of their hands now.

Date Point 10y10m2w3d AV
Celzi Alliance command facility, Crzlrfek System, The Freedom Stars

Warhorse

Hunters could be shockingly fast. In the minutes since the freakshow had landed on them, the greasy alien fucks had flooded through the base like water.

To which the appropriate response was to flood back. You didn’t try and dam the tide or stand in front of it like a rock, because that just got you washed away. You applied firepower, and you moved.

’Horse’s armor had already stopped one hit. Some big fat heavy Hunter round had skipped off the concrete wall he’d been using for cover and struck his arm at a shallow angle. He had some ammo left, he had some grenades left. He knew exactly how many, but numbers didn’t enter into it. Thought didn’t enter into it: the knowledge was just there.

Reality was simple: Aggression versus aggression. Move. Kill. Get target. Move. Find team. Leave. Warhorse was not a thinking man at that moment: He was a Brother, among Brothers, grappling with evil in the dark.

Muscle memory, animal impulse, Mission: get target. Move. Hunters in the way? Kill. Clear the obstacle. Secure the flank. The thought was there, but the words only came when needed. Otherwise, he lived in a place of blood and rocks and splintered bones that men had known long before fire or the wheel had come along to paint them with a brittle veneer of civilization.

Warhorse was a killer, Hunters were weak. Puny. Red Hunter, ambush. Too close, teeth and claws. Tackle, stomp, check target. Target secure, keep moving.

Explosion.

Dizzy for a moment. Roll to cover, check limbs, check weapon, check brothers. Check target.

“Fuck!”

The Celzi was a crumpled mess. Off-color alien blood was oozing out of at least three of his eyes, and he really wasn’t supposed to bend that way. He was still trying to breathe, but…

Warhorse stepped back and Adam, the medic, stepped into his place. This was a moment for the rational human brain to step in, the bit that was more than intuition and trained operant conditioning.

But he was still assessing for triage when a white disk the size of a poker chip landed in front of him, flashing yellow. Both he and Murray were in the nervejam’s lethal radius.

Warhorse took over again.

Grab brother.

MOVE.

++END CHAPTER 32++